<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<news>
	<whatsnew><id>042720110628123260042878557747</id><date>04/28/2011</date><article>Significant updates have been made to the Pipelines field in the Transportation category.</article></whatsnew><whatsnew><id>041920111259294140925700109131</id><date>04/21/2011</date><article>Did you know that there are more member "countries" of the International Olympic Committee than there are member countries of the UN? (The former includes a number of autonomous or semi-autonomous territories, dependencies, and areas of special sovereignty.) To find out just what countries compose each of these organizations, visit Appendix B.</article></whatsnew><whatsnew><id>040620111423311000562650507141</id><date>04/08/2011</date><article>The Indian Ocean island entity of Mayotte became an overseas department of France on 31 March. The change in status makes it an integral part of France and so its description is now included in the France country profile.</article></whatsnew><whatsnew><id>032320111423041100185390096625</id><date>03/25/2011</date><article>What country was formerly named Upper Volta? Find out by checking Appendix F (Cross-Reference List of Geographic Names).</article></whatsnew><whatsnew><id>031520110849373280742747229952</id><date>03/18/2011</date><article>Japan's strongest-ever earthquake, and an accompanying tsunami, recently devastated northeast Japan, killing thousands and damaging several nuclear power plants. The "Economic overview" for Japan presents a preliminary survey of the calamitous situation.</article></whatsnew><whatsnew><id>030820110902587480887360702642</id><date>03/10/2011</date><article>What country has the longest system of waterways - navigable rivers and canals - in the world? Go to the References tab/ Country Comparison/ Waterways to find out. In the Transportation section, both the "Waterways" and "Roadways" entries have been updated. New photos introduced for Egypt.</article></whatsnew><whatsnew>
		<id>030220110634451110225597534727</id>
		<date>03/02/2011</date>
		<article>What country has three megacites with populations of greater than 15 million? (No, it's not China.) Now you can find out
			the size of a country's four largest cities, as well as its capital, in the new &amp;quot;Major cities - population&amp;quot;
			field, in the People section of a country entry. See the Definitions and Notes, under the References tab, to get the exact breakdown
			on what is included in this new field.</article>
	</whatsnew>
	<whatsnew>
		<id>022220110843158670835548769783</id>
		<date>02/24/2011</date>
		<article>Did you know that the developing world increased its estimated share of worldwide mobile-cellular subscriptions from roughly
			35% at the beginning of the decade to nearly 75% in 2010? All of the telephone-related fields, as well as all of the population
			entries, have been updated with the latest data.</article>
	</whatsnew>
	<whatsnew>
		<id>0216201107221715100191241820422</id>
		<date>02/16/2011</date>
		<article>The 2011 Factbook cover has been unveiled in the Gallery of Covers under the References tab! While you are there, find
			out what year The World Factbook first featured a color cover.</article>
	</whatsnew>
	<whatsnew>
		<id>012620111227502030142630267306</id>
		<date>02/02/2011</date>
		<article>What do the initials ESA stand for? Check out 'Appendix A: Abbreviations' to find out. New space-based photos have been
			uploaded for Australia, China, Namibia, Mexico, and the US.</article>
	</whatsnew>
	<whatsnew>
		<id>01202011063439807066606480254</id>
		<date>01/25/2011</date>
		<article>What country enjoyed the lowest unemployment rate in 2010? Find out by checking "Unemployment rate" under the Country
			Comparison feature (in the References tab). The entire Economy category has been updated to reflect data for years 2010 and earlier.</article>
	</whatsnew>
	<whatsnew>
		<id>011220110832321380481830595764</id>
		<date>01/14/2011</date>
		<article>Did you know that the highest elevation in the Netherlands is not in Europe? Where is it? Find out by checking the &amp;quot;Elevation
			extremes&amp;quot; field in the Geography section. New space-based photos have been added for Iran and Russia.</article>
	</whatsnew>
	<whatsnew>
		<id>01052011145419675077765876682</id>
		<date>01/07/2011</date>
		<article>What country flag is only one color? To find out visit the Flags of the World page.</article>
	</whatsnew>
	<whatsnew>
		<id>12282010081130330064877506922</id>
		<date>12/30/2010</date>
		<article>What airport handles the most passengers annually? Find out by going to the World entry, Transportation category, "Airports" field,
			and locating the top ten airports by passengers and by cargo.</article>
	</whatsnew>
	<whatsnew>
		<id>122120100952134060559708733915</id>
		<date>12/23/2010</date>
		<article>If it's noon in Washington, DC, what time is it in Nairobi, Kenya? The answer may be found in the Government section,
			under "Capital," where the time difference is specified. New photos from Kenya have been uploaded.</article>
	</whatsnew>
	<whatsnew>
		<id>121420101050237430643528531027</id>
		<date>12/17/2010</date>
		<article>How many rare earth elements (REEs) are there? Find the answer in the "Definitions and Notes" (below the References tab).
			These critical elements, necessary in so many of today's high-tech industries, are now listed in the "Natural resources" field,
			under Geography, for countries that are producing REEs or initializing mining operations (including Australia, China, Russia,
			South Africa, and the US).</article>
	</whatsnew>
	<whatsnew>
		<id>120820101212458640388094131311</id>
		<date>12/10/2010</date>
		<article>Quick! What's the national anthem of Australia? Now you can find the name, lyricist, composer, and additional basic anthem
			info for every country in the world by visiting the new "National anthems" field in the Government section of the Factbook.</article>
	</whatsnew>
	<whatsnew>
		<id>112320100857438010360671742649</id>
		<date>11/30/2010</date>
		<article>Since 2004, The World Factbook Web site has been updated on a bi-weekly schedule. Culminating a three-month trial effort,
			we are pleased to announce that the Factbook will now be updated on a weekly basis.</article>
	</whatsnew>
	<whatsnew>
		<id>11162010143105431022953443033</id>
		<date>11/19/2010</date>
		<article>Significant updates entered under the People, Government, and Communications categories.</article>
	</whatsnew>
	<whatsnew>
		<id>110920101125514120600765732976</id>
		<date>11/11/2010</date>
		<article>In the Geography category, a new subfield, "volcanism," has been added under the "Natural hazards" field for countries
			with historically active volcanoes. The Economy section has been updated to reflect the most recent data for 2009 and earlier
			years.</article>
	</whatsnew>
	<whatsnew>
		<id>110320101516598390366802056799</id>
		<date>11/05/2010</date>
		<article>In the Economy category, the "Oil - exports," "Oil - imports," "Oil - proved reserves," and "Natural gas - proved reserves" fields
			have been updated with the most recent estimates available.</article>
	</whatsnew>
	<whatsnew>
		<id>102720101224396200219665293615</id>
		<date>10/29/2010</date>
		<article>In the People category, significant updates have been made to the "School life expectancy" and "Education expenditures" fields.
			In the Economy category, the "Stock of domestic credit" field has been updated to include data for 2009. In addition, the definition
			has been expanded to include credit provided by all financial institutions, not just banks, as had been The World Factbook practice
			until now. For some countries this change significantly broadens the coverage.</article>
	</whatsnew>
	<whatsnew>
		<id>102120100641444710963630254754</id>
		<date>10/22/2010</date>
		<article>The dissolution of the Netherlands Antilles has resulted in two new World Factbook entries: the autonomous entities of
			Curacao and Sint Maarten (the remaining three islands - Bonaire, Saba, and Sint Eustatius - have joined the Netherlands as special
			municipalities). The number of entities in The World Factbook now stands at 267.</article>
	</whatsnew>
	<whatsnew>
		<id>101220101209101210915735426356</id>
		<date>10/13/2010</date>
		<article>In the Economy category, the "Stock of money" and "Stock of quasi money" fields have been updated and renamed as "Stock
			of narrow money" and "Stock of broad money" in keeping with the International Monetary Fund's new presentation of monetary data.
			This new format provides greater standardization of reporting and permits more consistent comparisons across countries. Please
			see "Definitions and Notes" (under the References tab) for descriptions of the new fields.</article>
	</whatsnew>
	<whatsnew>
		<id>100620100914087060906963726734</id>
		<date>10/08/2010</date>
		<article>In the Communications category, the "Internet hosts" field has been updated with 2010 data; significant updates entered
			in the Geography, Government, and Military categories.</article>
	</whatsnew>
	<whatsnew>
		<id>092920101034121430113183370222</id>
		<date>10/01/2010</date>
		<article>In the Transportation category, the &amp;quot;Merchant marine&amp;quot; field has been updated with the latest available
			data; substantial updates also entered in fields of the Government and Economy categories.</article>
	</whatsnew>
	<whatsnew>
		<id>092220101345487030751950492614</id>
		<date>09/24/2010</date>
		<article>In the Economy category, new data have been added for 2009 in the fields for "Central bank discount rate" and "Commercial
			bank prime lending rate."</article>
	</whatsnew>
	<whatsnew>
		<id>091520100731471110419994411444</id>
		<date>09/17/2010</date>
		<article>In the Transportation category, the "Roadways" field has been updated with the latest available data; significant updates
			also entered in fields of the Government and Military categories.</article>
	</whatsnew>
	<whatsnew>
		<id>091320100913143420748188674978</id>
		<date>09/13/2010</date>
		<article>In the Government category, the amplification of flag descriptions - to include explanations of colors and symbols - has
			been completed for all of the country entries.</article>
	</whatsnew>
	<whatsnew>
		<id>090120100934407760417308207171</id>
		<date>09/03/2010</date>
		<article>In addition to various population, governmental, and military updates, new photos have been added for Burma, Canada, Poland,
			the United Kingdom, and the United States.</article>
	</whatsnew>
	<whatsnew>
		<id>081620100835541270198521686131</id>
		<date>08/23/2010</date>
		<article>In the Communications category, the former "Radio broadcast stations" and "Television broadcast stations" entries have
			been replaced by a new "Broadcast media" field that provides information on the approximate number of public and private TV and
			radio stations in a country, as well as basic information on the availability of satellite and cable TV services. Malawi's recently
			unveiled new flag may be viewed either in the Flags of the World link or under the Malawi country entry. In the Economy category,
			GDP statistics have been updated and revised.</article>
	</whatsnew>
	<whatsnew>
		<id>080420101441252850969884920849</id>
		<date>08/06/2010</date>
		<article>In the Transportation category, the "Airports," "Airports - with paved runways," "Airports with unpaved runways," and "Heliports" fields
			have all been updated with the latest available data.</article>
	</whatsnew>
	<whatsnew>
		<id>072820101159475040301391781887</id>
		<date>07/29/2010</date>
		<article>The "International Court of Justice (ICJ)" entry listed under International Organizations and Groups in Appendix B has
			been expanded considerably and now includes countries adherent to jurisdiction. Several fields in the Economy category covering
			trade as well as oil and natural gas have been updated with the latest available annual data.</article>
	</whatsnew>
	<whatsnew>
		<id>072120100713034290584256674826</id>
		<date>07/23/2010</date>
		<article>Under the References tab, in the Definitions and Notes, the entry for &amp;quot;Legal system&amp;quot; has been significantly
			expanded; it now includes descriptions, origins, and features of the most common legal systems.</article>
	</whatsnew>
	<whatsnew>
		<id>06242010064955924035155904457</id>
		<date>07/01/2010</date>
		<article>Many fields in the Economy category have been updated with the latest available annual data, including &amp;quot;Labor
			force,&amp;quot; &amp;quot;Unemployment rate,&amp;quot; &amp;quot;Budget - revenues and expenditures,&amp;quot; &amp;quot;Public
			debt,&amp;quot; &amp;quot;Inflation rate,&amp;quot; &amp;quot;Current account balance,&amp;quot; &amp;quot;Exports,&amp;quot; &amp;quot;Imports,&amp;quot; &amp;quot;Reserves
			of foreign exchange,&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;Direct foreign investment.&amp;quot;</article>
	</whatsnew>
	<whatsnew>
		<id>061720100640084410794784447877</id>
		<date>06/18/2010</date>
		<article>The fields in the Economy category for "Stock of money," "Stock of quasi-money," "and "Market value of publicly traded
			shares" have been updated with the latest available data.</article>
	</whatsnew>
	<whatsnew>
		<id>060220101137191570165963807735</id>
		<date>06/04/2010</date>
		<article>Significant updates entered under the Government, Economy, and Military categories. The Country Comparisons function now
			also appears in the 'World' entry to allow users to quickly view how countries rank in 58 different Factbook fields.</article>
	</whatsnew>
	<whatsnew>
		<id>051720101423116830483365295843</id>
		<date>05/21/2010</date>
		<article>Dozens of new photos uploaded for Central and Eastern European countries, most notably Bosnia and Herzegovina, Georgia,
			Latvia, Poland, and Russia.</article>
	</whatsnew>
	<whatsnew>
		<id>0504201007111080200666977232706</id>
		<date>05/07/2010</date>
		<article>Major updates made to fields in the People, Government, and Military categories. New photos appear under China, Romania,
			and Ukraine.</article>
	</whatsnew>
	<whatsnew>
		<id>042020101137168360394157653894</id>
		<date>04/23/2010</date>
		<article>The 'World' entry continues to accrue "top ten" rankings; recent additions in the Geography category include the world's
			ten highest mountains and largest islands. The Transportation category lists the top ten airports (both by passengers and cargo)
			and container ports, as well as the ten longest rivers.</article>
	</whatsnew>
	<whatsnew>
		<id>040720100949422120553534391716</id>
		<date>04/09/2010</date>
		<article>The ongoing expansion of flag descriptions - to also include explanations of colors and symbols - is now complete for
			over two-thirds of the Factbook entries.</article>
	</whatsnew>
	<whatsnew>
		<id>031820100940268240955821257183</id>
		<date>03/26/2010</date>
		<article>The fields in the Economy category have been updated with the latest available data. New photos introduced for the World,
			the Holy See (Vatican City), and the Philippines.</article>
	</whatsnew>
	<whatsnew>
		<id>0303201011321489100456469358578</id>
		<date>03/05/2010</date>
		<article>In the Government category, a link to the World Leaders website under the "Executive branch: cabinet" entry allows users
			to find a listing of a country's major officials.</article>
	</whatsnew>
	<whatsnew>
		<id>02182010070708170417035986775</id>
		<date>02/19/2010</date>
		<article>Significant updates introduced in the Government, Communications, and Transportation categories. New photos appear under
			France and Germany.</article>
	</whatsnew>
	<whatsnew>
		<id>012120101256217240529125515209</id>
		<date>01/26/2010</date>
		<article>In the Economy category, information has been updated and now covers the year 2009. New photos added for Egypt and Italy.</article>
	</whatsnew>
	<whatsnew>
		<id>010620100943061340152420780981</id>
		<date>01/08/2010</date>
		<article>The introductory Background statements have been updated or revised for dozens of countries. New images introduced for
			Argentina, China, the Czech Republic, South Africa, Svalbard, and Turkey.</article>
	</whatsnew>
	<whatsnew>
		<id>120120091344353490713058407652</id>
		<date>12/04/2009</date>
		<article>In addition to various governmental and military updates, new photos have been introduced for Germany, Greenland, Italy,
			Malaysia, Maldives, and the United Kingdom.</article>
	</whatsnew>
	<whatsnew>
		<id>111020091106144730133136650091</id>
		<date>11/13/2009</date>
		<article>Recent elections and governmental changes recorded for Afghanistan, Aruba, Fiji, Germany, Haiti, Marshall Islands, Mongolia,
			Tunisia, and Uruguay. In the Economy category, some 20 macro-economic fields have been updated with the latest data. New NASA
			space photos added for the Atlantic, Indian, and Pacific Oceans, as well as for Montserrat and the World; new ground photos added
			for Cambodia, France, and Luxembourg.</article>
	</whatsnew>
	<whatsnew>
		<id>1028200914035137046967698531</id>
		<date>10/30/2009</date>
		<article>In the Economy category, all the energy-related fields have been updated with the latest data; new photos added for Norway
			and Poland.</article>
	</whatsnew>
	<whatsnew>
		<id>10132009074653349042323525165</id>
		<date>10/14/2009</date>
		<article>In addition to regular informational updates, new photos have been added for Denmark, Estonia, Finland, Russia, and Sweden.</article>
	</whatsnew>
	<whatsnew>
		<id>092920090840004830341220113796</id>
		<date>10/02/2009</date>
		<article>In the Transportation category, updates have been made to the "Airports" and "Heliports" fields; new photos added for
			Libya, Turkey, and the United Kingdom.</article>
	</whatsnew>
	<whatsnew>
		<id>091620090733432060587700685965</id>
		<date>09/17/2009</date>
		<article>NASA images taken from space have been introduced to enhance various country photo presentations. Significant numbers
			of high altitude photos appear under China, Egypt, Spain, Australia, and New Zealand, but can also be found scattered among other
			country entries. In the Economy category, statistics for "Distribution of family income - Gini index," "Public debt," and "Debt
			- external" now include two year's worth of data.</article>
	</whatsnew>
	<whatsnew>
		<id>083120090757105070643309741874</id>
		<date>09/03/2009</date>
		<article>In the Economy category, statistics for "Current Account Balance,"  "Exports," "Imports," "Reserves of foreign exchange
			and gold," "Stock of direct foreign investment - at home," and "Stock of direct foreign investment - abroad"  now include two
			year's worth of data; statistics for "Market value of publicly traded shares" now include three year's worth of data. New photos
			added for Austria, France, Monaco, Netherlands, and Netherlands Antilles.</article>
	</whatsnew>
	<whatsnew>
		<id>081720090630144670540828820855</id>
		<date>08/17/2009</date>
		<article>Various rail gauge line lengths have been updated for all countries in the Railways entry; selected economic and political
			entries also updated.</article>
	</whatsnew>
	<whatsnew>
		<id>091020090657251340306365298729</id>
		<date>07/31/2009</date>
		<article>In the Economy category, statistics for "Central bank discount rate," "Commercial bank prime lending rate," "Stock of
			money," "Stock of quasi money," and "Stock of domestic credit" now include two year's worth of data.</article>
	</whatsnew>
	<whatsnew>
		<id>071620090630144670540828820854</id>
		<date>07/20/2009</date>
		<article>Latest updates include changes to the chief of state or head of government in Bosnia and Herzegovina, Croatia, Lithuania,
			and Panama. New photographs have been added for Spain, Portugal, Gibraltar, and South Africa.</article>
	</whatsnew>
	<whatsnew>
		<id>063020091006377560887509915432</id>
		<date>07/01/2009</date>
		<article>With the launch of the new Web site, the former "Rank Order" function was renamed "Country Comparisons." The link to Country
			Comparisons may be found under the References tab. &#xd;
			In addition, many of the regional reference maps now incorporate both elevation and vegetation on landmasses, and bathymetry
			for ocean areas. Statistics for "Unemployment rate" and "Inflation rate (consumer prices)" now include two year's worth of data.</article>
	</whatsnew>
	<whatsnew>
		<id>0521200915474711200351099953137</id>
		<date>06/08/2009</date>
		<article>Completely redesigned website - presenting a cleaner look, improved navigation, and a host of added features - launched
			on the World Wide Web. Among the major enhancements are downloadable and printable photos for nearly 100 countries, a &amp;quot;Did
			You Know?&amp;quot; section explaining the impact of the Factbook around the world, and built-in world rankings for many of the
			Factbook information fields. Government sections reflect the results of recent parliamentary elections in Kuwait - where women
			were elected for the first time - and India, as well as presidential elections in Lithuania, Mongolia, Panama, and South Africa.</article>
	</whatsnew>
	<whatsnew>
		<id>0416200914170843002574888135</id>
		<date>04/27/2009</date>
		<article>Significant updates made to the People and Economy categories; statistics for "GDP - real growth rate" and "GDP - per
			capita" (at purchasing power parity) now include three year's worth of data, in 2008 dollars. The Urbanization entry under People
			expanded to include all countries.</article>
	</whatsnew>
	<whatsnew>
		<id>041620091417436550225291298801</id>
		<date>04/03/2009</date>
		<article>In addition to regular country updates, statistics for "GDP (purchasing power parity)" now include three year's worth
			of data, in 2008 dollars.</article>
	</whatsnew>
	<whatsnew>
		<id>041620091418274030524905835845</id>
		<date>03/20/2009</date>
		<article>Recent major leadership changes in Guinea-Bissau, Latvia, and Madagascar included in the Government sections of those
			countries.</article>
	</whatsnew>
	<whatsnew>
		<id>0416200914190961200274258906057</id>
		<date>03/02/2009</date>
		<article>Latest US Census Bureau figures - updating basic demographic data for all countries - entered into the database. Entries
			on religions, languages, ethnic groups, and literacy also updated.</article>
	</whatsnew>
	<whatsnew>
		<id>031920091154103570912747266801</id>
		<date>02/06/2009</date>
		<article>Country information updated across all categories. Economic data now includes 2008 estimates where available.</article>
	</whatsnew>
	<whatsnew>
		<id>031920091154401190723134651147</id>
		<date>11/05/2008</date>
		<article>In order to provide more information on the nature and global dimensions of the current financial crisis, five additional
			fields appended to the Economy category: "Central bank discount rate," "Commercial bank prime lending rate," "Stock of money," "Stock
			of quasi money," and "Stock of domestic credit."</article>
	</whatsnew>
	<whatsnew>
		<id>0319200911550699400969939538841</id>
		<date>08/06/2008</date>
		<article>In the People category, two new fields provide information on education in terms of opportunity and resources: "School
			Life Expectancy" and "Education expenditures."</article>
	</whatsnew>
	<whatsnew>
		<id>031920091155228270612273046699</id>
		<date>11/06/2007</date>
		<article>In the Geography category, two new fields focus on the vital resource of water: "Total renewable water resources" and "Freshwater
			withdrawal."</article>
	</whatsnew>
	<whatsnew>
		<id>031920091155351360542880701075</id>
		<date>10/31/2007</date>
		<article>Three new fields added to the Economy category: "Stock of direct foreign investment - abroad," "Stock of direct foreign
			investment - at home," "Market value of publicly traded shares."</article>
	</whatsnew>
	<whatsnew>
		<id>090920091501208110189990141496</id>
		<date>Ongoing</date>
		<article>Revision of some individual country maps, first introduced in the 2001 edition, continues. Several regional maps have
			been updated to reflect boundary changes and place name spelling changes.</article>
	</whatsnew>
</news>
