<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<country>
	<code>ag</code>
	<name>Algeria</name>
	<region>Africa</region>
	<background>After more than a century of rule by France, Algerians fought through much of the 1950s to achieve independence in 1962. Algeria's primary political party, the National Liberation Front (FLN), was established in 1954 as part of the struggle for independence and has largely dominated politics since. The Government of Algeria in 1988 instituted a multi-party system in response to public unrest, but the surprising first round success of the Islamic Salvation Front (FIS) in the December 1991 balloting spurred the Algerian army to intervene and postpone the second round of elections to prevent what the secular elite feared would be an extremist-led government from assuming power. The army began a crackdown on the FIS that spurred FIS supporters to begin attacking government targets, and fighting escalated into an insurgency, which saw intense violence between 1992-98 resulting in over 100,000 deaths - many attributed to indiscriminate massacres of villagers by extremists. The government gained the upper hand by the late-1990s, and FIS's armed wing, the Islamic Salvation Army, disbanded in January 2000. Abdelaziz BOUTEFLIKA, with the backing of the military, won the presidency in 1999 in an election widely viewed as fraudulent. He was reelected to a second term in 2004, and overwhelmingly won a third term in 2009 after the government amended the constitution in 2008 to remove presidential term limits. Longstanding problems continue to face BOUTEFLIKA, including large-scale unemployment, a shortage of housing, unreliable electrical and water supplies, government inefficiencies and corruption, and the continuing activities of extremist militants. The Salafist Group for Preaching and Combat (GSPC) in 2006 merged with al-Qai'da to form al-Qai'da in the Lands of the Islamic Maghreb, which has launched an ongoing series of kidnappings and bombings targeting the Algerian Government and Western interests. The Arab uprising across the Near Eastern and North African region beginning in December 2010, coupled with a sudden rise in the cost of food staples, triggered a wave of protests across Algeria during early 2011. Organizers of many of these protests included opposition political parties, labor and trade unions, and human rights organizations. The government's initial response to protester demands included lifting the 19-year state of emergency laws and temporarily cutting taxes and duties on selected food items, but demonstrators continued to attempt to organize protests. An overwhelming Algerian police response managed to contain most demonstrations with some reports of violence. In mid-April 2011, President BOUTEFLIKA said he would seek to amend the nation's constitution to reinforce representative democracy, propose changes to the election laws, and submit the proposals for national referendum.</background>
	<geo>
		<note>second-largest country in Africa (after Sudan)</note>
		<location>
			<desc>Northern Africa, bordering the Mediterranean Sea, between Morocco and Tunisia</desc>
			<coordinates>TO DO</coordinates>
		</location>
		<area>
			<total unit="sq km">2381</total>
			<land unit="sq km">2381</land>
			<water unit="sq km">0</water>
			<comparison>slightly less than 3.5 times the size of Texas</comparison>
		</area>
		<boundaries>
			<borders unit=""></borders>
			<coastline unit="km">998</coastline>
		</boundaries>
		<maritime-claims>
			<territorial unit="nm">12</territorial>
			<contiguous unit=""></contiguous>
			<economic unit=""></economic>
			<continental-shelf></continental-shelf>
		</maritime-claims>
		<climate>arid to semiarid; mild, wet winters with hot, dry summers along coast; drier with cold winters and hot summers on high plateau; sirocco is a hot, dust/sand-laden wind especially common in summer</climate>
		<terrain>mostly high plateau and desert; some mountains; narrow, discontinuous coastal plain</terrain>
		<elevation>
			<high>Tahat 3,003 m</high>
			<low>Chott Melrhir -40 m</low>
		</elevation>
		<resources>petroleum, natural gas, iron ore, phosphates, uranium, lead, zinc</resources>
		<land-use>
			<arable unit="%">3.17</arable>
			<crops unit="%">0.28</crops>
			<other unit="%">96.55</other>
		</land-use>
		<hazards>mountainous areas subject to severe earthquakes; mudslides and floods in rainy season</hazards>
		<issues>soil erosion from overgrazing and other poor farming practices; desertification; dumping of raw sewage, petroleum refining wastes, and other industrial effluents is leading to the pollution of rivers and coastal waters; Mediterranean Sea, in particular, becoming polluted from oil wastes, soil erosion, and fertilizer runoff; inadequate supplies of potable water</issues>
		<water>
			<irrigated-land unit="sq km">5700</irrigated-land>
			<renewable-water unit="cu km">14.3</renewable-water>
			<freshwater-withdrawal>
				<total unit="cu km/yr">6.07</total>
				<per-capita unit="cu m/yr">185</per-capita>
			</freshwater-withdrawal>
		</water>
		<!--
"geo": {

		"Natural hazards": "flooding is a threat in some areas of the country (e.g., parts of Jutland, along the southern coast of the island of Lolland) that are protected from the sea by a system of dikes",
		"Environment - current issues": "air pollution, principally from vehicle and power plant emissions; nitrogen and phosphorus pollution of the North Sea; drinking and surface water becoming polluted from animal wastes and pesticides",
		"Environment - international agreements": {
			"party to:": "Air Pollution, Air Pollution-Nitrogen Oxides, Air Pollution-Persistent Organic Pollutants, Air Pollution-Sulfur 85, Air Pollution-Sulfur 94, Air Pollution-Volatile Organic Compounds, Antarctic Treaty, Biodiversity, Climate Change, Climate Change-Kyoto Protocol, Desertification, Endangered Species, Environmental Modification, Hazardous Wastes, Law of the Sea, Marine Dumping, Marine Life Conservation, Ozone Layer Protection, Ship Pollution, Tropical Timber 83, Tropical Timber 94, Wetlands, Whaling",
			"signed, but not ratified:": "none of the selected agreements"
		},
		"Geography - note": "controls Danish Straits (Skagerrak and Kattegat) linking Baltic and North Seas; about one-quarter of the population lives in greater Copenhagen"

		-->
	</geo>
	<people>
		<population>
			<total>34994</total>
			<birth unit="births/1,000 population">16.69</birth>
			<death unit="deaths/1,000 population">4.69</birth>
			<migration unit=""></migration>
			<growth unit="%">1.173</growth>
		</population>
		<age-distribution unit="percent">
			<group min="0" max="14">24.2</group>
			<group min="15" max="64">70.6</group>
			<group min="65"></group>
		</age-distribution>
		<median-age unit="years">
			<total>27.6</total>
			<male>27.4</male>
			<female>27.8</female>
		</median-age>
		<urbanization>
			<urban unit="% of total population">66</urban>
			<rate unit="% annual rate of change">2.3</urban>
			<cities>ALGIERS (capital) 2.74 million; Oran 770,000 (2009)</cities>
		</urbanization>
		<sex unit="male(s)/female">
			<group name="at birth" max="0">1.05</group>
			<group name="0 to 14" min="0" max="14">1.04</group>
			<group name="15 to 64" min="15" max="64">1.02</group>
			<group name="65 and over" min="65" max="0">0.86</group>
			<group name="total" min="0">1.01</group>
		</sex>
		<infant-mortality>
			<total unit="deaths/1,000 live births">25.81</total>
			<male unit="deaths/1,000 live births">28.8</male>
			<female unit="deaths/1,000 live births">22.67</female>
		</infant-mortality>
		<life-expectancy-at-birth>
			<total unit="years">74.5</total>
			<male unit="years">72.78</male>
			<female unit="years">76.31</female>
		</life-expectancy-at-birth>
		<fertility-rate unit="1.75">children born/woman</fertility-rate>
		<hiv>
			<prevalence>0.1%; 0.1% note - no country specific models provided (2009 est.)</prevalence>
			<total>18000</total>
			<deaths>fewer than 1,000 (2009 est.)</deaths>
		</hiv>
		<infectious-disease risk="">
			<food-or-waterborne></food-or-waterborne>
			<vectorborne></vectorborne>
			<water-contact></water-contact>
		</infectious-disease>
		<drinking-water-source>[object Object]</drinking-water-source>
		<sanitation-access>[object Object]</sanitation-access>
		<nationality>
			<noun>Algerian(s)</noun>
			<adjective>Algerian</adjective>
		</nationality>
		<ethnic-groups>[object Object]</ethnic-groups>
		<religions>Sunni Muslim (state religion) 99%, Christian and Jewish 1%</religions>
		<languages>Arabic (official), French, Berber dialects</languages>
		<literacy>
			<definition>age 15 and over can read and write</definition>
			<total unit="%">69.9</total>
			<male unit="%">79.6</male>
			<female unit="%">60.1</female>
		</literacy>
		<school-expectancy unit="years">13</school-expectancy>
		<education-expenditure unit="% of GDP">4.3</school-expectancy>
	</people>
	<government>
		<country-name>
			<long>People's Democratic Republic of Algeria</long>
			<short>Algeria</short>
		</country-name>
		<dependency></dependency>
		<government-type>republic</government-type>
		<capital>
			<name>Algiers</name>
			<coordinates>36° 45' N, 3° 3' E</coordinates>
			<time-difference>UTC+1 (6 hours ahead of Washington, DC during Standard Time)</time-difference>
		</capital>
		<administrative-divisions>48 provinces (wilayat, singular - wilaya); Adrar, Ain Defla, Ain Temouchent, Alger, Annaba, Batna, Bechar, Bejaia, Biskra, Blida, Bordj Bou Arreridj, Bouira, Boumerdes, Chlef, Constantine, Djelfa, El Bayadh, El Oued, El Tarf, Ghardaia, Guelma, Illizi, Jijel, Khenchela, Laghouat, Mascara, Medea, Mila, Mostaganem, M'Sila, Naama, Oran, Ouargla, Oum el Bouaghi, Relizane, Saida, Setif, Sidi Bel Abbes, Skikda, Souk Ahras, Tamanghasset, Tebessa, Tiaret, Tindouf, Tipaza, Tissemsilt, Tizi Ouzou, Tlemcen</administrative-divisions>
		<independence>5 July 1962 (from France)</independence>
		<national-holiday>Revolution Day, 1 November (1954)</national-holiday>
		<legal-system>mixed legal system of French civil law and Islamic law; judicial review of legislative acts in ad hoc Constitutional Council composed of various public officials including several Supreme Court justices</legal-system>
		<suffrage>18 years of age; universal</suffrage>
		<executive>
			<head-of-state>President Abdelaziz BOUTEFLIKA (since 28 April 1999); note - the president is both the chief of state and head of government; a November 2008 constitutional amendment separated the position of head of government from that of the prime minister</head-of-state>
			<head-of-government>President Abdelaziz BOUTEFLIKA (since 28 April 1999)</head-of-government>
			<cabinet>Cabinet of Ministers appointed by the president</cabinet>
			<elections>president elected by popular vote for a five-year term; note - a November 2008 constitutional amendment abolished presidential term limits; election last held on 9 April 2009 (next to be held in April 2014)</elections>
			<election-results>Abdelaziz BOUTEFLIKA was reelected president for a third term; percent of vote - Abdelaziz BOUTEFLIKA 90.2%, Louisa HANOUNE 4.2%, Moussa TOUATI 2.3%, Djahid YOUNSI 1.4%, Ali Fawzi REBIANE less than 1%, Mohamed SAID less than 1%</election-results>
		</executive>
		<legislative>
			<description>bicameral Parliament consists of the Council of the Nation (upper house; 144 seats; one-third of the members appointed by the president, two-thirds elected by indirect vote to serve six-year terms; the constitution requires half the Council to be renewed every three years) and the National People's Assembly (lower house; 389 seats; members elected by popular vote to serve five-year terms)</description>
			<elections>Council of the Nation - last held on 29 December 2009 (next to be held in December 2012); National People's Assembly - last held on 17 May 2007 (next to be held in 2012)</elections>
			<election-results>Council of the Nation - percent of vote by party - NA; seats by party - NA; National People's Assembly - percent of vote by party - NA; seats by party - FLN 136, RND 61, MSP 52, PT 26, RCD 19, FNA 13, other 49, independents 33;</election-results>
		</legislative>
		<judicial>Supreme Court</judicial>
		<parties>[object Object]</parties>
		<pressure-groups>TO DO</pressure-groups>
		<membership>ABEDA, AfDB, AFESD, AMF, AMU, AU, BIS, FAO, G-15, G-24, G-77, IAEA, IBRD, ICAO, ICC, ICRM, IDA, IDB, IFAD, IFC, IFRCS, IHO, ILO, IMF, IMO, IMSO, Interpol, IOC, IOM, IPU, ISO, ITSO, ITU, ITUC, LAS, MIGA, MONUSCO, NAM, OAPEC, OAS (observer), OIC, OPCW, OPEC, OSCE (partner), UN, UNCTAD, UNESCO, UNHCR, UNIDO, UNITAR, UNWTO, UPU, WCO, WHO, WIPO, WMO, WTO (observer)</membership>
		<representation-in-usa>
			<chief>Ambassador Abdallah BAALI</chief>
			<chancery>2118 Kalorama Road NW, Washington, DC 20008</chancery>
			<telephone>[1] (202) 265-2800</telephone>
			<FAX>[1] (202) 667-2174</FAX>
			<consulates></consulates>
		</representation-in-usa>
		<representation-from-usa>
			<chief>Ambassador David D. PEARCE</chief>
			<embassy>05 Chemin Cheikh Bachir, El-Ibrahimi, El-Biar 16000 Algiers</embassy>
			<mailing-address>B. P. 408, Alger-Gare, 16030 Algiers</mailing-address>
			<telephone>[213] 770-08-2000</telephone>
			<FAX>[213] 21-60-7355</FAX>
		</representation-from-usa>
		<flag>two equal vertical bands of green (hoist side) and white; a red, five-pointed star within a red crescent centered over the two-color boundary; the colors represent Islam (green), purity and peace (white), and liberty (red); the crescent and star are also Islamic symbols, but the crescent is more closed than those of other Muslim countries because the Algerians believe the long crescent horns bring happiness</flag>
		<anthem>
			<name>&quot;Kassaman&quot; (We Pledge)</name>
			<by>Mufdi ZAKARIAH/Mohamed FAWZI</by>
		</anthem>
	</government>
	<economy>
		<overview>Algeria's economy remains dominated by the state, a legacy of the country's socialist post-independence development model. Gradual liberalization since the mid-1990s has opened up more of the economy, but in recent years Algeria has imposed new restrictions on foreign involvement in its economy and largely halted the privatization of state-owned industries. Hydrocarbons have long been the backbone of the economy, accounting for roughly 60% of budget revenues, 30% of GDP, and over 95% of export earnings. Algeria has the eighth-largest reserves of natural gas in the world and is the fourth-largest gas exporter. It ranks 16th in oil reserves. Thanks to strong hydrocarbon revenues, Algeria has a cushion of $150 billion in foreign currency reserves and a large hydrocarbon stabilization fund. In addition, Algeria's external debt is extremely low at about 1% of GDP. Algeria has struggled to develop industries outside of hydrocarbons in part because of high costs and an inert state bureaucracy. The government's efforts to diversify the economy by attracting foreign and domestic investment outside the energy sector have done little to reduce high poverty and youth unemployment rates. In 2010, Algeria began a five-year, $286 billion development program to update the country's infrastructure and provide jobs. The costly program will boost Algeria's economy in 2011 but worsen the country's budget deficit. Long-term economic challenges include diversification from hydrocarbons, relaxing state control of the economy, and providing adequate jobs for younger Algerians.</overview>
		<gdp>
			<purchasing-power-parity></purchasing-power-parity>
			<official-exchange-rate>160300000000</official-exchange-rate>
			<real-growth-rate unit="%">3.3</real-growth-rate>
			<per-capita></per-capita>
			<sector unit="%">
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
		</gdp>
		<labour>
			<force>9877000</force>
			<sector>
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
			<unemployment unit="%">9.9</unemployment>
		</labour>
		<poverty>[object Object]</poverty>
		<household-income>TO DO</household-income>
		<budget>
			<revenue unit="USD"></revenue>
			<expenditure unit="USD"></expenditure>
		</budget>
		<public-debt unit="% of GDP">25.7</public-debt>
		<consumer-inflation unit="%">5</consumer-inflation>
		<central-bank-discount-rate unit="%">4</central-bank-discount-rate>
		<commercial-prime-lending-rate unit="%">8</commercial-prime-lending-rate>
		<narrow-money-stock unit="USD">79070000000</narrow-money-stock>
		<broad-money-stock unit="USD">109700000000</broad-money-stock>
		<domestic-credit-stock unit="USD">12290000000</domestic-credit-stock>
		<agriculture-products>wheat, barley, oats, grapes, olives, citrus, fruits; sheep, cattle</agriculture-products>
		<industries>petroleum, natural gas, light industries, mining, electrical, petrochemical, food processing</industries>
		<industrial-production-growth>[object Object]</industrial-production-growth>
		<electricity unit="kWh">
			<production>34980000000</production>
			<consumption>28340000000</consumption>
			<exports>273000000</exports>
			<imports>279000000</imports>
		</electricity>
		<oil>
			<production unit="bbl/day">2125000</production>
			<consumption unit="bbl/day">325000</consumption>
			<exports unit="bbl/day">1891000</exports>
			<imports unit="bbl/day">14320</imports>
			<reserves unit="bbl">13420000000</reserves>
		</oil>
		<natural-gas>
			<production unit="cu m">86500000000</production>
			<consumption unit="cu m">26830000000</consumption>
			<exports unit="cu m">59670000000</exports>
			<imports unit="cu m">0</imports>
			<reserves unit="cu m">4502000000000</reserves>
		</natural-gas>
		<exports>
			<total unit="USD"></total>
			<commodities>petroleum, natural gas, and petroleum products 97%</commodities>
			<partners>US 23.2%, Italy 17.23%, Spain 10.83%, France 7.97%, Canada 7.65%, Netherlands 5.19%, Turkey 4.22% (2009)</partners>
		</exports>
		<imports>
			<total unit="USD">37070000000</total>
			<commodities>capital goods, foodstuffs, consumer goods</commodities>
			<partners>France 19.7%, China 11.72%, Italy 10.19%, Spain 8.13%, Germany 5.77%, Turkey 5.05% (2009)</partners>
		</imports>
		<external-debt unit="USD">4138000000</external-debt>
		<exchange-rates>Algerian dinars (DZD) per US dollar -</exchange-rates>
	</economy>
	<communications>
		<telephones>
			<assessment>privatization of Algeria's telecommunications sector began in 2000; three mobile cellular licenses have been issued and, in 2005, a consortium led by Egypt's Orascom Telecom won a 15-year license to build and operate a fixed-line network in Algeria; the license will allow Orascom to develop high-speed data and other specialized services and contribute to meeting the large unfulfilled demand for basic residential telephony; Internet broadband services began in 2003</assessment>
			<domestic>a limited network of fixed lines with a teledensity of less than 10 telephones per 100 persons is offset by the rapid increase in mobile-cellular subscribership; in 2009, combined fixed-line and mobile-cellular teledensity was roughly 100 telephones per 100 persons</domestic>
			<international>country code - 213; landing point for the SEA-ME-WE-4 fiber-optic submarine cable system that provides links to Europe, the Middle East, and Asia; microwave radio relay to Italy, France, Spain, Morocco, and Tunisia; coaxial cable to Morocco and Tunisia; participant in Medarabtel; satellite earth stations - 51 (Intelsat, Intersputnik, and Arabsat) (2009)</international>
			<land-lines>2576000</land-lines>
			<mobile>32729999.999999996</mobile>
		</telephones>
		<broadcast>state-run Radio-Television Algerienne operates the broadcast media and carries programming in Arabic, Berber dialects, and French; use of satellite dishes is widespread, providing easy access to European and Arab satellite stations; state-run radio operates several national networks and roughly 40 regional radio stations (2007)</broadcast>
		<internet>
			<tld>.dz</tld>
			<hosts>572</hosts>
			<users>4700000</users>
		</internet>
	</communications>
	<transport>
		<airports>
			<total>143</total>
			<paved>
				<altitude min="*" max="*"></altitude>
				<altitude min="3047m" max="*">12</altitude>
				<altitude min="2438m" max="3047m">28</altitude>
				<altitude min="1524m" max="2437m">11</altitude>
				<altitude min="914m" max="1524m">5</altitude>
				<altitude min="*" max="914m"></altitude>
			</paved>
		</airports>
		<ports-and-terminals>Algiers, Annaba, Arzew, Bejaia, Djendjene, Jijel, Mostaganem, Oran, Skikda</ports-and-terminals>
	</transport>
	<military>
		<branches>People's National Army (Armee Nationale Populaire, ANP), Land Forces (Forces Terrestres, FT), Navy of the Republic of Algeria (Marine de la Republique Algerienne, MRA), Air Force (Al-Quwwat al-Jawwiya al-Jaza'eriya, QJJ), Territorial Air Defense Force (2009)</branches>
		<manpower>
			<population-available>
				<male>10273</male>
				<female>10114</female>
			</population-available>
			<fit-for-service>
				<male>8622</male>
				<female>8626</female>
			</fit-for-service>
			<reaching-maturity>
				<male>342895</male>
				<female>330098</female>
			</reaching-maturity>
			<notes></notes>
		</manpower>
	</military>
	<issues>
		<disputes>Algeria, and many other states, rejects Moroccan administration of Western Sahara; the Polisario Front, exiled in Algeria, represents the Sahrawi Arab Democratic Republic; Algeria's border with Morocco remains an irritant to bilateral relations, each nation accusing the other of harboring militants and arms smuggling; dormant disputes include Libyan claims of about 32,000 sq km still reflected on its maps of southeastern Algeria and the FLN's assertions of a claim to Chirac Pastures in southeastern Morocco</disputes>
		<drugs></drugs>
	</issues>
</country>