<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<country>
	<code>as</code>
	<name>Australia</name>
	<region>Australia-Oceania</region>
	<background>Aboriginal settlers arrived on the continent from Southeast Asia about 40,000 years before the first Europeans began exploration in the 17th century. No formal territorial claims were made until 1770, when Capt. James COOK took possession of the east coast in the name of Great Britain (all of Australia was claimed as British territory in 1829 with the creation of the colony of Western Australia). Six colonies were created in the late 18th and 19th centuries; they federated and became the Commonwealth of Australia in 1901. The new country took advantage of its natural resources to rapidly develop agricultural and manufacturing industries and to make a major contribution to the British effort in World Wars I and II. In recent decades, Australia has transformed itself into an internationally competitive, advanced market economy. It boasted one of the OECD's fastest growing economies during the 1990s, a performance due in large part to economic reforms adopted in the 1980s. Long-term concerns include ageing of the population, pressure on infrastructure, and environmental issues such as frequent droughts.</background>
	<geo>
		<note>world's smallest continent but sixth-largest country; population concentrated along the eastern and southeastern coasts; the invigorating sea breeze known as the &quot;Fremantle Doctor&quot; affects the city of Perth on the west coast and is one of the most consistent winds in the world</note>
		<location>
			<desc>Oceania, continent between the Indian Ocean and the South Pacific Ocean</desc>
			<coordinates>TO DO</coordinates>
		</location>
		<area>
			<total unit="sq km">7741</total>
			<land unit="sq km">7682</land>
			<water unit="sq km">58920</water>
			<comparison>slightly smaller than the US contiguous 48 states</comparison>
		</area>
		<boundaries>
			<borders unit="km">0</borders>
			<coastline unit="km">25760</coastline>
		</boundaries>
		<maritime-claims>
			<territorial unit="nm">12</territorial>
			<contiguous unit="nm">24</contiguous>
			<economic unit="nm">200</economic>
			<continental-shelf>200 nm or to the edge of the continental margin</continental-shelf>
		</maritime-claims>
		<climate>generally arid to semiarid; temperate in south and east; tropical in north</climate>
		<terrain>mostly low plateau with deserts; fertile plain in southeast</terrain>
		<elevation>
			<high>Mount Kosciuszko 2,229 m</high>
			<low>Lake Eyre -15 m</low>
		</elevation>
		<resources>[object Object]</resources>
		<land-use>
			<arable unit="%">6.15</arable>
			<crops unit="%">0.04</crops>
			<other unit="%">93.81</other>
		</land-use>
		<hazards>[object Object]</hazards>
		<issues>soil erosion from overgrazing, industrial development, urbanization, and poor farming practices; soil salinity rising due to the use of poor quality water; desertification; clearing for agricultural purposes threatens the natural habitat of many unique animal and plant species; the Great Barrier Reef off the northeast coast, the largest coral reef in the world, is threatened by increased shipping and its popularity as a tourist site; limited natural freshwater resources</issues>
		<water>
			<irrigated-land unit="sq km">25500</irrigated-land>
			<renewable-water unit="cu km">398</renewable-water>
			<freshwater-withdrawal>
				<total unit="cu km/yr">24.06</total>
				<per-capita unit="cu m/yr">1193</per-capita>
			</freshwater-withdrawal>
		</water>
		<!--
"geo": {

		"Natural hazards": "flooding is a threat in some areas of the country (e.g., parts of Jutland, along the southern coast of the island of Lolland) that are protected from the sea by a system of dikes",
		"Environment - current issues": "air pollution, principally from vehicle and power plant emissions; nitrogen and phosphorus pollution of the North Sea; drinking and surface water becoming polluted from animal wastes and pesticides",
		"Environment - international agreements": {
			"party to:": "Air Pollution, Air Pollution-Nitrogen Oxides, Air Pollution-Persistent Organic Pollutants, Air Pollution-Sulfur 85, Air Pollution-Sulfur 94, Air Pollution-Volatile Organic Compounds, Antarctic Treaty, Biodiversity, Climate Change, Climate Change-Kyoto Protocol, Desertification, Endangered Species, Environmental Modification, Hazardous Wastes, Law of the Sea, Marine Dumping, Marine Life Conservation, Ozone Layer Protection, Ship Pollution, Tropical Timber 83, Tropical Timber 94, Wetlands, Whaling",
			"signed, but not ratified:": "none of the selected agreements"
		},
		"Geography - note": "controls Danish Straits (Skagerrak and Kattegat) linking Baltic and North Seas; about one-quarter of the population lives in greater Copenhagen"

		-->
	</geo>
	<people>
		<population>
			<total>21766</total>
			<birth unit="births/1,000 population">12.33</birth>
			<death unit="deaths/1,000 population">6.88</birth>
			<migration unit="migrant(s)/1,000 population">6.03</migration>
			<growth unit="%">1.148</growth>
		</population>
		<age-distribution unit="percent">
			<group min="0" max="14">18.3</group>
			<group min="15" max="64">67.7</group>
			<group min="65"></group>
		</age-distribution>
		<median-age unit="years">
			<total>37.7</total>
			<male>37</male>
			<female>38.4</female>
		</median-age>
		<urbanization>
			<urban unit="% of total population">89</urban>
			<rate unit="% annual rate of change">1.2</urban>
			<cities>Sydney 4.429 million; Melbourne 3.853 million; Brisbane 1.97 million; Perth 1.599 million; CANBERRA (capital) 384,000 (2009)</cities>
		</urbanization>
		<sex unit="male(s)/female">
			<group name="at birth" max="0">1.055</group>
			<group name="0 to 14" min="0" max="14">1.05</group>
			<group name="15 to 64" min="15" max="64">1.03</group>
			<group name="65 and over" min="65" max="0">0.84</group>
			<group name="total" min="0">1</group>
		</sex>
		<infant-mortality>
			<total unit="deaths/1,000 live births">4.61</total>
			<male unit="deaths/1,000 live births">4.93</male>
			<female unit="deaths/1,000 live births">4.27</female>
		</infant-mortality>
		<life-expectancy-at-birth>
			<total unit="years">81.81</total>
			<male unit="years">79.4</male>
			<female unit="years">84.35</female>
		</life-expectancy-at-birth>
		<fertility-rate unit="1.78">children born/woman</fertility-rate>
		<hiv>
			<prevalence>[object Object]</prevalence>
			<total>20000</total>
			<deaths>fewer than 100 (2009 est.)</deaths>
		</hiv>
		<infectious-disease risk="">
			<food-or-waterborne></food-or-waterborne>
			<vectorborne></vectorborne>
			<water-contact></water-contact>
		</infectious-disease>
		<drinking-water-source>[object Object]</drinking-water-source>
		<sanitation-access>[object Object]</sanitation-access>
		<nationality>
			<noun>Australian(s)</noun>
			<adjective>Australian</adjective>
		</nationality>
		<ethnic-groups>white 92%, Asian 7%, aboriginal and other 1%</ethnic-groups>
		<religions>Catholic 25.8%, Anglican 18.7%, Uniting Church 5.7%, Presbyterian and Reformed 3%, Eastern Orthodox 2.7%, other Christian 7.9%, Buddhist 2.1%, Muslim 1.7%, other 2.4%, unspecified 11.3%, none 18.7% (2006 Census)</religions>
		<languages>English 78.5%, Chinese 2.5%, Italian 1.6%, Greek 1.3%, Arabic 1.2%, Vietnamese 1%, other 8.2%, unspecified 5.7% (2006 Census)</languages>
		<literacy>
			<definition>age 15 and over can read and write</definition>
			<total unit="%">99</total>
			<male unit="%">99</male>
			<female unit="%">99</female>
		</literacy>
		<school-expectancy unit="years">21</school-expectancy>
		<education-expenditure unit="% of GDP">4.5</school-expectancy>
	</people>
	<government>
		<country-name>
			<long>Commonwealth of Australia</long>
			<short>Australia</short>
		</country-name>
		<dependency></dependency>
		<government-type>federal parliamentary democracy and a Commonwealth realm</government-type>
		<capital>
			<name>Canberra</name>
			<coordinates>35° 17' S, 149° 13' E</coordinates>
			<time-difference>UTC+10 (15 hours ahead of Washington, DC during Standard Time)</time-difference>
		</capital>
		<administrative-divisions>6 states and 2 territories*; Australian Capital Territory*, New South Wales, Northern Territory*, Queensland, South Australia, Tasmania, Victoria, Western Australia</administrative-divisions>
		<independence>1 January 1901 (from the federation of UK colonies)</independence>
		<national-holiday>Australia Day, 26 January (1788); ANZAC Day (commemorates the anniversary of the landing of troops of the Australian and New Zealand Army Corps during World War I at Gallipoli, Turkey), 25 April (1915)</national-holiday>
		<legal-system>common law system based on the English model</legal-system>
		<suffrage>18 years of age; universal and compulsory</suffrage>
		<executive>
			<head-of-state>Queen of Australia ELIZABETH II (since 6 February 1952); represented by Governor General Quentin BRYCE (since 5 September 2008)</head-of-state>
			<head-of-government>Prime Minister Julia Eileen GILLARD (since 24 June 2010); Deputy Prime Minister Wayne Maxwell SWAN (since 24 June 2010)</head-of-government>
			<cabinet>prime minister nominates, from among members of Parliament, candidates who are subsequently sworn in by the governor general to serve as government ministers</cabinet>
			<elections>the monarchy is hereditary; governor general appointed by the monarch on the recommendation of the prime minister; following legislative elections, the leader of the majority party or leader of a majority coalition is sworn in as prime minister by the governor general</elections>
			<election-results></election-results>
		</executive>
		<legislative>
			<description>bicameral Federal Parliament consists of the Senate (76 seats; 12 members from each of the six states and 2 from each of the two mainland territories; one-half of state members are elected every three years by popular vote to serve six-year terms while all territory members are elected every three years) and the House of Representatives (150 seats; members elected by popular vote to serve terms of up to three-years; no state can have fewer than 5 representatives)</description>
			<elections>Senate - last held on 21 August 2010; House of Representatives - last held on 21 August 2010 (the latest a simultaneous half-Senate and House of Representative elections can be held is 30 November 2013)</elections>
			<election-results>Senate (effective 1 July 2011) - percent of vote by party - NA; seats by party - Liberal/National Party 34, Australian Labor Party 31, Greens 9, others 2; House of Representatives - percent of vote by party - Australian Labor Party 38.1%, Liberal Party 30.4%, Greens 11.5%, Liberal National Party of Queensland 9.3%, independents 6.6%, The Nationals 3.7%, Country Liberals 0.3%; seats by party - Australian Labor Party 72, Liberal Party 44, Liberal National Party of Queensland 21, The Nationals 7, Country Liberals 1, Greens 1, independents 4</election-results>
		</legislative>
		<judicial>High Court (the chief justice and six other justices are appointed by the governor general acting on the advice of the government)</judicial>
		<parties>Australian Greens [Bob BROWN]; Australian Labor Party [Julia GILLARD]; Family First Party [Steve FIELDING]; Liberal Party [Tony ABBOTT]; The Nationals [Warren TRUSS]</parties>
		<pressure-groups>TO DO</pressure-groups>
		<membership>ADB, ANZUS, APEC, ARF, ASEAN (dialogue partner), Australia Group, BIS, C, CP, EAS, EBRD, FAO, FATF, G-20, IAEA, IBRD, ICAO, ICC, ICRM, IDA, IEA, IFC, IFRCS, IHO, ILO, IMF, IMO, IMSO, Interpol, IOC, IOM, IPU, ISO, ITSO, ITU, ITUC, MIGA, NEA, NSG, OECD, OPCW, OSCE (partner), Paris Club, PCA, PIF, SAARC (observer), Sparteca, SPC, UN, UNCTAD, UNESCO, UNHCR, UNMIS, UNMIT, UNRWA, UNTSO, UNWTO, UPU, WCO, WFTU, WHO, WIPO, WMO, WTO, ZC</membership>
		<representation-in-usa>
			<chief>Ambassador Kim Christian BEAZLEY</chief>
			<chancery>1601 Massachusetts Avenue NW, Washington, DC 20036</chancery>
			<telephone>[1] (202) 797-3000</telephone>
			<FAX>[1] (202) 797-3168</FAX>
			<consulates>Atlanta, Chicago, Honolulu, Los Angeles, New York, San Francisco</consulates>
		</representation-in-usa>
		<representation-from-usa>
			<chief>Ambassador Jeffrey L. BLEICH</chief>
			<embassy>Moonah Place, Yarralumla, Canberra, Australian Capital Territory 2600</embassy>
			<mailing-address>APO AP 96549</mailing-address>
			<telephone>[61] (02) 6214-5600</telephone>
			<FAX>[61] (02) 6214-5970</FAX>
		</representation-from-usa>
		<flag>blue with the flag of the UK in the upper hoist-side quadrant and a large seven-pointed star in the lower hoist-side quadrant known as the Commonwealth or Federation Star, representing the federation of the colonies of Australia in 1901; the star depicts one point for each of the six original states and one representing all of Australia's internal and external territories; on the fly half is a representation of the Southern Cross constellation in white with one small five-pointed star and four larger, seven-pointed stars</flag>
		<anthem>
			<name>&quot;Advance Australia Fair&quot;</name>
			<by>Peter Dodds McCORMICK</by>
		</anthem>
	</government>
	<economy>
		<overview>Australia's abundant and diverse natural resources attract high levels of foreign investment and include extensive reserves of coal, iron ore, copper, gold, natural gas, uranium, and renewable energy sources. A series of major investments, such as the US$40 billion Gorgon Liquid Natural Gas project, will significantly expand the resources sector. Australia also has a large services sector and is a significant exporter of natural resources, energy, and food. Key tenets of Australia's trade policy include support for open trade and the successful culmination of the Doha Round of multilateral trade negotiations, particularly for agriculture and services. The Australian economy grew for 17 consecutive years before the global financial crisis. Subsequently, the Rudd government introduced a fiscal stimulus package worth over US$50 billion to offset the effect of the slowing world economy, while the Reserve Bank of Australia cut interest rates to historic lows. These policies - and continued demand for commodities, especially from China - helped the Australian economy rebound after just one quarter of negative growth. The economy grew by 1.2% during 2009 - the best performance in the OECD - and by 3.3% in 2010. Unemployment, originally expected to reach 8-10%, peaked at 5.7% in late 2009 and fell to 5.1% in 2010. As a result of an improved economy, the budget deficit is expected to peak below 4.2% of GDP and the government could return to budget surpluses as early as 2015. Australia was one of the first advanced economies to raise interest rates, with seven rate hikes between October 2009 and November 2010. The GILLARD government is focused on raising Australia's economic productivity to ensure the sustainability of growth, and continues to manage the symbiotic, but sometimes tense, economic relationship with China. Australia is engaged in the Trans-Pacific Partnership talks and ongoing free trade agreement negotiations with China, Japan, and Korea.</overview>
		<gdp>
			<purchasing-power-parity></purchasing-power-parity>
			<official-exchange-rate>1236000000000</official-exchange-rate>
			<real-growth-rate unit="%">2.7</real-growth-rate>
			<per-capita></per-capita>
			<sector unit="%">
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
		</gdp>
		<labour>
			<force>11620000</force>
			<sector>
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
			<unemployment unit="%">5.1</unemployment>
		</labour>
		<poverty>NA%</poverty>
		<household-income>TO DO</household-income>
		<budget>
			<revenue unit="USD"></revenue>
			<expenditure unit="USD"></expenditure>
		</budget>
		<public-debt unit="% of GDP">22.4</public-debt>
		<consumer-inflation unit="%">2.9</consumer-inflation>
		<central-bank-discount-rate unit="%"></central-bank-discount-rate>
		<commercial-prime-lending-rate unit="%">6.02</commercial-prime-lending-rate>
		<narrow-money-stock unit="USD">347100000000</narrow-money-stock>
		<broad-money-stock unit="USD">1134000000000</broad-money-stock>
		<domestic-credit-stock unit="USD">1731000000000</domestic-credit-stock>
		<agriculture-products>wheat, barley, sugarcane, fruits; cattle, sheep, poultry</agriculture-products>
		<industries>mining, industrial and transportation equipment, food processing, chemicals, steel</industries>
		<industrial-production-growth>[object Object]</industrial-production-growth>
		<electricity unit="kWh">
			<production>239900000000</production>
			<consumption>222000000000</consumption>
			<exports>0</exports>
			<imports>0</imports>
		</electricity>
		<oil>
			<production unit="bbl/day">589200</production>
			<consumption unit="bbl/day">946300</consumption>
			<exports unit="bbl/day">311900</exports>
			<imports unit="bbl/day">716700</imports>
			<reserves unit="bbl">3318000000</reserves>
		</oil>
		<natural-gas>
			<production unit="cu m">42330000000</production>
			<consumption unit="cu m">26590000000</consumption>
			<exports unit="cu m">22300000000</exports>
			<imports unit="cu m">6560000000</imports>
			<reserves unit="cu m">3115000000000</reserves>
		</natural-gas>
		<exports>
			<total unit="USD"></total>
			<commodities>coal, iron ore, gold, meat, wool, alumina, wheat, machinery and transport equipment</commodities>
			<partners>China 21.81%, Japan 19.19%, South Korea 7.88%, India 7.51%, US 4.95%, UK 4.37%, NZ 4.1% (2009)</partners>
		</exports>
		<imports>
			<total unit="USD">200400000000</total>
			<commodities>machinery and transport equipment, computers and office machines, telecommunication equipment and parts; crude oil and petroleum products</commodities>
			<partners>China 17.94%, US 11.26%, Japan 8.36%, Thailand 5.81%, Singapore 5.54%, Germany 5.3% (2009)</partners>
		</imports>
		<external-debt unit="USD">1169000000000</external-debt>
		<exchange-rates>Australian dollars (AUD) per US dollar -</exchange-rates>
	</economy>
	<communications>
		<telephones>
			<assessment>excellent domestic and international service</assessment>
			<domestic>domestic satellite system; significant use of radiotelephone in areas of low population density; rapid growth of mobile telephones</domestic>
			<international>country code - 61; landing point for the SEA-ME-WE-3 optical telecommunications submarine cable with links to Asia, the Middle East, and Europe; the Southern Cross fiber optic submarine cable provides links to New Zealand and the United States; satellite earth stations - 19 (10 Intelsat - 4 Indian Ocean and 6 Pacific Ocean, 2 Inmarsat - Indian and Pacific Ocean regions, 2 Globalstar, 5 other) (2007)</international>
			<land-lines>9020000</land-lines>
			<mobile>24220000</mobile>
		</telephones>
		<broadcast>the Australian Broadcasting Corporation (ABC) runs multiple national and local radio networks and TV stations, as well as Australia Network, a TV service that broadcasts throughout the Asia-Pacific region and is the main public broadcaster; Special Broadcasting Service (SBS), a second large public broadcaster, operates radio and TV networks broadcasting in multiple languages; several large national commercial TV networks, a large number of local commercial TV stations, and hundreds of commercial radio stations are accessible; cable and satellite systems are available (2008)</broadcast>
		<internet>
			<tld>.au</tld>
			<hosts>13361000</hosts>
			<users>15810000</users>
		</internet>
	</communications>
	<transport>
		<airports>
			<total>465</total>
			<paved>
				<altitude min="*" max="*"></altitude>
				<altitude min="3047m" max="*">11</altitude>
				<altitude min="2438m" max="3047m">13</altitude>
				<altitude min="1524m" max="2437m">148</altitude>
				<altitude min="914m" max="1524m">140</altitude>
				<altitude min="*" max="914m"></altitude>
			</paved>
		</airports>
		<ports-and-terminals>Brisbane, Cairns, Dampier, Darwin, Fremantle, Gladstone, Geelong, Hay Point, Hobart, Jervis Bay, Melbourne, Newcastle, Port Adelaide, Port Dalrymple, Port Hedland, Port Kembla, Port Lincoln, Port Walcott, Sydney</ports-and-terminals>
	</transport>
	<military>
		<branches>Australian Defense Force (ADF): Australian Army, Royal Australian Navy, Royal Australian Air Force, Special Operations Command (2006)</branches>
		<manpower>
			<population-available>
				<male>5316</male>
				<female>5116</female>
			</population-available>
			<fit-for-service>
				<male>4411</male>
				<female>4239</female>
			</fit-for-service>
			<reaching-maturity>
				<male>143565</male>
				<female>135800</female>
			</reaching-maturity>
			<notes></notes>
		</manpower>
	</military>
	<issues>
		<disputes>In 2007, Australia and Timor-Leste signed agreed to a 50-year development zone and revenue sharing arrangement and deferred a maritime boundary; Australia asserts land and maritime claims to Antarctica; Australia's 2004 submission to Commission on the Limits of the Continental Shelf (CLCS) extends its continental margins over 3.37 million square kilometers, expanding its seabed roughly 30 percent beyond its claimed exclusive economic zone; a 1997 treaty between Indonesia and Australia settled some parts of their maritime boundary but some outstanding issues, especially around Timor Leste, remain; Indonesian groups challenge Australia's claim to Ashmore Reef; Australia has closed parts of the Ashmore and Cartier reserve to Indonesian traditional fishing</disputes>
		<drugs>Tasmania is one of the world's major suppliers of licit opiate products; government maintains strict controls over areas of opium poppy cultivation and output of poppy straw concentrate; major consumer of cocaine and amphetamines</drugs>
	</issues>
</country>