<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<country>
	<code>bl</code>
	<name>Bolivia</name>
	<region>South America</region>
	<background>Bolivia, named after independence fighter Simon BOLIVAR, broke away from Spanish rule in 1825; much of its subsequent history has consisted of a series of nearly 200 coups and countercoups. Democratic civilian rule was established in 1982, but leaders have faced difficult problems of deep-seated poverty, social unrest, and illegal drug production. In December 2005, Bolivians elected Movement Toward Socialism leader Evo MORALES president - by the widest margin of any leader since the restoration of civilian rule in 1982 - after he ran on a promise to change the country's traditional political class and empower the nation's poor, indigenous majority. However, since taking office, his controversial strategies have exacerbated racial and economic tensions between the Amerindian populations of the Andean west and the non-indigenous communities of the eastern lowlands. In December 2009, President MORALES easily won reelection, and his party took control of the legislative branch of the government, which will allow him to continue his process of change.</background>
	<geo>
		<note>landlocked; shares control of Lago Titicaca, world's highest navigable lake (elevation 3,805 m), with Peru</note>
		<location>
			<desc>Central South America, southwest of Brazil</desc>
			<coordinates>TO DO</coordinates>
		</location>
		<area>
			<total unit="sq km">1098</total>
			<land unit="sq km">1083</land>
			<water unit="sq km">15280</water>
			<comparison>slightly less than three times the size of Montana</comparison>
		</area>
		<boundaries>
			<borders unit=""></borders>
			<coastline unit="km">0</coastline>
		</boundaries>
		<maritime-claims>
			<territorial unit=""></territorial>
			<contiguous unit=""></contiguous>
			<economic unit=""></economic>
			<continental-shelf></continental-shelf>
		</maritime-claims>
		<climate>varies with altitude; humid and tropical to cold and semiarid</climate>
		<terrain>rugged Andes Mountains with a highland plateau (Altiplano), hills, lowland plains of the Amazon Basin</terrain>
		<elevation>
			<high>Nevado Sajama 6,542 m</high>
			<low>Rio Paraguay 90 m</low>
		</elevation>
		<resources>tin, natural gas, petroleum, zinc, tungsten, antimony, silver, iron, lead, gold, timber, hydropower</resources>
		<land-use>
			<arable unit="%">2.78</arable>
			<crops unit="%">0.19</crops>
			<other unit="%">97.03</other>
		</land-use>
		<hazards>[object Object]</hazards>
		<issues>the clearing of land for agricultural purposes and the international demand for tropical timber are contributing to deforestation; soil erosion from overgrazing and poor cultivation methods (including slash-and-burn agriculture); desertification; loss of biodiversity; industrial pollution of water supplies used for drinking and irrigation</issues>
		<water>
			<irrigated-land unit="sq km">1500</irrigated-land>
			<renewable-water unit="cu km">622.5</renewable-water>
			<freshwater-withdrawal>
				<total unit="cu km/yr">1.44</total>
				<per-capita unit="cu m/yr">157</per-capita>
			</freshwater-withdrawal>
		</water>
		<!--
"geo": {

		"Natural hazards": "flooding is a threat in some areas of the country (e.g., parts of Jutland, along the southern coast of the island of Lolland) that are protected from the sea by a system of dikes",
		"Environment - current issues": "air pollution, principally from vehicle and power plant emissions; nitrogen and phosphorus pollution of the North Sea; drinking and surface water becoming polluted from animal wastes and pesticides",
		"Environment - international agreements": {
			"party to:": "Air Pollution, Air Pollution-Nitrogen Oxides, Air Pollution-Persistent Organic Pollutants, Air Pollution-Sulfur 85, Air Pollution-Sulfur 94, Air Pollution-Volatile Organic Compounds, Antarctic Treaty, Biodiversity, Climate Change, Climate Change-Kyoto Protocol, Desertification, Endangered Species, Environmental Modification, Hazardous Wastes, Law of the Sea, Marine Dumping, Marine Life Conservation, Ozone Layer Protection, Ship Pollution, Tropical Timber 83, Tropical Timber 94, Wetlands, Whaling",
			"signed, but not ratified:": "none of the selected agreements"
		},
		"Geography - note": "controls Danish Straits (Skagerrak and Kattegat) linking Baltic and North Seas; about one-quarter of the population lives in greater Copenhagen"

		-->
	</geo>
	<people>
		<population>
			<total>10118</total>
			<birth unit="births/1,000 population">24.71</birth>
			<death unit="deaths/1,000 population">6.85</birth>
			<migration unit=""></migration>
			<growth unit="%">1.694</growth>
		</population>
		<age-distribution unit="percent">
			<group min="0" max="14">34.6</group>
			<group min="15" max="64">60.7</group>
			<group min="65"></group>
		</age-distribution>
		<median-age unit="years">
			<total>22.5</total>
			<male>21.8</male>
			<female>23.2</female>
		</median-age>
		<urbanization>
			<urban unit="% of total population">67</urban>
			<rate unit="% annual rate of change">2.2</urban>
			<cities>LA PAZ (capital) 1.642 million; Santa Cruz 1.584 million; Sucre 281,000 (2009)</cities>
		</urbanization>
		<sex unit="male(s)/female">
			<group name="at birth" max="0">1.05</group>
			<group name="0 to 14" min="0" max="14">1.04</group>
			<group name="15 to 64" min="15" max="64">0.96</group>
			<group name="65 and over" min="65" max="0">0.79</group>
			<group name="total" min="0">0.98</group>
		</sex>
		<infant-mortality>
			<total unit="deaths/1,000 live births">42.16</total>
			<male unit="deaths/1,000 live births">45.95</male>
			<female unit="deaths/1,000 live births">38.18</female>
		</infant-mortality>
		<life-expectancy-at-birth>
			<total unit="years">67.57</total>
			<male unit="years">64.84</male>
			<female unit="years">70.42</female>
		</life-expectancy-at-birth>
		<fertility-rate unit="3">children born/woman</fertility-rate>
		<hiv>
			<prevalence>[object Object]</prevalence>
			<total>12000</total>
			<deaths>fewer than 1,000 (2009 est.)</deaths>
		</hiv>
		<infectious-disease risk="high">
			<food-or-waterborne>bacterial diarrhea, hepatitis A, and typhoid fever</food-or-waterborne>
			<vectorborne>dengue fever, malaria, and yellow fever</vectorborne>
			<water-contact></water-contact>
		</infectious-disease>
		<drinking-water-source>[object Object]</drinking-water-source>
		<sanitation-access>[object Object]</sanitation-access>
		<nationality>
			<noun>Bolivian(s)</noun>
			<adjective>Bolivian</adjective>
		</nationality>
		<ethnic-groups>Quechua 30%, mestizo (mixed white and Amerindian ancestry) 30%, Aymara 25%, white 15%</ethnic-groups>
		<religions>Roman Catholic 95%, Protestant (Evangelical Methodist) 5%</religions>
		<languages>Spanish (official) 60.7%, Quechua (official) 21.2%, Aymara (official) 14.6%, foreign languages 2.4%, other 1.2% (2001 census)</languages>
		<literacy>
			<definition>age 15 and over can read and write</definition>
			<total unit="%">86.7</total>
			<male unit="%">93.1</male>
			<female unit="%">80.7</female>
		</literacy>
		<school-expectancy unit="years">14</school-expectancy>
		<education-expenditure unit="% of GDP">6.3</school-expectancy>
	</people>
	<government>
		<country-name>
			<long>Plurinational State of Bolivia</long>
			<short>Bolivia</short>
		</country-name>
		<dependency></dependency>
		<government-type>republic; note - the new constitution defines Bolivia as a &quot;Social Unitarian State&quot;</government-type>
		<capital>
			<name>La Paz (administrative capital)</name>
			<coordinates>16° 30' S, 68° 9' W</coordinates>
			<time-difference>UTC-4 (1 hour ahead of Washington, DC during Standard Time)</time-difference>
		</capital>
		<administrative-divisions>9 departments (departamentos, singular - departamento); Beni, Chuquisaca, Cochabamba, La Paz, Oruro, Pando, Potosi, Santa Cruz, Tarija</administrative-divisions>
		<independence>6 August 1825 (from Spain)</independence>
		<national-holiday>Independence Day, 6 August (1825)</national-holiday>
		<legal-system>civil law system with influences from Roman, Spanish, canon (religious), French, and indigenous law</legal-system>
		<suffrage>18 years of age, universal and compulsory</suffrage>
		<executive>
			<head-of-state>President Juan Evo MORALES Ayma (since 22 January 2006); Vice President Alvaro GARCIA Linera (since 22 January 2006); note - the president is both chief of state and head of government</head-of-state>
			<head-of-government>President Juan Evo MORALES Ayma (since 22 January 2006); Vice President Alvaro GARCIA Linera (since 22 January 2006)</head-of-government>
			<cabinet>Cabinet appointed by the president</cabinet>
			<elections>president and vice president elected on the same ticket by popular vote for a five-year term and are eligible for re-election; election last held on 6 December 2009 (next to be held in 2014)</elections>
			<election-results>Juan Evo MORALES Ayma reelected president; percent of vote - Juan Evo MORALES Ayma 64%; Manfred REYES VILLA 26%; Samuel DORIA MEDINA Arana 6%; Rene JOAQUINO 2%; other 2%</election-results>
		</executive>
		<legislative>
			<description>bicameral Plurinational Legislative Assembly or Asamblea Legislativa Plurinacional consists of Chamber of Senators or Camara de Senadores (36 seats; members are elected by proportional representation from party lists to serve five-year terms) and Chamber of Deputies or Camara de Diputados (130 seats total; 70 uninominal deputies directly elected from a single district, 7 &quot;special&quot; indigenous deputies directly elected from non-contiguous indigenous districts, and 53 plurinominal deputies elected by proportional representation from party lists; all deputies serve five-year terms)</description>
			<elections>Chamber of Senators and Chamber of Deputies - last held on 6 December 2009 (next to be held in 2014)</elections>
			<election-results>Chamber of Senators - percent of vote by party - NA; seats by party - MAS 26, PPB-CN 10; Chamber of Deputies - percent of vote by party - NA; seats by party - MAS 89, PPB-CN 36, UN 3, AS 2</election-results>
		</legislative>
		<judicial>Supreme Court or Tribunal Supremo de Justicia (judges elected by popular vote from list of candidates pre-selected by Assembly for six-year terms); District Courts (one in each department); Plurinational Constitutional Tribunal (seven primary or titulares and seven alternate or suplente magistrates elected by popular vote from list of candidates pre-selected by Assembly for six-year terms; to rule on constitutional issues (at least two candidates must be indigenous)); Plurinational Electoral Organ (seven members elected by the Assembly and the president; one member must be of indigenous origin to six-year terms); Agro-Environmental Court (judges elected by popular vote from list of candidates pre-selected by Assembly for six-year terms; to run on agro-environmental issues); provincial and local courts (to try minor cases)</judicial>
		<parties>Bolivia-National Convergence or PPB-CN [Manfred REYES VILLA]; Fearless Movement or MSM [Juan DE GRANADO Cosio]; Movement Toward Socialism or MAS [Juan Evo MORALES Ayma]; National Unity or UN [Samuel DORIA MEDINA Arana]; People or Gente [Roman LOAYZA]; Social Alliance or AS [Rene JOAQUINO]</parties>
		<pressure-groups>TO DO</pressure-groups>
		<membership>CAN, FAO, G-77, IADB, IAEA, IBRD, ICAO, ICC, ICRM, IDA, IFAD, IFC, IFRCS, ILO, IMF, IMO, Interpol, IOC, IOM, IPU, ISO (correspondent), ITSO, ITU, LAES, LAIA, Mercosur (associate), MIGA, MINUSTAH, MONUSCO, NAM, OAS, OPANAL, OPCW, PCA, RG, UN, UNASUR, UNCTAD, UNESCO, UNFICYP, UNIDO, Union Latina, UNMIL, UNMIS, UNOCI, UNWTO, UPU, WCO, WFTU, WHO, WIPO, WMO, WTO</membership>
		<representation-in-usa>
			<chief>Ambassador (vacant); Charge d'Affaires Freddy BERSATTI</chief>
			<chancery>3014 Massachusetts Avenue NW, Washington, DC 20008</chancery>
			<telephone>[1] (202) 483-4410</telephone>
			<FAX>[1] (202) 328-3712</FAX>
			<consulates>Los Angeles, Miami, New York, San Francisco</consulates>
		</representation-in-usa>
		<representation-from-usa>
			<chief>Ambassador (vacant); Charge d'Affaires John CREAMER</chief>
			<embassy>Avenida Arce 2780, Casilla 425, La Paz</embassy>
			<mailing-address>P. O. Box 425, La Paz; APO AA 34032</mailing-address>
			<telephone>[591] (2) 216-8000</telephone>
			<FAX>[591] (2) 216-8111</FAX>
		</representation-from-usa>
		<flag>[object Object]</flag>
		<anthem>
			<name>&quot;Cancion Patriotica&quot; (Patriotic Song)</name>
			<by>Jose Ignacio de SANJINES/Leopoldo Benedetto VINCENTI</by>
		</anthem>
	</government>
	<economy>
		<overview>Bolivia is one of the poorest and least developed countries in Latin America. Following a disastrous economic crisis during the early 1980s, reforms spurred private investment, stimulated economic growth, and cut poverty rates in the 1990s. The period 2003-05 was characterized by political instability, racial tensions, and violent protests against plans - subsequently abandoned - to export Bolivia's newly discovered natural gas reserves to large northern hemisphere markets. In 2005, the government passed a controversial hydrocarbons law that imposed significantly higher royalties and required foreign firms then operating under risk-sharing contracts to surrender all production to the state energy company in exchange for a predetermined service fee. After higher prices for mining and hydrocarbons exports produced a fiscal surplus in 2008, the global recession in 2009 slowed growth. Nevertheless, Bolivia recorded the highest growth rate in South America that year. During 2010 an increase in world commodity prices resulted in the biggest trade surplus in history. However, a lack of foreign investment in the key sectors of mining and hydrocarbons and higher food prices pose challenges for the Bolivian economy.</overview>
		<gdp>
			<purchasing-power-parity></purchasing-power-parity>
			<official-exchange-rate>19370000000</official-exchange-rate>
			<real-growth-rate unit="%">4.2</real-growth-rate>
			<per-capita></per-capita>
			<sector unit="%">
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
		</gdp>
		<labour>
			<force>4186000</force>
			<sector>
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
			<unemployment unit=""></unemployment>
		</labour>
		<poverty>[object Object]</poverty>
		<household-income>TO DO</household-income>
		<budget>
			<revenue unit="USD"></revenue>
			<expenditure unit="USD"></expenditure>
		</budget>
		<public-debt unit="% of GDP">39.7</public-debt>
		<consumer-inflation unit="%">7.2</consumer-inflation>
		<central-bank-discount-rate unit="%">3</central-bank-discount-rate>
		<commercial-prime-lending-rate unit="%">5.75</commercial-prime-lending-rate>
		<narrow-money-stock unit="USD">5367000000</narrow-money-stock>
		<broad-money-stock unit="USD">12160000000</broad-money-stock>
		<domestic-credit-stock unit="USD">7060000000</domestic-credit-stock>
		<agriculture-products>soybeans, coffee, coca, cotton, corn, sugarcane, rice, potatoes; timber</agriculture-products>
		<industries>mining, smelting, petroleum, food and beverages, tobacco, handicrafts, clothing</industries>
		<industrial-production-growth>[object Object]</industrial-production-growth>
		<electricity unit="kWh">
			<production>6085000000</production>
			<consumption>5814000000</consumption>
			<exports>0</exports>
			<imports>0</imports>
		</electricity>
		<oil>
			<production unit="bbl/day">43740</production>
			<consumption unit="bbl/day">31070</consumption>
			<exports unit="bbl/day">5621</exports>
			<imports unit="bbl/day">17330</imports>
			<reserves unit="bbl">465000000</reserves>
		</oil>
		<natural-gas>
			<production unit="cu m">14400000000</production>
			<consumption unit="cu m">2410000000</consumption>
			<exports unit="cu m">11590000000</exports>
			<imports unit="cu m">0</imports>
			<reserves unit="cu m">750400000000</reserves>
		</natural-gas>
		<exports>
			<total unit="USD"></total>
			<commodities>natural gas, soybeans and soy products, crude petroleum, zinc ore, tin</commodities>
			<partners>Brazil 41.38%, US 13.87%, Japan 5.62%, Colombia 5.32%, South Korea 4.7%, Peru 4.16% (2009)</partners>
		</exports>
		<imports>
			<total unit="USD">5366000000</total>
			<commodities>petroleum products, plastics, paper, aircraft and aircraft parts, prepared foods, automobiles, insecticides, soybeans</commodities>
			<partners>Brazil 27.12%, Argentina 15.69%, US 12.77%, Chile 9.11%, Peru 6.85% (2009)</partners>
		</imports>
		<external-debt unit="USD">2864000000</external-debt>
		<exchange-rates>bolivianos (BOB) per US dollar -</exchange-rates>
	</economy>
	<communications>
		<telephones>
			<assessment>Bolivian National Telecommunications Company (ENTEL) was privatized in 1995 but re-nationalized in 2007; the primary trunk system is being expanded and employs digital microwave radio relay; some areas are served by fiber-optic cable; system operations, reliability, and coverage have steadily improved.</assessment>
			<domestic>most telephones are concentrated in La Paz, Santa Cruz, and other capital cities; mobile-cellular telephone use expanding rapidly and, in 2009, teledensity reached about 75 per 100 persons</domestic>
			<international>country code - 591; satellite earth station - 1 Intelsat (Atlantic Ocean) (2009)</international>
			<land-lines>810200</land-lines>
			<mobile>7148000</mobile>
		</telephones>
		<broadcast>large number of radio and television broadcasting stations with private media outlets dominating; state-owned and private radio and television stations generally operating freely, although both pro-government and anti-government groups have attacked media outlets in response to their reporting (2010)</broadcast>
		<internet>
			<tld>.bo</tld>
			<hosts>125462</hosts>
			<users>1103000</users>
		</internet>
	</communications>
	<transport>
		<airports>
			<total>881</total>
			<paved>
				<altitude min="*" max="*"></altitude>
				<altitude min="3047m" max="*">3</altitude>
				<altitude min="2438m" max="3047m">4</altitude>
				<altitude min="1524m" max="2437m">4</altitude>
				<altitude min="914m" max="1524m">5</altitude>
				<altitude min="*" max="914m"></altitude>
			</paved>
		</airports>
		<ports-and-terminals>Puerto Aguirre (inland port on the Paraguay/Parana waterway at the Bolivia/Brazil border); Bolivia has free port privileges in maritime ports in Argentina, Brazil, Chile, and Paraguay</ports-and-terminals>
	</transport>
	<military>
		<branches>Bolivian Armed Forces: Bolivian Army (Ejercito Boliviano, EB), Bolivian Navy (Fuerza Naval Boliviana, FNB; includes marines), Bolivian Air Force (Fuerza Aerea Boliviana, FAB) (2011)</branches>
		<manpower>
			<population-available>
				<male>2472</male>
				<female>2535</female>
			</population-available>
			<fit-for-service>
				<male>1762</male>
				<female>2013</female>
			</fit-for-service>
			<reaching-maturity>
				<male>108334</male>
				<female>104945</female>
			</reaching-maturity>
			<notes></notes>
		</manpower>
	</military>
	<issues>
		<disputes>Chile and Peru rebuff Bolivia's reactivated claim to restore the Atacama corridor, ceded to Chile in 1884, but Chile offers instead unrestricted but not sovereign maritime access through Chile for Bolivian natural gas; contraband smuggling, human trafficking, and illegal narcotic trafficking are problems in the porous areas of the border with Argentina</disputes>
		<drugs>world's third-largest cultivator of coca (after Colombia and Peru) with an estimated 29,500 hectares under cultivation in 2007, increased slightly when compared to 2006; third largest producer of cocaine, estimated at 120 metric tons potential pure cocaine in 2007; transit country for Peruvian and Colombian cocaine destined for Brazil, Argentina, Chile, Paraguay, and Europe; cultivation generally increasing since 2000, despite eradication and alternative crop programs; weak border controls; some money-laundering activity related to narcotics trade; major cocaine consumption
 (2008)</drugs>
	</issues>
</country>