<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<country>
	<code>ce</code>
	<name>Sri Lanka</name>
	<region>South Asia</region>
	<background>The first Sinhalese arrived in Sri Lanka late in the 6th century B.C., probably from northern India. Buddhism was introduced in about the mid-third century B.C., and a great civilization developed at the cities of Anuradhapura (kingdom from circa 200 B.C. to circa A.D. 1000) and Polonnaruwa (from about 1070 to 1200). In the 14th century, a south Indian dynasty established a Tamil kingdom in northern Sri Lanka. The coastal areas of the island were controlled by the Portuguese in the 16th century and by the Dutch in the 17th century. The island was ceded to the British in 1796, became a crown colony in 1802, and was formally united under British rule by 1815. As Ceylon, it became independent in 1948; its name was changed to Sri Lanka in 1972. Tensions between the Sinhalese majority and Tamil separatists erupted into war in 1983. After two decades of fighting, the government and Liberation Tigers of Tamil Eelam (LTTE) formalized a cease-fire in February 2002 with Norway brokering peace negotiations. Violence between the LTTE and government forces intensified in 2006, but the government regained control of the Eastern Province in 2007. By May 2009, the government announced that its military had defeated the remnants of the LTTE. Since the end of the conflict, the government has resettled tens of thousands of internally displaced persons and has undertaken a number of massive infrastructure projects to reconstruct its economy.</background>
	<geo>
		<note>strategic location near major Indian Ocean sea lanes</note>
		<location>
			<desc>Southern Asia, island in the Indian Ocean, south of India</desc>
			<coordinates>TO DO</coordinates>
		</location>
		<area>
			<total unit="sq km">65610</total>
			<land unit="sq km">64630</land>
			<water unit="sq km">980</water>
			<comparison>slightly larger than West Virginia</comparison>
		</area>
		<boundaries>
			<borders unit="km">0</borders>
			<coastline unit="km">1340</coastline>
		</boundaries>
		<maritime-claims>
			<territorial unit="nm">12</territorial>
			<contiguous unit="nm">24</contiguous>
			<economic unit="nm">200</economic>
			<continental-shelf>200 nm or to the edge of the continental margin</continental-shelf>
		</maritime-claims>
		<climate>tropical monsoon; northeast monsoon (December to March); southwest monsoon (June to October)</climate>
		<terrain>mostly low, flat to rolling plain; mountains in south-central interior</terrain>
		<elevation>
			<high>Pidurutalagala 2,524 m</high>
			<low>Indian Ocean 0 m</low>
		</elevation>
		<resources>limestone, graphite, mineral sands, gems, phosphates, clay, hydropower</resources>
		<land-use>
			<arable unit="%">13.96</arable>
			<crops unit="%">15.24</crops>
			<other unit="%">70.8</other>
		</land-use>
		<hazards>occasional cyclones and tornadoes</hazards>
		<issues>deforestation; soil erosion; wildlife populations threatened by poaching and urbanization; coastal degradation from mining activities and increased pollution; freshwater resources being polluted by industrial wastes and sewage runoff; waste disposal; air pollution in Colombo</issues>
		<water>
			<irrigated-land unit="sq km">5700</irrigated-land>
			<renewable-water unit="cu km">50</renewable-water>
			<freshwater-withdrawal>
				<total unit="cu km/yr">12.61</total>
				<per-capita unit="cu m/yr">608</per-capita>
			</freshwater-withdrawal>
		</water>
		<!--
"geo": {

		"Natural hazards": "flooding is a threat in some areas of the country (e.g., parts of Jutland, along the southern coast of the island of Lolland) that are protected from the sea by a system of dikes",
		"Environment - current issues": "air pollution, principally from vehicle and power plant emissions; nitrogen and phosphorus pollution of the North Sea; drinking and surface water becoming polluted from animal wastes and pesticides",
		"Environment - international agreements": {
			"party to:": "Air Pollution, Air Pollution-Nitrogen Oxides, Air Pollution-Persistent Organic Pollutants, Air Pollution-Sulfur 85, Air Pollution-Sulfur 94, Air Pollution-Volatile Organic Compounds, Antarctic Treaty, Biodiversity, Climate Change, Climate Change-Kyoto Protocol, Desertification, Endangered Species, Environmental Modification, Hazardous Wastes, Law of the Sea, Marine Dumping, Marine Life Conservation, Ozone Layer Protection, Ship Pollution, Tropical Timber 83, Tropical Timber 94, Wetlands, Whaling",
			"signed, but not ratified:": "none of the selected agreements"
		},
		"Geography - note": "controls Danish Straits (Skagerrak and Kattegat) linking Baltic and North Seas; about one-quarter of the population lives in greater Copenhagen"

		-->
	</geo>
	<people>
		<population>
			<total>21283</total>
			<birth unit="births/1,000 population">17.42</birth>
			<death unit="deaths/1,000 population">5.92</birth>
			<migration unit=""></migration>
			<growth unit="%">0.934</growth>
		</population>
		<age-distribution unit="percent">
			<group min="0" max="14">24.9</group>
			<group min="15" max="64">67.2</group>
			<group min="65"></group>
		</age-distribution>
		<median-age unit="years">
			<total>30.8</total>
			<male>29.7</male>
			<female>31.8</female>
		</median-age>
		<urbanization>
			<urban unit="% of total population">14</urban>
			<rate unit="% annual rate of change">1.1</urban>
			<cities>COLOMBO (capital) 681,000 (2009)</cities>
		</urbanization>
		<sex unit="male(s)/female">
			<group name="at birth" max="0">1.04</group>
			<group name="0 to 14" min="0" max="14">1.04</group>
			<group name="15 to 64" min="15" max="64">0.96</group>
			<group name="65 and over" min="65" max="0">0.86</group>
			<group name="total" min="0">0.97</group>
		</sex>
		<infant-mortality>
			<total unit="deaths/1,000 live births">9.7</total>
			<male unit="deaths/1,000 live births">10.68</male>
			<female unit="deaths/1,000 live births">8.68</female>
		</infant-mortality>
		<life-expectancy-at-birth>
			<total unit="years">75.73</total>
			<male unit="years">72.21</male>
			<female unit="years">79.38</female>
		</life-expectancy-at-birth>
		<fertility-rate unit="2.2">children born/woman</fertility-rate>
		<hiv>
			<prevalence>less than 0.1% (2009 est.)</prevalence>
			<total>2800</total>
			<deaths>fewer than 200 (2009 est.)</deaths>
		</hiv>
		<infectious-disease risk="high">
			<food-or-waterborne>bacterial diarrhea and hepatitis A</food-or-waterborne>
			<vectorborne></vectorborne>
			<water-contact></water-contact>
		</infectious-disease>
		<drinking-water-source>[object Object]</drinking-water-source>
		<sanitation-access>[object Object]</sanitation-access>
		<nationality>
			<noun>Sri Lankan(s)</noun>
			<adjective>Sri Lankan</adjective>
		</nationality>
		<ethnic-groups>Sinhalese 73.8%, Sri Lankan Moors 7.2%, Indian Tamil 4.6%, Sri Lankan Tamil 3.9%, other 0.5%, unspecified 10% (2001 census provisional data)</ethnic-groups>
		<religions>Buddhist 69.1%, Muslim 7.6%, Hindu 7.1%, Christian 6.2%, unspecified 10% (2001 census provisional data)</religions>
		<languages>[object Object]</languages>
		<literacy>
			<definition>age 15 and over can read and write</definition>
			<total unit="%">90.7</total>
			<male unit="%">92.3</male>
			<female unit="%">89.1</female>
		</literacy>
		<school-expectancy unit="years">13</school-expectancy>
		<education-expenditure unit=""></school-expectancy>
	</people>
	<government>
		<country-name>
			<long>Democratic Socialist Republic of Sri Lanka</long>
			<short>Sri Lanka</short>
		</country-name>
		<dependency></dependency>
		<government-type>republic</government-type>
		<capital>
			<name>Colombo</name>
			<coordinates>6° 56' N, 79° 51' E</coordinates>
			<time-difference>UTC+5.5 (10.5 hours ahead of Washington, DC during Standard Time)</time-difference>
		</capital>
		<administrative-divisions>9 provinces; Central, Eastern, North Central, Northern, North Western, Sabaragamuwa, Southern, Uva, Western</administrative-divisions>
		<independence>4 February 1948 (from the UK)</independence>
		<national-holiday>Independence Day, 4 February (1948)</national-holiday>
		<legal-system>mixed legal system of Roman-Dutch civil law, English common law, and Jaffna Tamil customary law</legal-system>
		<suffrage>18 years of age; universal</suffrage>
		<executive>
			<head-of-state>President Mahinda Percy RAJAPAKSA (since 19 November 2005); note - the president is both the chief of state and head of government; Dissanayake Mudiyanselage JAYARATNE holds the largely ceremonial title of prime minister (since 21 April 2010)</head-of-state>
			<head-of-government>President Mahinda Percy RAJAPAKSA (since 19 November 2005)</head-of-government>
			<cabinet>Cabinet appointed by the president in consultation with the prime minister</cabinet>
			<elections>president elected by popular vote for a six-year term (two-term limit); election last held on 26 January 2010 (next to be held in 2016)</elections>
			<election-results>Mahinda RAJAPAKSA reelected president for second term; percent of vote - Mahinda RAJAPAKSA 57.88%, Sarath FONSEKA 40.15%, other 1.97%</election-results>
		</executive>
		<legislative>
			<description>unicameral Parliament (225 seats; members elected by popular vote on the basis of an open-list, proportional representation system by electoral district to serve six-year terms)</description>
			<elections>last held on 8 April 2010 with a repoll in two electorates held on 20 April 2010 (next to be held by April 2016)</elections>
			<election-results>percent of vote by alliance or party - United People's Freedom Alliance 60.93%, United National Party 29.34%, Democratic National Alliance 5.49%, Tamil National Alliance 2.9%, other 1.94%; seats by alliance or party - United People's Freedom Alliance 144, United National Party 60, Tamil National Alliance 14, Democratic National Alliance 7</election-results>
		</legislative>
		<judicial>Supreme Court; Court of Appeals; judges for both courts are appointed by the president</judicial>
		<parties>Coalitions and leaders: Democratic National Alliance led by Janatha Vimukthi Peramuna or JVP [Somawansa AMARASINGHE]; Tamil National Alliance led by Illandai Tamil Arasu Kachchi [R. SAMPANTHAN]; United National Front led by United National Party [Ranil WICKREMESINGHE]; United People's Freedom Alliance led by Sri Lanka Freedom Party [Mahinda RAJAPAKSA]</parties>
		<pressure-groups>TO DO</pressure-groups>
		<membership>ADB, ARF, BIMSTEC, C, CP, FAO, G-11, G-15, G-24, G-77, IAEA, IBRD, ICAO, ICC, ICRM, IDA, IFAD, IFC, IFRCS, IHO, ILO, IMF, IMO, IMSO, Interpol, IOC, IOM, IPU, ISO, ITSO, ITU, ITUC, MIGA, MINURSO, MINUSTAH, MONUSCO, NAM, OAS (observer), OPCW, PCA, SAARC, SACEP, SCO (dialogue member), UN, UNCTAD, UNESCO, UNIDO, UNWTO, UPU, WCO, WFTU, WHO, WIPO, WMO, WTO</membership>
		<representation-in-usa>
			<chief>Ambassador Jaliya Chitran WICKRAMASURIYA</chief>
			<chancery>2148 Wyoming Avenue NW, Washington, DC 20008</chancery>
			<telephone>[1] (202) 483-4025 through 4028</telephone>
			<FAX>[1] (202) 232-7181</FAX>
			<consulates>Los Angeles</consulates>
		</representation-in-usa>
		<representation-from-usa>
			<chief>Ambassador Patricia A. BUTENIS</chief>
			<embassy>210 Galle Road, Colombo 3</embassy>
			<mailing-address>P. O. Box 106, Colombo</mailing-address>
			<telephone>[94] (11) 249-8500</telephone>
			<FAX>[94] (11) 243-7345</FAX>
		</representation-from-usa>
		<flag>yellow with two panels; the smaller hoist-side panel has two equal vertical bands of green (hoist side) and orange; the other larger panel depicts a yellow lion holding a sword on a dark red rectangular field that also displays a yellow bo leaf in each corner; the yellow field appears as a border around the entire flag and extends between the two panels; the lion represents Sinhalese ethnicity, the strength of the nation, and bravery; the sword demonstrates the sovereignty of the nation; the four bo leaves - symbolizing Buddhism and its influence on the country - stand for the four virtues of kindness, friendliness, happiness, and equanimity; orange signifies Sri Lankan Tamils, green the Sri Lankan Moors; dark red represents the European Burghers, but also refers to the rich colonial background of the country; yellow denotes other ethnic groups; also referred to as the Lion Flag</flag>
		<anthem>
			<name>&quot;Sri Lanka Matha&quot; (Mother Sri Lanka)</name>
			<by>Ananda SAMARKONE</by>
		</anthem>
	</government>
	<economy>
		<overview>Sri Lanka is engaging in large-scale reconstruction and development projects following the end of the 26-year conflict with the LTTE, including increasing electricity access and rebuilding its road and rail network. Additionally, Sri Lanka seeks to reduce poverty by using a combination of state directed policies and private investment promotion to spur growth in disadvantaged areas, develop small and medium enterprises, and promote increased agriculture. High levels of government funding may be difficult, as the government already is faced with high debt interest payments, a bloated civil service, and historically high budget deficits. The 2008-09 global financial crisis and recession exposed Sri Lanka's economic vulnerabilities and nearly caused a balance of payments crisis, which was alleviated by a $2.6 billion IMF standby agreement in July 2009. The end of the civil war and the IMF loan, however, have largely restored investors' confidence, reflected in part by the Sri Lankan stock market's recognition as one of the best performing markets in the world. Sri Lankan growth rates averaged nearly 5% in during the war, but increased government spending on development and fighting the LTTE in the final years spurred GDP growth to around 6-7% per year in 2006-08. After experiencing 3.5% growth in 2009, Sri Lanka's economy is poised to achieve high growth rates in the postwar period.</overview>
		<gdp>
			<purchasing-power-parity></purchasing-power-parity>
			<official-exchange-rate>49680000000</official-exchange-rate>
			<real-growth-rate unit="%">9.1</real-growth-rate>
			<per-capita></per-capita>
			<sector unit="%">
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
		</gdp>
		<labour>
			<force>8100000</force>
			<sector>
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
			<unemployment unit="%">5.4</unemployment>
		</labour>
		<poverty>[object Object]</poverty>
		<household-income>TO DO</household-income>
		<budget>
			<revenue unit="USD"></revenue>
			<expenditure unit="USD"></expenditure>
		</budget>
		<public-debt unit="% of GDP">86.7</public-debt>
		<consumer-inflation unit="%">5.6</consumer-inflation>
		<central-bank-discount-rate unit="%">7.5</central-bank-discount-rate>
		<commercial-prime-lending-rate unit="%">10.91</commercial-prime-lending-rate>
		<narrow-money-stock unit="USD">4400000000</narrow-money-stock>
		<broad-money-stock unit="USD">19720000000</broad-money-stock>
		<domestic-credit-stock unit="USD">18340000000</domestic-credit-stock>
		<agriculture-products>rice, sugarcane, grains, pulses, oilseed, spices, vegetables, fruit, tea, rubber, coconuts; milk, eggs, hides, beef; fish</agriculture-products>
		<industries>processing of rubber, tea, coconuts, tobacco and other agricultural commodities; telecommunications, insurance, banking; tourism, shipping; clothing, textiles; cement, petroleum refining, information technology services, construction</industries>
		<industrial-production-growth>[object Object]</industrial-production-growth>
		<electricity unit="kWh">
			<production>9901000000</production>
			<consumption>8417000000</consumption>
			<exports>0</exports>
			<imports>0</imports>
		</electricity>
		<oil>
			<production unit="bbl/day">0</production>
			<consumption unit="bbl/day">90000</consumption>
			<exports unit="bbl/day">968.4</exports>
			<imports unit="bbl/day">87690</imports>
			<reserves unit="bbl">0</reserves>
		</oil>
		<natural-gas>
			<production unit="cu m">0</production>
			<consumption unit="cu m">0</consumption>
			<exports unit="cu m">0</exports>
			<imports unit=""></imports>
			<reserves unit="cu m">0</reserves>
		</natural-gas>
		<exports>
			<total unit="USD"></total>
			<commodities>textiles and apparel, tea and spices; rubber manufactures; precious stones; coconut products, fish</commodities>
			<partners>US 20.59%, UK 12.87%, Italy 5.51%, Germany 5.29%, India 4.54%, Belgium 4.43% (2009)</partners>
		</exports>
		<imports>
			<total unit="USD">11600000000</total>
			<commodities>petroleum, textiles, machinery and transportation equipment, building materials, mineral products, foodstuffs</commodities>
			<partners>India 20.73%, China 13.45%, Singapore 7.26%, Iran 6.7%, South Korea 5.23% (2009)</partners>
		</imports>
		<external-debt unit="USD">17970000000</external-debt>
		<exchange-rates>Sri Lankan rupees (LKR) per US dollar -</exchange-rates>
	</economy>
	<communications>
		<telephones>
			<assessment>telephone services have improved significantly and are available in most parts of the country</assessment>
			<domestic>national trunk network consists mostly of digital microwave radio relay; fiber-optic links now in use in Colombo area and fixed wireless local loops have been installed; competition is strong in mobile cellular systems and mobile cellular subscribership is increasing</domestic>
			<international>country code - 94; the SEA-ME-WE-3 and SEA-ME-WE-4 submarine cables provide connectivity to Asia, Australia, Middle East, Europe, US; satellite earth stations - 2 Intelsat (Indian Ocean)</international>
			<land-lines>3523000</land-lines>
			<mobile>15868000</mobile>
		</telephones>
		<broadcast>government operates 2 television channels and a radio network; multi-channel satellite and cable TV subscription services are obtainable; 8 private TV stations and about a dozen private radio stations in operation (2008)</broadcast>
		<internet>
			<tld>.lk</tld>
			<hosts>8865</hosts>
			<users>1777000</users>
		</internet>
	</communications>
	<transport>
		<airports>
			<total>18</total>
			<paved>
				<altitude min="*" max="*"></altitude>
				<altitude min="3047m" max="*">1</altitude>
				<altitude min="2438m" max="3047m"></altitude>
				<altitude min="1524m" max="2437m">6</altitude>
				<altitude min="914m" max="1524m">7</altitude>
				<altitude min="*" max="914m"></altitude>
			</paved>
		</airports>
		<ports-and-terminals>Colombo</ports-and-terminals>
	</transport>
	<military>
		<branches>Sri Lanka Army, Sri Lanka Navy, Sri Lanka Air Force (2010)</branches>
		<manpower>
			<population-available>
				<male>5342</male>
				<female>5466</female>
			</population-available>
			<fit-for-service>
				<male>4177</male>
				<female>4574</female>
			</fit-for-service>
			<reaching-maturity>
				<male>167026</male>
				<female>162587</female>
			</reaching-maturity>
			<notes></notes>
		</manpower>
	</military>
	<issues>
		<disputes>none</disputes>
		<drugs></drugs>
	</issues>
</country>