<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<country>
	<code>dr</code>
	<name>Dominican Republic</name>
	<region>Central America and Caribbean</region>
	<background>The Taino - indigenous inhabitants of Hispaniola prior to the arrival of the Europeans - divided the island into five chiefdoms and territories. Christopher COLUMBUS explored and claimed the island on his first voyage in 1492; it became a springboard for Spanish conquest of the Caribbean and the American mainland. In 1697, Spain recognized French dominion over the western third of the island, which in 1804 became Haiti. The remainder of the island, by then known as Santo Domingo, sought to gain its own independence in 1821 but was conquered and ruled by the Haitians for 22 years; it finally attained independence as the Dominican Republic in 1844. In 1861, the Dominicans voluntarily returned to the Spanish Empire, but two years later they launched a war that restored independence in 1865. A legacy of unsettled, mostly non-representative rule followed, capped by the dictatorship of Rafael Leonidas TRUJILLO from 1930-61. Juan BOSCH was elected president in 1962 but was deposed in a military coup in 1963. In 1965, the United States led an intervention in the midst of a civil war sparked by an uprising to restore BOSCH. In 1966, Joaquin BALAGUER defeated BOSCH in an election to become president. BALAGUER maintained a tight grip on power for most of the next 30 years when international reaction to flawed elections forced him to curtail his term in 1996. Since then, regular competitive elections have been held in which opposition candidates have won the presidency. Former President (1996-2000) Leonel FERNANDEZ Reyna won election to a new term in 2004 following a constitutional amendment allowing presidents to serve more than one term, and was since reelected to a second consecutive term.</background>
	<geo>
		<note>shares island of Hispaniola with Haiti</note>
		<location>
			<desc>Caribbean, eastern two-thirds of the island of Hispaniola, between the Caribbean Sea and the North Atlantic Ocean, east of Haiti</desc>
			<coordinates>TO DO</coordinates>
		</location>
		<area>
			<total unit="sq km">48670</total>
			<land unit="sq km">48320</land>
			<water unit="sq km">350</water>
			<comparison>slightly more than twice the size of New Hampshire</comparison>
		</area>
		<boundaries>
			<borders unit=""></borders>
			<coastline unit="km">1288</coastline>
		</boundaries>
		<maritime-claims>
			<territorial unit="nm">6</territorial>
			<contiguous unit="nm">24</contiguous>
			<economic unit="nm">200</economic>
			<continental-shelf>200 nm or to the edge of the continental margin</continental-shelf>
		</maritime-claims>
		<climate>tropical maritime; little seasonal temperature variation; seasonal variation in rainfall</climate>
		<terrain>rugged highlands and mountains with fertile valleys interspersed</terrain>
		<elevation>
			<high>Pico Duarte 3,175 m</high>
			<low>Lago Enriquillo -46 m</low>
		</elevation>
		<resources>nickel, bauxite, gold, silver</resources>
		<land-use>
			<arable unit="%">22.49</arable>
			<crops unit="%">10.26</crops>
			<other unit="%">67.25</other>
		</land-use>
		<hazards>lies in the middle of the hurricane belt and subject to severe storms from June to October; occasional flooding; periodic droughts</hazards>
		<issues>water shortages; soil eroding into the sea damages coral reefs; deforestation</issues>
		<water>
			<irrigated-land unit="sq km">2750</irrigated-land>
			<renewable-water unit="cu km">21</renewable-water>
			<freshwater-withdrawal>
				<total unit="cu km/yr">3.39</total>
				<per-capita unit="cu m/yr">381</per-capita>
			</freshwater-withdrawal>
		</water>
		<!--
"geo": {

		"Natural hazards": "flooding is a threat in some areas of the country (e.g., parts of Jutland, along the southern coast of the island of Lolland) that are protected from the sea by a system of dikes",
		"Environment - current issues": "air pollution, principally from vehicle and power plant emissions; nitrogen and phosphorus pollution of the North Sea; drinking and surface water becoming polluted from animal wastes and pesticides",
		"Environment - international agreements": {
			"party to:": "Air Pollution, Air Pollution-Nitrogen Oxides, Air Pollution-Persistent Organic Pollutants, Air Pollution-Sulfur 85, Air Pollution-Sulfur 94, Air Pollution-Volatile Organic Compounds, Antarctic Treaty, Biodiversity, Climate Change, Climate Change-Kyoto Protocol, Desertification, Endangered Species, Environmental Modification, Hazardous Wastes, Law of the Sea, Marine Dumping, Marine Life Conservation, Ozone Layer Protection, Ship Pollution, Tropical Timber 83, Tropical Timber 94, Wetlands, Whaling",
			"signed, but not ratified:": "none of the selected agreements"
		},
		"Geography - note": "controls Danish Straits (Skagerrak and Kattegat) linking Baltic and North Seas; about one-quarter of the population lives in greater Copenhagen"

		-->
	</geo>
	<people>
		<population>
			<total>9956</total>
			<birth unit="births/1,000 population">19.67</birth>
			<death unit="deaths/1,000 population">4.35</birth>
			<migration unit=""></migration>
			<growth unit="%">1.331</growth>
		</population>
		<age-distribution unit="percent">
			<group min="0" max="14">29.5</group>
			<group min="15" max="64">64</group>
			<group min="65"></group>
		</age-distribution>
		<median-age unit="years">
			<total>26.1</total>
			<male>26</male>
			<female>26.3</female>
		</median-age>
		<urbanization>
			<urban unit="% of total population">69</urban>
			<rate unit="% annual rate of change">2.1</urban>
			<cities>SANTO DOMINGO (capital) 2.138 million (2009)</cities>
		</urbanization>
		<sex unit="male(s)/female">
			<group name="at birth" max="0">1.04</group>
			<group name="0 to 14" min="0" max="14">1.04</group>
			<group name="15 to 64" min="15" max="64">1.04</group>
			<group name="65 and over" min="65" max="0">0.86</group>
			<group name="total" min="0">1.03</group>
		</sex>
		<infant-mortality>
			<total unit="deaths/1,000 live births">22.22</total>
			<male unit="deaths/1,000 live births">24.21</male>
			<female unit="deaths/1,000 live births">20.14</female>
		</infant-mortality>
		<life-expectancy-at-birth>
			<total unit="years">77.31</total>
			<male unit="years">75.16</male>
			<female unit="years">79.55</female>
		</life-expectancy-at-birth>
		<fertility-rate unit="2.44">children born/woman</fertility-rate>
		<hiv>
			<prevalence>[object Object]</prevalence>
			<total>57000</total>
			<deaths>2300</deaths>
		</hiv>
		<infectious-disease risk="high">
			<food-or-waterborne>bacterial diarrhea, hepatitis A, and typhoid fever</food-or-waterborne>
			<vectorborne>dengue fever and malaria</vectorborne>
			<water-contact></water-contact>
		</infectious-disease>
		<drinking-water-source>[object Object]</drinking-water-source>
		<sanitation-access>[object Object]</sanitation-access>
		<nationality>
			<noun>Dominican(s)</noun>
			<adjective>Dominican</adjective>
		</nationality>
		<ethnic-groups>mixed 73%, white 16%, black 11%</ethnic-groups>
		<religions>Roman Catholic 95%, other 5%</religions>
		<languages>Spanish (official)</languages>
		<literacy>
			<definition>age 15 and over can read and write</definition>
			<total unit="%">87</total>
			<male unit="%">86.8</male>
			<female unit="%">87.2</female>
		</literacy>
		<school-expectancy unit="years">12</school-expectancy>
		<education-expenditure unit="% of GDP">2.3</school-expectancy>
	</people>
	<government>
		<country-name>
			<long>Dominican Republic</long>
			<short>The Dominican</short>
		</country-name>
		<dependency></dependency>
		<government-type>democratic republic</government-type>
		<capital>
			<name>Santo Domingo</name>
			<coordinates>18° 28' N, 69° 54' W</coordinates>
			<time-difference>UTC-4 (1 hour ahead of Washington, DC during Standard Time)</time-difference>
		</capital>
		<administrative-divisions>31 provinces (provincias, singular - provincia) and 1 district* (distrito); Azua, Bahoruco, Barahona, Dajabon, Distrito Nacional*, Duarte, El Seibo, Elias Pina, Espaillat, Hato Mayor, Independencia, La Altagracia, La Romana, La Vega, Maria Trinidad Sanchez, Monsenor Nouel, Monte Cristi, Monte Plata, Pedernales, Peravia, Puerto Plata, Salcedo, Samana, San Cristobal, San Jose de Ocoa, San Juan, San Pedro de Macoris, Sanchez Ramirez, Santiago, Santiago Rodriguez, Santo Domingo, Valverde</administrative-divisions>
		<independence>27 February 1844 (from Haiti)</independence>
		<national-holiday>Independence Day, 27 February (1844)</national-holiday>
		<legal-system>civil law system based on the French civil code; Criminal Procedures Code modified in 2004 to include important elements of an accusatory system</legal-system>
		<suffrage>18 years of age, universal and compulsory; married persons regardless of age; note - members of the armed forces and national police cannot vote</suffrage>
		<executive>
			<head-of-state>President Leonel FERNANDEZ Reyna (since 16 August 2004); Vice President Rafael ALBURQUERQUE de Castro (since 16 August 2004); note - the president is both the chief of state and head of government</head-of-state>
			<head-of-government>President Leonel FERNANDEZ Reyna (since 16 August 2004); Vice President Rafael ALBURQUERQUE de Castro (since 16 August 2004)</head-of-government>
			<cabinet>Cabinet nominated by the president</cabinet>
			<elections>president and vice president elected on the same ticket by popular vote for four-year terms; election last held on 16 May 2008 (next to be held in May 2012)</elections>
			<election-results>Leonel FERNANDEZ reelected president; percent of vote - Leonel FERNANDEZ 53.6%, Miguel VARGAS 41%, Amable ARISTY less than 5%</election-results>
		</executive>
		<legislative>
			<description>bicameral National Congress or Congreso Nacional consists of the Senate or Senado (32 seats; members elected by popular vote to serve four-year terms) and the House of Representatives or Camara de Diputados (183 seats; members are elected by popular vote to serve four-year terms)</description>
			<elections>Senate - last held on 16 May 2010 (next to be held in May 2016); House of Representatives - last held on 16 May 2010 (next to be held in May 2016); in order to synchronize presidential, legislative, and local elections for 2016, those members elected in 2010 will actually serve terms of six years</elections>
			<election-results>Senate - percent of vote by party - NA; seats by party - PLD 31, PRD 1; House of Representatives - percent of vote by party - NA; seats by party - PLD 105, PRD 75, PRSC 3</election-results>
		</legislative>
		<judicial>Supreme Court or Corte Suprema (judges are appointed by the National Judicial Council comprised of the president, the leaders of both chambers of congress, the president of the Supreme Court, and an additional non-governing party congressional representative)</judicial>
		<parties>Dominican Liberation Party or PLD [Leonel FERNANDEZ Reyna]; Dominican Revolutionary Party or PRD [Ramon ALBURQUERQUE]; National Progressive Front [Vincent CASTILLO, Pelegrin CASTILLO]; Social Christian Reformist Party or PRSC [Enrique ANTUN]</parties>
		<pressure-groups>TO DO</pressure-groups>
		<membership>ACP, AOSIS, BCIE, Caricom (observer), FAO, G-77, IADB, IAEA, IBRD, ICAO, ICC, ICRM, IDA, IFAD, IFC, IFRCS, IHO, ILO, IMF, IMO, Interpol, IOC, IOM, IPU, ISO (correspondent), ITSO, ITU, ITUC, LAES, LAIA (observer), MIGA, NAM, OAS, OPANAL, OPCW, PCA, PetroCaribe, RG, SICA (associated member), UN, UNCTAD, UNESCO, UNIDO, Union Latina, UNWTO, UPU, WCO, WFTU, WHO, WIPO, WMO, WTO</membership>
		<representation-in-usa>
			<chief>Ambassador Roberto B. SALADIN Selin</chief>
			<chancery>1715 22nd Street NW, Washington, DC 20008</chancery>
			<telephone>[1] (202) 332-6280</telephone>
			<FAX>[1] (202) 265-8057</FAX>
			<consulates>Anchorage, Boston, Chicago, Mayaguez (Puerto Rico), Miami, New Orleans, New York, San Juan (Puerto Rico), Sun Valley (California)</consulates>
		</representation-in-usa>
		<representation-from-usa>
			<chief>Ambassador Raul H. YZAGUIRRE</chief>
			<embassy>corner of Calle Cesar Nicolas Penson and Calle Leopoldo Navarro, Santo Domingo</embassy>
			<mailing-address>Unit 5500, APO AA 34041-5500</mailing-address>
			<telephone>[1] (809) 221-2171</telephone>
			<FAX>[1] (809) 686-7437</FAX>
		</representation-from-usa>
		<flag>a centered white cross that extends to the edges divides the flag into four rectangles - the top ones are blue (hoist side) and red, and the bottom ones are red (hoist side) and blue; a small coat of arms featuring a shield supported by a laurel branch (left) and a palm branch (right) is at the center of the cross; above the shield a blue ribbon displays the motto, DIOS, PATRIA, LIBERTAD (God, Fatherland, Liberty), and below the shield, REPUBLICA DOMINICANA appears on a red ribbon; in the shield a bible is opened to a verse that reads &quot;Y la verdad nos hara libre&quot; (And the truth shall set you free); blue stands for liberty, white for salvation, and red for the blood of heroes</flag>
		<anthem>
			<name>&quot;Himno Nacional&quot; (National Anthem)</name>
			<by>Emilio PRUD&quot;HOMME/Jose REYES</by>
		</anthem>
	</government>
	<economy>
		<overview>The Dominican Republic has long been viewed primarily as an exporter of sugar, coffee, and tobacco, but in recent years the service sector has overtaken agriculture as the economy's largest employer, due to growth in telecommunications, tourism, and free trade zones. The economy is highly dependent upon the US, the destination for nearly 60% of exports. Remittances from the US amount to about a tenth of GDP, equivalent to almost half of exports and three-quarters of tourism receipts. The country suffers from marked income inequality; the poorest half of the population receives less than one-fifth of GDP, while the richest 10% enjoys nearly 40% of GDP. High unemployment and underemployment remains an important long-term challenge. The Central America-Dominican Republic Free Trade Agreement (CAFTA-DR) came into force in March 2007, boosting investment and exports and reducing losses to the Asian garment industry. The growth of the Dominican Republic's economy rebounded in 2010 from the global recession, and remains one of the fastest growing in the region.</overview>
		<gdp>
			<purchasing-power-parity></purchasing-power-parity>
			<official-exchange-rate>51630000000</official-exchange-rate>
			<real-growth-rate unit="%">7.8</real-growth-rate>
			<per-capita></per-capita>
			<sector unit="%">
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
		</gdp>
		<labour>
			<force>4498000</force>
			<sector>
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
			<unemployment unit="%">14.2</unemployment>
		</labour>
		<poverty>[object Object]</poverty>
		<household-income>TO DO</household-income>
		<budget>
			<revenue unit="USD"></revenue>
			<expenditure unit="USD"></expenditure>
		</budget>
		<public-debt unit="% of GDP">41.7</public-debt>
		<consumer-inflation unit="%">6.3</consumer-inflation>
		<central-bank-discount-rate unit="%"></central-bank-discount-rate>
		<commercial-prime-lending-rate unit="%">18.14</commercial-prime-lending-rate>
		<narrow-money-stock unit="USD">4734000000</narrow-money-stock>
		<broad-money-stock unit="USD">15710000000</broad-money-stock>
		<domestic-credit-stock unit="USD">21630000000</domestic-credit-stock>
		<agriculture-products>sugarcane, coffee, cotton, cocoa, tobacco, rice, beans, potatoes, corn, bananas; cattle, pigs, dairy products, beef, eggs</agriculture-products>
		<industries>tourism, sugar processing, ferronickel and gold mining, textiles, cement, tobacco</industries>
		<industrial-production-growth>[object Object]</industrial-production-growth>
		<electricity unit="kWh">
			<production>14020000000</production>
			<consumption>12700000000</consumption>
			<exports>0</exports>
			<imports>0</imports>
		</electricity>
		<oil>
			<production unit="bbl/day">0</production>
			<consumption unit="bbl/day">118000</consumption>
			<exports unit="bbl/day">0</exports>
			<imports unit="bbl/day">116200</imports>
			<reserves unit="bbl">0</reserves>
		</oil>
		<natural-gas>
			<production unit="cu m">0</production>
			<consumption unit="cu m">470000000</consumption>
			<exports unit="cu m">0</exports>
			<imports unit="cu m">470000000</imports>
			<reserves unit="cu m">0</reserves>
		</natural-gas>
		<exports>
			<total unit="USD"></total>
			<commodities>ferronickel, sugar, gold, silver, coffee, cocoa, tobacco, meats, consumer goods</commodities>
			<partners>US 54.08%, Haiti 9.78% (2009)</partners>
		</exports>
		<imports>
			<total unit="USD">14530000000</total>
			<commodities>foodstuffs, petroleum, cotton and fabrics, chemicals and pharmaceuticals</commodities>
			<partners>US 42.79%, Venezuela 7.04%, Mexico 6.17%, Colombia 5.59% (2009)</partners>
		</imports>
		<external-debt unit="USD">13090000000</external-debt>
		<exchange-rates>Dominican pesos (DOP) per US dollar -</exchange-rates>
	</economy>
	<communications>
		<telephones>
			<assessment>relatively efficient system based on island-wide microwave radio relay network</assessment>
			<domestic>fixed-line teledensity is about 10 per 100 persons; multiple providers of mobile-cellular service with a subscribership of roughly 75 per 100 persons</domestic>
			<international>country code - 1-809; landing point for the Americas Region Caribbean Ring System (ARCOS-1), Antillas 1, and the Fibralink submarine cables that provide links to South and Central America, parts of the Caribbean, and US; satellite earth station - 1 Intelsat (Atlantic Ocean) (2009)</international>
			<land-lines>965400</land-lines>
			<mobile>8630000</mobile>
		</telephones>
		<broadcast>combination of state-owned and privately-owned broadcast media; 1 state-owned television network and a number of private TV networks; networks operate repeaters to extend signals throughout country; combination of state-owned and privately-owned radio stations; more than 300 radio stations operating (2007)</broadcast>
		<internet>
			<tld>.do</tld>
			<hosts>283298</hosts>
			<users>2701000</users>
		</internet>
	</communications>
	<transport>
		<airports>
			<total>35</total>
			<paved>
				<altitude min="*" max="*"></altitude>
				<altitude min="3047m" max="*">3</altitude>
				<altitude min="2438m" max="3047m">4</altitude>
				<altitude min="1524m" max="2437m">4</altitude>
				<altitude min="914m" max="1524m">4</altitude>
				<altitude min="*" max="914m"></altitude>
			</paved>
		</airports>
		<ports-and-terminals>Andres (Boca Chica), Puerto Haina, Puerto Plata, Santo Domingo</ports-and-terminals>
	</transport>
	<military>
		<branches>Army, Navy (Marina de Guerra), Air Force (Fuerza Aerea Dominicana, FAD) (2011)</branches>
		<manpower>
			<population-available>
				<male>2580</male>
				<female>2464</female>
			</population-available>
			<fit-for-service>
				<male>2188</male>
				<female>2090</female>
			</fit-for-service>
			<reaching-maturity>
				<male>100047</male>
				<female>96302</female>
			</reaching-maturity>
			<notes></notes>
		</manpower>
	</military>
	<issues>
		<disputes>Haitian migrants cross the porous border into the Dominican Republic to find work; illegal migrants from the Dominican Republic cross the Mona Passage each year to Puerto Rico to find better work</disputes>
		<drugs>transshipment point for South American drugs destined for the US and Europe; has become a transshipment point for ecstasy from the Netherlands and Belgium destined for US and Canada; substantial money laundering activity in particular by Colombian narcotics traffickers; significant amphetamine consumption
 (2008)</drugs>
	</issues>
</country>