<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<country>
	<code>ec</code>
	<name>Ecuador</name>
	<region>South America</region>
	<background>What is now Ecuador formed part of the northern Inca Empire until the Spanish conquest in 1533. Quito became a seat of Spanish colonial government in 1563 and part of the Viceroyalty of New Granada in 1717. The territories of the Viceroyalty - New Granada (Colombia), Venezuela, and Quito - gained their independence between 1819 and 1822 and formed a federation known as Gran Colombia. When Quito withdrew in 1830, the traditional name was changed in favor of the &quot;Republic of the Equator.&quot; Between 1904 and 1942, Ecuador lost territories in a series of conflicts with its neighbors. A border war with Peru that flared in 1995 was resolved in 1999. Although Ecuador marked 30 years of civilian governance in 2004, the period was marred by political instability. Protests in Quito contributed to the mid-term ouster of three of Ecuador's last four democratically elected Presidents. In September 2008, voters approved a new constitution, Ecuador's 20th since gaining independence. General elections, under the new constitutional framework, were held in April 2009, and voters re-elected President Rafael CORREA.</background>
	<geo>
		<note>Cotopaxi in Andes is highest active volcano in world</note>
		<location>
			<desc>Western South America, bordering the Pacific Ocean at the Equator, between Colombia and Peru</desc>
			<coordinates>TO DO</coordinates>
		</location>
		<area>
			<total unit="sq km">283561</total>
			<land unit="sq km">276841</land>
			<water unit="sq km">6720</water>
			<comparison>slightly smaller than Nevada</comparison>
		</area>
		<boundaries>
			<borders unit=""></borders>
			<coastline unit="km">2237</coastline>
		</boundaries>
		<maritime-claims>
			<territorial unit="nm">200</territorial>
			<contiguous unit=""></contiguous>
			<economic unit=""></economic>
			<continental-shelf>100 nm from 2,500-m isobath</continental-shelf>
		</maritime-claims>
		<climate>tropical along coast, becoming cooler inland at higher elevations; tropical in Amazonian jungle lowlands</climate>
		<terrain>coastal plain (costa), inter-Andean central highlands (sierra), and flat to rolling eastern jungle (oriente)</terrain>
		<elevation>
			<high>Chimborazo 6,267 m</high>
			<low>Pacific Ocean 0 m</low>
		</elevation>
		<resources>petroleum, fish, timber, hydropower</resources>
		<land-use>
			<arable unit="%">5.71</arable>
			<crops unit="%">4.81</crops>
			<other unit="%">89.48</other>
		</land-use>
		<hazards>[object Object]</hazards>
		<issues>deforestation; soil erosion; desertification; water pollution; pollution from oil production wastes in ecologically sensitive areas of the Amazon Basin and Galapagos Islands</issues>
		<water>
			<irrigated-land unit="sq km">8650</irrigated-land>
			<renewable-water unit="cu km">432</renewable-water>
			<freshwater-withdrawal>
				<total unit="cu km/yr">16.98</total>
				<per-capita unit="cu m/yr">1283</per-capita>
			</freshwater-withdrawal>
		</water>
		<!--
"geo": {

		"Natural hazards": "flooding is a threat in some areas of the country (e.g., parts of Jutland, along the southern coast of the island of Lolland) that are protected from the sea by a system of dikes",
		"Environment - current issues": "air pollution, principally from vehicle and power plant emissions; nitrogen and phosphorus pollution of the North Sea; drinking and surface water becoming polluted from animal wastes and pesticides",
		"Environment - international agreements": {
			"party to:": "Air Pollution, Air Pollution-Nitrogen Oxides, Air Pollution-Persistent Organic Pollutants, Air Pollution-Sulfur 85, Air Pollution-Sulfur 94, Air Pollution-Volatile Organic Compounds, Antarctic Treaty, Biodiversity, Climate Change, Climate Change-Kyoto Protocol, Desertification, Endangered Species, Environmental Modification, Hazardous Wastes, Law of the Sea, Marine Dumping, Marine Life Conservation, Ozone Layer Protection, Ship Pollution, Tropical Timber 83, Tropical Timber 94, Wetlands, Whaling",
			"signed, but not ratified:": "none of the selected agreements"
		},
		"Geography - note": "controls Danish Straits (Skagerrak and Kattegat) linking Baltic and North Seas; about one-quarter of the population lives in greater Copenhagen"

		-->
	</geo>
	<people>
		<population>
			<total>15007</total>
			<birth unit="births/1,000 population">19.96</birth>
			<death unit="deaths/1,000 population">5</birth>
			<migration unit=""></migration>
			<growth unit="%">1.443</growth>
		</population>
		<age-distribution unit="percent">
			<group min="0" max="14">30.1</group>
			<group min="15" max="64">63.5</group>
			<group min="65"></group>
		</age-distribution>
		<median-age unit="years">
			<total>25.7</total>
			<male>25</male>
			<female>26.3</female>
		</median-age>
		<urbanization>
			<urban unit="% of total population">67</urban>
			<rate unit="% annual rate of change">2</urban>
			<cities>Guayaquil 2.634 million; QUITO (capital) 1.801 million (2009)</cities>
		</urbanization>
		<sex unit="male(s)/female">
			<group name="at birth" max="0">1.05</group>
			<group name="0 to 14" min="0" max="14">1.04</group>
			<group name="15 to 64" min="15" max="64">0.97</group>
			<group name="65 and over" min="65" max="0">0.93</group>
			<group name="total" min="0">0.99</group>
		</sex>
		<infant-mortality>
			<total unit="deaths/1,000 live births">19.65</total>
			<male unit="deaths/1,000 live births">23.02</male>
			<female unit="deaths/1,000 live births">16.11</female>
		</infant-mortality>
		<life-expectancy-at-birth>
			<total unit="years">75.73</total>
			<male unit="years">72.79</male>
			<female unit="years">78.82</female>
		</life-expectancy-at-birth>
		<fertility-rate unit="2.42">children born/woman</fertility-rate>
		<hiv>
			<prevalence>[object Object]</prevalence>
			<total>37000</total>
			<deaths>2200</deaths>
		</hiv>
		<infectious-disease risk="high">
			<food-or-waterborne>bacterial diarrhea, hepatitis A, and typhoid fever</food-or-waterborne>
			<vectorborne>dengue fever and malaria</vectorborne>
			<water-contact></water-contact>
		</infectious-disease>
		<drinking-water-source>[object Object]</drinking-water-source>
		<sanitation-access>[object Object]</sanitation-access>
		<nationality>
			<noun>Ecuadorian(s)</noun>
			<adjective>Ecuadorian</adjective>
		</nationality>
		<ethnic-groups>mestizo (mixed Amerindian and white) 65%, Amerindian 25%, Spanish and others 7%, black 3%</ethnic-groups>
		<religions>Roman Catholic 95%, other 5%</religions>
		<languages>Spanish (official), Amerindian languages (especially Quechua)</languages>
		<literacy>
			<definition>age 15 and over can read and write</definition>
			<total unit="%">91</total>
			<male unit="%">92.3</male>
			<female unit="%">89.7</female>
		</literacy>
		<school-expectancy unit="years">14</school-expectancy>
		<education-expenditure unit=""></school-expectancy>
	</people>
	<government>
		<country-name>
			<long>Republic of Ecuador</long>
			<short>Ecuador</short>
		</country-name>
		<dependency></dependency>
		<government-type>republic</government-type>
		<capital>
			<name>Quito</name>
			<coordinates>0° 13' S, 78° 30' W</coordinates>
			<time-difference>UTC-5 (same time as Washington, DC during Standard Time)</time-difference>
		</capital>
		<administrative-divisions>24 provinces (provincias, singular - provincia); Azuay, Bolivar, Canar, Carchi, Chimborazo, Cotopaxi, El Oro, Esmeraldas, Galapagos, Guayas, Imbabura, Loja, Los Rios, Manabi, Morona-Santiago, Napo, Orellana, Pastaza, Pichincha, Santa Elena, Santo Domingo de los Tsachilas, Sucumbios, Tungurahua, Zamora-Chinchipe</administrative-divisions>
		<independence>24 May 1822 (from Spain)</independence>
		<national-holiday>Independence Day (independence of Quito), 10 August (1809)</national-holiday>
		<legal-system>civil law based on the Chilean civil code with modifications</legal-system>
		<suffrage>16 years of age; universal, compulsory for persons ages 18-65, optional for other eligible voters</suffrage>
		<executive>
			<head-of-state>President Rafael CORREA Delgado (since 15 January 2007); Vice President Lenin MORENO Garces (since 15 January 2007); note - the president is both the chief of state and head of government</head-of-state>
			<head-of-government>President Rafael CORREA Delgado (since 15 January 2007); Vice President Lenin MORENO Garces (since 15 January 2007)</head-of-government>
			<cabinet>Cabinet appointed by the president</cabinet>
			<elections>the president and vice president elected on the same ticket by popular vote for a four-year term and can be re-elected for another consecutive term; election last held on 26 April 2009 (next to be held in 2013)</elections>
			<election-results>President Rafael CORREA Delgado reelected president; percent of vote - Rafael CORREA Delgado 52%; Lucio GUTIERREZ 28.2%; Alvaro NOBOA 11.4%; other 8.4%</election-results>
		</executive>
		<legislative>
			<description>unicameral National Assembly or Asamblea Nacional (124 seats; members are elected through a party-list proportional representation system to serve four-year terms)</description>
			<elections>last held on 26 April 2009 (next to be held in 2013)</elections>
			<election-results>percent of vote by party - NA; seats by party - PAIS 59, PSP 19, PSC 11, PRIAN 7, MPD 5, PRE 3, other 20; note - defections by members of National Assembly are commonplace, resulting in frequent changes in the numbers of seats held by the various parties</election-results>
		</legislative>
		<judicial>National Court of Justice or Corte Nacional de Justicia (according to the Constitution, justices are elected through a procedure overseen by the Judiciary Council); Constitutional Court or Corte Constitucional (Constitutional Court justices are appointed by a commission composed of two delegates each from the Executive, Legislative, and Transparency branches of government)</judicial>
		<parties>Alianza PAIS movement [Rafael Vicente CORREA Delgado]; Democratic Left or ID [Dalton BACIGALUPO]; Ethical and Democratic Network or RED [Martha ROLDOS]; Institutional Renewal and National Action Party or PRIAN [Vicente TAIANO]; Pachakutik Plurinational Unity Movement - New Country or MUPP-NP [Rafael ANTUNI]; Patriotic Society Party or PSP [Lucio GUTIERREZ Borbua]; Popular Democratic Movement or MPD [Luis VILLACIS]; Roldosist Party or PRE [Abdala BUCARAM Pulley, director]; Social Christian Party or PSC [Pascual DEL CIOPPO]; Socialist Party - Broad Front or PS-FA [Rafael QUINTERO]; Warrior's Spirit Movement [Jaime NEBOT]</parties>
		<pressure-groups>TO DO</pressure-groups>
		<membership>CAN, FAO, G-11, G-77, IADB, IAEA, IBRD, ICAO, ICC, ICRM, IDA, IFAD, IFC, IFRCS, IHO, ILO, IMF, IMO, Interpol, IOC, IOM, IPU, ISO, ITSO, ITU, ITUC, LAES, LAIA, Mercosur (associate), MIGA, MINUSTAH, NAM, OAS, OPANAL, OPCW, OPEC, PCA, RG, UN, UNASUR, UNCTAD, UNESCO, UNHCR, UNIDO, Union Latina, UNMIL, UNMIS, UNOCI, UNWTO, UPU, WCO, WFTU, WHO, WIPO, WMO, WTO</membership>
		<representation-in-usa>
			<chief>Ambassador Luis Benigno GALLEGOS Chiriboga</chief>
			<chancery>2535 15th Street NW, Washington, DC 20009</chancery>
			<telephone>[1] (202) 234-7200</telephone>
			<FAX>[1] (202) 667-3482</FAX>
			<consulates>Atlanta, Boston, Chicago, Dallas, Houston, Las Vegas, Los Angeles, Miami, Minneapolis, New Haven, New Orleans, New York, Newark (New Jersey), Phoenix, San Francisco, San Juan (Puerto Rico)</consulates>
		</representation-in-usa>
		<representation-from-usa>
			<chief>Ambassador Heather HODGES</chief>
			<embassy>Avenida Avigiras E12-170 y Avenida Eloy Alfaro, Quito</embassy>
			<mailing-address>Avenida Guayacanes N52-205 y Avenida Avigiras</mailing-address>
			<telephone>[593] (2) 398-5000</telephone>
			<FAX>[593] (2) 398-5100</FAX>
		</representation-from-usa>
		<flag>[object Object]</flag>
		<anthem>
			<name>&quot;Salve, Oh Patria!&quot; (We Salute You Our Homeland)</name>
			<by>Juan Leon MERA/Antonio NEUMANE</by>
		</anthem>
	</government>
	<economy>
		<overview>Ecuador is substantially dependent on its petroleum resources, which have accounted for more than half of the country's export earnings and approximately one-third of public sector revenues in recent years. In 1999/2000, Ecuador suffered a severe economic crisis, with GDP contracting by 5.3%. Poverty increased significantly, the banking system collapsed, and Ecuador defaulted on its external debt. In March 2000, the Congress approved a series of structural reforms that also provided for the adoption of the US dollar as legal tender. Dollarization stabilized the economy, and positive growth returned in the years that followed, helped by high oil prices, remittances, and increased non-traditional exports. From 2002-06 the economy grew an average of 5.2% per year, the highest five-year average in 25 years. After moderate growth in 2007, the economy reached a growth rate of 7.2% in 2008, in large part due to high global petroleum prices and increased public sector investment. President Rafael CORREA, who took office in January 2007, defaulted in December 2008 on Ecuador's sovereign debt, which, with a total face value of approximately US$3.2 billion, represented about 80% of Ecuador's private external debt. In May 2009, Ecuador bought back 91% of its &quot;defaulted&quot; bonds via an international auction. Economic policies under the CORREA administration - including an announcement in late 2009 of its intention to terminate 13 bilateral investment treaties, including one with the United States - have generated economic uncertainty and discouraged private investment. The Ecuadorian economy contracted 0.4% in 2009 due to the global financial crisis and to the sharp decline in world oil prices and remittance flows. Growth picked up to a 3.7% rate in 2010, according to Ecuadorian government estimates.</overview>
		<gdp>
			<purchasing-power-parity></purchasing-power-parity>
			<official-exchange-rate>58910000000</official-exchange-rate>
			<real-growth-rate unit="%">3.2</real-growth-rate>
			<per-capita></per-capita>
			<sector unit="%">
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
		</gdp>
		<labour>
			<force>4.59 million (urban) (2010 est.)</force>
			<sector>
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
			<unemployment unit="%">5</unemployment>
		</labour>
		<poverty>[object Object]</poverty>
		<household-income>TO DO</household-income>
		<budget>
			<revenue unit="USD"></revenue>
			<expenditure unit="USD"></expenditure>
		</budget>
		<public-debt unit="% of GDP">23.2</public-debt>
		<consumer-inflation unit="%">3.3</consumer-inflation>
		<central-bank-discount-rate unit="%">8.68</central-bank-discount-rate>
		<commercial-prime-lending-rate unit="%">19</commercial-prime-lending-rate>
		<narrow-money-stock unit="USD">6198000000</narrow-money-stock>
		<broad-money-stock unit="USD">21220000000</broad-money-stock>
		<domestic-credit-stock unit="USD">17470000000</domestic-credit-stock>
		<agriculture-products>bananas, coffee, cocoa, rice, potatoes, manioc (tapioca), plantains, sugarcane; cattle, sheep, pigs, beef, pork, dairy products; balsa wood; fish, shrimp</agriculture-products>
		<industries>petroleum, food processing, textiles, wood products, chemicals</industries>
		<industrial-production-growth>[object Object]</industrial-production-growth>
		<electricity unit="kWh">
			<production>16420000000.000002</production>
			<consumption>15810000000</consumption>
			<exports>20680000</exports>
			<imports>1120000000</imports>
		</electricity>
		<oil>
			<production unit="bbl/day">485700</production>
			<consumption unit="bbl/day">181000</consumption>
			<exports unit="bbl/day">338000</exports>
			<imports unit="bbl/day">80500</imports>
			<reserves unit="bbl">6542000000</reserves>
		</oil>
		<natural-gas>
			<production unit="cu m">283200000</production>
			<consumption unit="cu m">283200000</consumption>
			<exports unit="cu m">0</exports>
			<imports unit="cu m">0</imports>
			<reserves unit="cu m">7985000000</reserves>
		</natural-gas>
		<exports>
			<total unit="USD"></total>
			<commodities>petroleum, bananas, cut flowers, shrimp, cacao, coffee, wood, fish</commodities>
			<partners>US 33.5%, Peru 6.8%, Chile 6.5%, Columbia 4.9% (2009 est.)</partners>
		</exports>
		<imports>
			<total unit="USD">17650000000</total>
			<commodities>industrial materials, fuels and lubricants, nondurable consumer goods</commodities>
			<partners>US 25.4%, Columbia 10.6%, Venezuela 6.5%, Brazil 4.5% (2009 est.)</partners>
		</imports>
		<external-debt unit="USD">14710000000</external-debt>
		<exchange-rates>the US dollar became El Salvador's currency in 2001</exchange-rates>
	</economy>
	<communications>
		<telephones>
			<assessment>generally elementary but being expanded</assessment>
			<domestic>fixed-line services provided by multiple telecommunications operators; fixed-line teledensity stands at about 14 per 100 persons; mobile-cellular use has surged and subscribership reached about 95 per 100 persons in 2009</domestic>
			<international>country code - 593; landing points for the PAN-AM and South America-1 submarine cables that provide links to the west coast of South America, Panama, Colombia, Venezuela, and extending onward to Aruba and the US Virgin Islands in the Caribbean; satellite earth station - 1 Intelsat (Atlantic Ocean) (2009)</international>
			<land-lines>2004000</land-lines>
			<mobile>13635000</mobile>
		</telephones>
		<broadcast>many TV and radio stations are privately-owned; the government owns and runs  one national television station and controls two others, as well as multiple radio stations; Ecuador has multiple television networks and  TV channels, and a large number of local channels; more than 400 radio stations; broadcast media required by law to give the government free air time to broadcast programs produced by the state (2007)</broadcast>
		<internet>
			<tld>.ec</tld>
			<hosts>67975</hosts>
			<users>3352000</users>
		</internet>
	</communications>
	<transport>
		<airports>
			<total>428</total>
			<paved>
				<altitude min="*" max="*"></altitude>
				<altitude min="3047m" max="*">3</altitude>
				<altitude min="2438m" max="3047m">5</altitude>
				<altitude min="1524m" max="2437m">17</altitude>
				<altitude min="914m" max="1524m">25</altitude>
				<altitude min="*" max="914m"></altitude>
			</paved>
		</airports>
		<ports-and-terminals>Esmeraldas, Guayaquil, Manta, Puerto Bolivar</ports-and-terminals>
	</transport>
	<military>
		<branches>Ecuadorian Armed Forces: Ecuadorian Land Force (Fuerza Terrestre Ecuatoriana, FTE), Ecuadorian Navy (Fuerza Naval del Ecuador (FNE), includes Naval Infantry, Naval Aviation, Coast Guard), Ecuadorian Air Force (Fuerza Aerea Ecuatoriana, FAE) (2011)</branches>
		<manpower>
			<population-available>
				<male>3728</male>
				<female>3844</female>
			</population-available>
			<fit-for-service>
				<male>2834</male>
				<female>3269</female>
			</fit-for-service>
			<reaching-maturity>
				<male>152593</male>
				<female>147143</female>
			</reaching-maturity>
			<notes></notes>
		</manpower>
	</military>
	<issues>
		<disputes>organized illegal narcotics operations in Colombia penetrate across Ecuador's shared border, which thousands of Colombians also cross to escape the violence in their home country</disputes>
		<drugs>significant transit country for cocaine originating in Colombia and Peru, with much of the US-bound cocaine passing through Ecuadorian Pacific waters; importer of precursor chemicals used in production of illicit narcotics; attractive location for cash-placement by drug traffickers laundering money because of dollarization and weak anti-money-laundering regime; increased activity on the northern frontier by trafficking groups and Colombian insurgents
 (2008)</drugs>
	</issues>
</country>