<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<country>
	<code>eg</code>
	<name>Egypt</name>
	<region>Africa</region>
	<background>The regularity and richness of the annual Nile River flood, coupled with semi-isolation provided by deserts to the east and west, allowed for the development of one of the world's great civilizations. A unified kingdom arose circa 3200 B.C., and a series of dynasties ruled in Egypt for the next three millennia. The last native dynasty fell to the Persians in 341 B.C., who in turn were replaced by the Greeks, Romans, and Byzantines. It was the Arabs who introduced Islam and the Arabic language in the 7th century and who ruled for the next six centuries. A local military caste, the Mamluks took control about 1250 and continued to govern after the conquest of Egypt by the Ottoman Turks in 1517. Following the completion of the Suez Canal in 1869, Egypt became an important world transportation hub, but also fell heavily into debt. Ostensibly to protect its investments, Britain seized control of Egypt's government in 1882, but nominal allegiance to the Ottoman Empire continued until 1914. Partially independent from the UK in 1922, Egypt acquired full sovereignty with the overthrow of the British-backed monarchy in 1952. The completion of the Aswan High Dam in 1971 and the resultant Lake Nasser have altered the time-honored place of the Nile River in the agriculture and ecology of Egypt. A rapidly growing population (the largest in the Arab world), limited arable land, and dependence on the Nile all continue to overtax resources and stress society. The government has struggled to meet the demands of Egypt's growing population through economic reform and massive investment in communications and physical infrastructure.</background>
	<geo>
		<note>controls Sinai Peninsula, only land bridge between Africa and remainder of Eastern Hemisphere; controls Suez Canal, a sea link between Indian Ocean and Mediterranean Sea; size, and juxtaposition to Israel, establish its major role in Middle Eastern geopolitics; dependence on upstream neighbors; dominance of Nile basin issues; prone to influxes of refugees from Sudan and the Palestinian territories</note>
		<location>
			<desc>Northern Africa, bordering the Mediterranean Sea, between Libya and the Gaza Strip, and the Red Sea north of Sudan, and includes the Asian Sinai Peninsula</desc>
			<coordinates>TO DO</coordinates>
		</location>
		<area>
			<total unit="sq km">1001</total>
			<land unit="sq km">995450</land>
			<water unit="sq km">6000</water>
			<comparison>slightly more than three times the size of New Mexico</comparison>
		</area>
		<boundaries>
			<borders unit=""></borders>
			<coastline unit="km">2450</coastline>
		</boundaries>
		<maritime-claims>
			<territorial unit="nm">12</territorial>
			<contiguous unit="nm">24</contiguous>
			<economic unit="nm">200</economic>
			<continental-shelf>200 m depth or to the depth of exploitation</continental-shelf>
		</maritime-claims>
		<climate>desert; hot, dry summers with moderate winters</climate>
		<terrain>vast desert plateau interrupted by Nile valley and delta</terrain>
		<elevation>
			<high>Mount Catherine 2,629 m</high>
			<low>Qattara Depression -133 m</low>
		</elevation>
		<resources>petroleum, natural gas, iron ore, phosphates, manganese, limestone, gypsum, talc, asbestos, lead, rare earth elements, zinc</resources>
		<land-use>
			<arable unit="%">2.92</arable>
			<crops unit="%">0.5</crops>
			<other unit="%">96.58</other>
		</land-use>
		<hazards>periodic droughts; frequent earthquakes; flash floods; landslides; hot, driving windstorm called khamsin occurs in spring; dust storms; sandstorms</hazards>
		<issues>agricultural land being lost to urbanization and windblown sands; increasing soil salination below Aswan High Dam; desertification; oil pollution threatening coral reefs, beaches, and marine habitats; other water pollution from agricultural pesticides, raw sewage, and industrial effluents; limited natural freshwater resources away from the Nile, which is the only perennial water source; rapid growth in population overstraining the Nile and natural resources</issues>
		<water>
			<irrigated-land unit="sq km">35300</irrigated-land>
			<renewable-water unit="cu km">86.8</renewable-water>
			<freshwater-withdrawal>
				<total unit="cu km/yr">68.3</total>
				<per-capita unit="cu m/yr">923</per-capita>
			</freshwater-withdrawal>
		</water>
		<!--
"geo": {

		"Natural hazards": "flooding is a threat in some areas of the country (e.g., parts of Jutland, along the southern coast of the island of Lolland) that are protected from the sea by a system of dikes",
		"Environment - current issues": "air pollution, principally from vehicle and power plant emissions; nitrogen and phosphorus pollution of the North Sea; drinking and surface water becoming polluted from animal wastes and pesticides",
		"Environment - international agreements": {
			"party to:": "Air Pollution, Air Pollution-Nitrogen Oxides, Air Pollution-Persistent Organic Pollutants, Air Pollution-Sulfur 85, Air Pollution-Sulfur 94, Air Pollution-Volatile Organic Compounds, Antarctic Treaty, Biodiversity, Climate Change, Climate Change-Kyoto Protocol, Desertification, Endangered Species, Environmental Modification, Hazardous Wastes, Law of the Sea, Marine Dumping, Marine Life Conservation, Ozone Layer Protection, Ship Pollution, Tropical Timber 83, Tropical Timber 94, Wetlands, Whaling",
			"signed, but not ratified:": "none of the selected agreements"
		},
		"Geography - note": "controls Danish Straits (Skagerrak and Kattegat) linking Baltic and North Seas; about one-quarter of the population lives in greater Copenhagen"

		-->
	</geo>
	<people>
		<population>
			<total>82079</total>
			<birth unit="births/1,000 population">24.63</birth>
			<death unit="deaths/1,000 population">4.82</birth>
			<migration unit=""></migration>
			<growth unit="%">1.96</growth>
		</population>
		<age-distribution unit="percent">
			<group min="0" max="14">32.7</group>
			<group min="15" max="64">62.8</group>
			<group min="65"></group>
		</age-distribution>
		<median-age unit="years">
			<total>24.3</total>
			<male>24</male>
			<female>24.6</female>
		</median-age>
		<urbanization>
			<urban unit="% of total population">43.4</urban>
			<rate unit="% annual rate of change">2.1</urban>
			<cities>CAIRO (capital) 10.902 million; Alexandria 4.387 million (2009)</cities>
		</urbanization>
		<sex unit="male(s)/female">
			<group name="at birth" max="0">1.05</group>
			<group name="0 to 14" min="0" max="14">1.05</group>
			<group name="15 to 64" min="15" max="64">1.03</group>
			<group name="65 and over" min="65" max="0">0.83</group>
			<group name="total" min="0">1.03</group>
		</sex>
		<infant-mortality>
			<total unit="deaths/1,000 live births">25.2</total>
			<male unit="deaths/1,000 live births">26.8</male>
			<female unit="deaths/1,000 live births">23.52</female>
		</infant-mortality>
		<life-expectancy-at-birth>
			<total unit="years">72.66</total>
			<male unit="years">70.07</male>
			<female unit="years">75.38</female>
		</life-expectancy-at-birth>
		<fertility-rate unit="2.97">children born/woman</fertility-rate>
		<hiv>
			<prevalence>less than 0.1% (2009 est.)</prevalence>
			<total>11000</total>
			<deaths>fewer than 500 (2009 est.)</deaths>
		</hiv>
		<infectious-disease risk="intermediate">
			<food-or-waterborne>bacterial diarrhea, hepatitis A, and typhoid fever</food-or-waterborne>
			<vectorborne></vectorborne>
			<water-contact></water-contact>
		</infectious-disease>
		<drinking-water-source>[object Object]</drinking-water-source>
		<sanitation-access>[object Object]</sanitation-access>
		<nationality>
			<noun>Egyptian(s)</noun>
			<adjective>Egyptian</adjective>
		</nationality>
		<ethnic-groups>Egyptian 99.6%, other 0.4% (2006 census)</ethnic-groups>
		<religions>Muslim (mostly Sunni) 90%, Coptic 9%, other Christian 1%</religions>
		<languages>Arabic (official), English and French widely understood by educated classes</languages>
		<literacy>
			<definition>age 15 and over can read and write</definition>
			<total unit="%">71.4</total>
			<male unit="%">83</male>
			<female unit="%">59.4</female>
		</literacy>
		<school-expectancy unit="years">11</school-expectancy>
		<education-expenditure unit="% of GDP">3.8</school-expectancy>
	</people>
	<government>
		<country-name>
			<long>Arab Republic of Egypt</long>
			<short>Egypt</short>
		</country-name>
		<dependency></dependency>
		<government-type>republic</government-type>
		<capital>
			<name>Cairo</name>
			<coordinates>30° 3' N, 31° 15' E</coordinates>
			<time-difference>UTC+2 (7 hours ahead of Washington, DC during Standard Time)</time-difference>
		</capital>
		<administrative-divisions>29 governorates (muhafazat, singular - muhafazat); Ad Daqahliyah, Al Bahr al Ahmar (Red Sea), Al Buhayrah (El Beheira), Al Fayyum (El Faiyum), Al Gharbiyah, Al Iskandariyah (Alexandria), Al Isma'iliyah (Ismailia), Al Jizah (Giza), Al Minufiyah (El Monofia), Al Minya, Al Qahirah (Cairo), Al Qalyubiyah, Al Uqsur (Luxor), Al Wadi al Jadid (New Valley), As Suways (Suez), Ash Sharqiyah, Aswan, Asyut, Bani Suwayf (Beni Suef), Bur Sa'id (Port Said), Dumyat (Damietta), Helwan, Janub Sina' (South Sinai), Kafr ash Shaykh, Matruh (Western Desert), Qina (Qena), Shamal Sina' (North Sinai), Sittah Uktubar, Suhaj (Sohag)</administrative-divisions>
		<independence>28 February 1922 (from UK protectorate status; the revolution that began on 23 July 1952 led to a republic being declared on 18 June 1953 and all British troops withdrawn on 18 June 1956); note - it was ca. 3200 B.C. that the Two Lands of Upper (southern) and Lower (northern) Egypt were first united politically</independence>
		<national-holiday>Revolution Day, 23 July (1952)</national-holiday>
		<legal-system>mixed legal system based on Napoleonic civil law and Islamic religious law; judicial review by Supreme Court and Council of State (oversees validity of administrative decisions)</legal-system>
		<suffrage>18 years of age; universal and compulsory</suffrage>
		<executive>
			<head-of-state>President (vacant); Vice President (vacant); note - following the resignation of President Mohamed Hosni MUBARAK in February 2011, the Supreme Council of the Armed Forces, headed by Defense Minister Muhammad Hussein TANTAWI, assumed control of the government</head-of-state>
			<head-of-government>Prime Minister Essam Abdel Aziz SHARAF (since 4 March 2011); Deputy Prime Minister Yehia El-GAMAL (since 24 February 2011)</head-of-government>
			<cabinet>a new cabinet was sworn in on 7 March 2011</cabinet>
			<elections>president elected by popular vote for a six-year term (no term limits)</elections>
			<election-results>Hosni MUBARAK reelected president; percent of vote - Hosni MUBARAK 88.6%, Ayman NOUR 7.6%, Noman GOMAA 2.9%</election-results>
		</executive>
		<legislative>
			<description>bicameral system consists of the Advisory Council or Majlis al-Shura (Shura Council) that traditionally functions mostly in a consultative role (264 seats; 176 members elected by popular vote, 88 appointed by the president; members serve six-year terms; mid-term elections for half of the elected members) and the People's Assembly or Majlis al-Sha'b (518 seats; 508 members elected by popular vote, 64 seats reserved for women, 10 appointed by the president; members serve five-year terms)</description>
			<elections>Advisory Council - last held in June 2010 (next to be held in 2013); People's Assembly - last held in November-December 2010 in one round of voting and one run-off election (next to be held in 2015); note - on 13 February 2011 the ruling military council dissolved the parliament</elections>
			<election-results>Advisory Council - percent of vote by party - NA; seats by party - NDP 80, Al-Geel 1, Nasserist 1, NWP 1, Tagammu 1, Tomorrow Party 1, independents 3; People's Assembly - percent of vote by party - NA; seats by party - NDP 419, NWP 6, Tagammu 5, Democratic Peace Party 1, Social Justice Party 1, Tomorrow Party 1, independents 71, seats undecided 4, seats appointed by president 10</election-results>
		</legislative>
		<judicial>Supreme Constitutional Court</judicial>
		<parties>[object Object]</parties>
		<pressure-groups>TO DO</pressure-groups>
		<membership>ABEDA, AfDB, AFESD, AMF, AU, BSEC (observer), CAEU, CICA, COMESA, D-8, EBRD, FAO, G-15, G-24, G-77, IAEA, IBRD, ICAO, ICC, ICRM, IDA, IDB, IFAD, IFC, IFRCS, IHO, ILO, IMF, IMO, IMSO, Interpol, IOC, IOM, IPU, ISO, ITSO, ITU, LAS, MIGA, MINURSO, MONUSCO, NAM, OAPEC, OAS (observer), OIC, OIF, OSCE (partner), PCA, UN, UNAMID, UNCTAD, UNESCO, UNHCR, UNIDO, UNMIL, UNMIS, UNOCI, UNRWA, UNWTO, UPU, WCO, WFTU, WHO, WIPO, WMO, WTO</membership>
		<representation-in-usa>
			<chief>Ambassador Sameh Hassan SHOUKRY</chief>
			<chancery>3521 International Court NW, Washington, DC 20008</chancery>
			<telephone>[1] (202) 895-5400</telephone>
			<FAX>[1] (202) 244-4319</FAX>
			<consulates>Chicago, Houston, New York, San Francisco</consulates>
		</representation-in-usa>
		<representation-from-usa>
			<chief>Ambassador Margaret SCOBEY</chief>
			<embassy>8 Kamal El Din Salah St., Garden City, Cairo</embassy>
			<mailing-address>Unit 64900, Box 15, APO AE 09839-4900; 5 Tawfik Diab Street, Garden City, Cairo</mailing-address>
			<telephone>[20] (2) 2797-3300</telephone>
			<FAX>[20] (2) 2797-3200</FAX>
		</representation-from-usa>
		<flag>[object Object]</flag>
		<anthem>
			<name>&quot;Bilady, Bilady, Bilady&quot; (My Homeland, My Homeland, My Homeland)</name>
			<by>Younis-al QADI/Sayed DARWISH</by>
		</anthem>
	</government>
	<economy>
		<overview>Occupying the northeast corner of the African continent, Egypt is bisected by the highly fertile Nile valley, where most economic activity takes place. Egypt's economy was highly centralized during the rule of former President Gamal Abdel NASSER but opened up considerably under former Presidents Anwar EL-SADAT and Mohamed Hosni MUBARAK. Cairo from 2004 to 2008 aggressively pursued economic reforms to attract foreign investment and facilitate GDP growth. The global financial crisis slowed the reform efforts. The budget deficit climbed to over 8% of GDP and Egypt's GDP growth slowed to 4.6% in 2009, predominately due to reduced growth in export-oriented sectors, including manufacturing and tourism, and Suez Canal revenues. In 2010, the government spent more on infrastructure and public projects, and exports drove GDP growth to more than 5%, but GDP growth in 2011 is unlikely to bounce back to pre-global financial recession levels, when it stood at 7%. Despite the relatively high levels of economic growth over the past few years, living conditions for the average Egyptian remain poor.</overview>
		<gdp>
			<purchasing-power-parity></purchasing-power-parity>
			<official-exchange-rate>218500000000</official-exchange-rate>
			<real-growth-rate unit="%">5.1</real-growth-rate>
			<per-capita></per-capita>
			<sector unit="%">
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
		</gdp>
		<labour>
			<force>26100000</force>
			<sector>
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
			<unemployment unit="%">9.7</unemployment>
		</labour>
		<poverty>[object Object]</poverty>
		<household-income>TO DO</household-income>
		<budget>
			<revenue unit="USD"></revenue>
			<expenditure unit="USD"></expenditure>
		</budget>
		<public-debt unit="% of GDP">80.5</public-debt>
		<consumer-inflation unit="%">12.8</consumer-inflation>
		<central-bank-discount-rate unit="%">8.5</central-bank-discount-rate>
		<commercial-prime-lending-rate unit="%">11.98</commercial-prime-lending-rate>
		<narrow-money-stock unit="USD">37800000000</narrow-money-stock>
		<broad-money-stock unit="USD">166200000000</broad-money-stock>
		<domestic-credit-stock unit="USD">145600000000</domestic-credit-stock>
		<agriculture-products>cotton, rice, corn, wheat, beans, fruits, vegetables; cattle, water buffalo, sheep, goats</agriculture-products>
		<industries>textiles, food processing, tourism, chemicals, pharmaceuticals, hydrocarbons, construction, cement, metals, light manufactures</industries>
		<industrial-production-growth>[object Object]</industrial-production-growth>
		<electricity unit="kWh">
			<production>118400000000</production>
			<consumption>104100000000</consumption>
			<exports>814000000</exports>
			<imports>251000000</imports>
		</electricity>
		<oil>
			<production unit="bbl/day">680500</production>
			<consumption unit="bbl/day">683000</consumption>
			<exports unit="bbl/day">89300</exports>
			<imports unit="bbl/day">48450</imports>
			<reserves unit="bbl">4300000000</reserves>
		</oil>
		<natural-gas>
			<production unit="cu m">62700000000</production>
			<consumption unit="cu m">42500000000</consumption>
			<exports unit="cu m">8550000000.000001</exports>
			<imports unit="cu m">0</imports>
			<reserves unit="cu m">1656000000000</reserves>
		</natural-gas>
		<exports>
			<total unit="USD"></total>
			<commodities>crude oil and petroleum products, cotton, textiles, metal products, chemicals, processed food</commodities>
			<partners>US 7.95%, Italy 7.26%, Spain 6.78%, India 6.69%, Saudi Arabia 5.53%, Syria 5.3%, France 4.39%, South Korea 4.27% (2009)</partners>
		</exports>
		<imports>
			<total unit="USD">46520000000</total>
			<commodities>machinery and equipment, foodstuffs, chemicals, wood products, fuels</commodities>
			<partners>US 9.92%, China 9.63%, Germany 6.98%, Italy 6.88%, Turkey 4.94% (2009)</partners>
		</imports>
		<external-debt unit="USD">30610000000</external-debt>
		<exchange-rates>Egyptian pounds (EGP) per US dollar -</exchange-rates>
	</economy>
	<communications>
		<telephones>
			<assessment>underwent extensive upgrading during 1990s; principal centers at Alexandria, Cairo, Al Mansurah, Ismailia, Suez, and Tanta are connected by coaxial cable and microwave radio relay</assessment>
			<domestic>largest fixed-line system in the region; as of 2010 there were three mobile-cellular networks with a total of more than 55 million subscribers</domestic>
			<international>country code - 20; landing point for Aletar, the SEA-ME-WE-3 and SEA-ME-WE-4 submarine cable networks, Link Around the Globe (FLAG) Falcon and FLAG FEA; satellite earth stations - 4 (2 Intelsat - Atlantic Ocean and Indian Ocean, 1 Arabsat, and 1 Inmarsat); tropospheric scatter to Sudan; microwave radio relay to Israel; a participant in Medarabtel (2009)</international>
			<land-lines>10313000</land-lines>
			<mobile>55352000</mobile>
		</telephones>
		<broadcast>mix of state-run and private broadcast media; state-run TV operates 2 national and 6 regional terrestrial networks as well as a few satellite channels; about 20 private satellite channels and a large number of Arabic satellite channels are available via subscription; state-run radio operates about 70 stations belonging to 8 networks; 2 privately-owned radio stations operational (2008)</broadcast>
		<internet>
			<tld>.eg</tld>
			<hosts>187197</hosts>
			<users>20136000</users>
		</internet>
	</communications>
	<transport>
		<airports>
			<total>86</total>
			<paved>
				<altitude min="*" max="*"></altitude>
				<altitude min="3047m" max="*">15</altitude>
				<altitude min="2438m" max="3047m">36</altitude>
				<altitude min="1524m" max="2437m">15</altitude>
				<altitude min="914m" max="1524m">2</altitude>
				<altitude min="*" max="914m"></altitude>
			</paved>
		</airports>
		<ports-and-terminals>Ayn Sukhnah, Alexandria, Damietta, El Dekheila, Port Said, Sidi Kurayr, Suez</ports-and-terminals>
	</transport>
	<military>
		<branches>Army, Navy, Air Force, Air Defense Command</branches>
		<manpower>
			<population-available>
				<male>21012</male>
				<female>20145</female>
			</population-available>
			<fit-for-service>
				<male>18060</male>
				<female>17244</female>
			</fit-for-service>
			<reaching-maturity>
				<male>783405</male>
				<female>748647</female>
			</reaching-maturity>
			<notes></notes>
		</manpower>
	</military>
	<issues>
		<disputes>Sudan claims but Egypt de facto administers security and economic development of Halaib region north of the 22nd parallel boundary; Egypt no longer shows its administration of the Bir Tawil trapezoid in Sudan on its maps; Gazan breaches in the security wall with Egypt in January 2008 highlight difficulties in monitoring the Sinai border; Saudi Arabia claims Egyptian-administered islands of Tiran and Sanafir</disputes>
		<drugs>transit point for cannabis, heroin, and opium moving to Europe, Israel, and North Africa; transit stop for Nigerian drug couriers; concern as money laundering site due to lax enforcement of financial regulations</drugs>
	</issues>
</country>