<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<country>
	<code>ez</code>
	<name>Czech Republic</name>
	<region>Europe</region>
	<background>At the close of World War I, the Czechs and Slovaks of the former Austro-Hungarian Empire merged to form Czechoslovakia. During the interwar years, having rejected a federal system, the new country's leaders were frequently preoccupied with meeting the demands of other ethnic minorities within the republic, most notably the Sudeten Germans and the Ruthenians (Ukrainians). On the eve of World War II, the Czech part of the country was forcibly annexed to the Third Reich, and the Slovaks declared independence as a fascist ally of Nazi Germany. After the war, a reunited but truncated Czechoslovakia (less Ruthenia) fell within the Soviet sphere of influence. In 1968, an invasion by Warsaw Pact troops ended the efforts of the country's leaders to liberalize Communist Party rule and create &quot;socialism with a human face.&quot; Anti-Soviet demonstrations the following year ushered in a period of harsh repression known as &quot;normalization.&quot; With the collapse of Soviet-backed authority in 1989, Czechoslovakia regained its freedom through a peaceful &quot;Velvet Revolution.&quot; On 1 January 1993, the country underwent a &quot;velvet divorce&quot; into its two national components, the Czech Republic and Slovakia. The Czech Republic joined NATO in 1999 and the European Union in 2004.</background>
	<geo>
		<note>landlocked; strategically located astride some of oldest and most significant land routes in Europe; Moravian Gate is a traditional military corridor between the North European Plain and the Danube in central Europe</note>
		<location>
			<desc>Central Europe, between Germany, Poland, Slovakia, and Austria</desc>
			<coordinates>TO DO</coordinates>
		</location>
		<area>
			<total unit="sq km">78867</total>
			<land unit="sq km">77247</land>
			<water unit="sq km">1620</water>
			<comparison>slightly smaller than South Carolina</comparison>
		</area>
		<boundaries>
			<borders unit=""></borders>
			<coastline unit="km">0</coastline>
		</boundaries>
		<maritime-claims>
			<territorial unit=""></territorial>
			<contiguous unit=""></contiguous>
			<economic unit=""></economic>
			<continental-shelf></continental-shelf>
		</maritime-claims>
		<climate>temperate; cool summers; cold, cloudy, humid winters</climate>
		<terrain>Bohemia in the west consists of rolling plains, hills, and plateaus surrounded by low mountains; Moravia in the east consists of very hilly country</terrain>
		<elevation>
			<high>Snezka 1,602 m</high>
			<low>Elbe River 115 m</low>
		</elevation>
		<resources>hard coal, soft coal, kaolin, clay, graphite, timber</resources>
		<land-use>
			<arable unit="%">38.82</arable>
			<crops unit="%">3</crops>
			<other unit="%">58.18</other>
		</land-use>
		<hazards>flooding</hazards>
		<issues>air and water pollution in areas of northwest Bohemia and in northern Moravia around Ostrava present health risks; acid rain damaging forests; efforts to bring industry up to EU code should improve domestic pollution</issues>
		<water>
			<irrigated-land unit="sq km">390</irrigated-land>
			<renewable-water unit="cu km">16</renewable-water>
			<freshwater-withdrawal>
				<total unit="cu km/yr">1.91</total>
				<per-capita unit="cu m/yr">187</per-capita>
			</freshwater-withdrawal>
		</water>
		<!--
"geo": {

		"Natural hazards": "flooding is a threat in some areas of the country (e.g., parts of Jutland, along the southern coast of the island of Lolland) that are protected from the sea by a system of dikes",
		"Environment - current issues": "air pollution, principally from vehicle and power plant emissions; nitrogen and phosphorus pollution of the North Sea; drinking and surface water becoming polluted from animal wastes and pesticides",
		"Environment - international agreements": {
			"party to:": "Air Pollution, Air Pollution-Nitrogen Oxides, Air Pollution-Persistent Organic Pollutants, Air Pollution-Sulfur 85, Air Pollution-Sulfur 94, Air Pollution-Volatile Organic Compounds, Antarctic Treaty, Biodiversity, Climate Change, Climate Change-Kyoto Protocol, Desertification, Endangered Species, Environmental Modification, Hazardous Wastes, Law of the Sea, Marine Dumping, Marine Life Conservation, Ozone Layer Protection, Ship Pollution, Tropical Timber 83, Tropical Timber 94, Wetlands, Whaling",
			"signed, but not ratified:": "none of the selected agreements"
		},
		"Geography - note": "controls Danish Straits (Skagerrak and Kattegat) linking Baltic and North Seas; about one-quarter of the population lives in greater Copenhagen"

		-->
	</geo>
	<people>
		<population>
			<total>10190</total>
			<birth unit="births/1,000 population">8.7</birth>
			<death unit="deaths/1,000 population">10.86</birth>
			<migration unit="migrant(s)/1,000 population">0.97</migration>
			<growth unit=""></growth>
		</population>
		<age-distribution unit="percent">
			<group min="0" max="14">13.5</group>
			<group min="15" max="64">70.2</group>
			<group min="65"></group>
		</age-distribution>
		<median-age unit="years">
			<total>40.8</total>
			<male>39.2</male>
			<female>42.5</female>
		</median-age>
		<urbanization>
			<urban unit="% of total population">74</urban>
			<rate unit="% annual rate of change">0.3</urban>
			<cities>PRAGUE (capital) 1.162 million (2009)</cities>
		</urbanization>
		<sex unit="male(s)/female">
			<group name="at birth" max="0">1.059</group>
			<group name="0 to 14" min="0" max="14">1.06</group>
			<group name="15 to 64" min="15" max="64">1.01</group>
			<group name="65 and over" min="65" max="0">0.66</group>
			<group name="total" min="0">0.95</group>
		</sex>
		<infant-mortality>
			<total unit="deaths/1,000 live births">3.73</total>
			<male unit="deaths/1,000 live births">4.06</male>
			<female unit="deaths/1,000 live births">3.38</female>
		</infant-mortality>
		<life-expectancy-at-birth>
			<total unit="years">77.19</total>
			<male unit="years">73.93</male>
			<female unit="years">80.66</female>
		</life-expectancy-at-birth>
		<fertility-rate unit="1.26">children born/woman</fertility-rate>
		<hiv>
			<prevalence>less than 0.1% (2009 est.)</prevalence>
			<total>2000</total>
			<deaths>fewer than 100 (2009 est.)</deaths>
		</hiv>
		<infectious-disease risk="">
			<food-or-waterborne></food-or-waterborne>
			<vectorborne></vectorborne>
			<water-contact></water-contact>
		</infectious-disease>
		<drinking-water-source>[object Object]</drinking-water-source>
		<sanitation-access>[object Object]</sanitation-access>
		<nationality>
			<noun>Czech(s)</noun>
			<adjective>Czech</adjective>
		</nationality>
		<ethnic-groups>Czech 90.4%, Moravian 3.7%, Slovak 1.9%, other 4% (2001 census)</ethnic-groups>
		<religions>Roman Catholic 26.8%, Protestant 2.1%, other 3.3%, unspecified 8.8%, unaffiliated 59% (2001 census)</religions>
		<languages>Czech 94.9%, Slovak 2%, other 2.3%, unidentified 0.8% (2001 census)</languages>
		<literacy>
			<definition>NA</definition>
			<total unit="%">99</total>
			<male unit="%">99</male>
			<female unit="%">99</female>
		</literacy>
		<school-expectancy unit="years">15</school-expectancy>
		<education-expenditure unit="% of GDP">4.2</school-expectancy>
	</people>
	<government>
		<country-name>
			<long>Czech Republic</long>
			<short>Czech Republic</short>
		</country-name>
		<dependency></dependency>
		<government-type>parliamentary democracy</government-type>
		<capital>
			<name>Prague</name>
			<coordinates>50° 5' N, 14° 28' E</coordinates>
			<time-difference>UTC+1 (6 hours ahead of Washington, DC during Standard Time)</time-difference>
		</capital>
		<administrative-divisions>13 regions (kraje, singular - kraj) and 1 capital city* (hlavni mesto); Jihocesky (South Bohemia), Jihomoravsky (South Moravia), Karlovarsky, Kralovehradecky, Liberecky, Moravskoslezsky (Moravia-Silesia), Olomoucky, Pardubicky, Plzensky (Pilsen), Praha (Prague)*, Stredocesky (Central Bohemia), Ustecky, Vysocina, Zlinsky</administrative-divisions>
		<independence>1 January 1993 (Czechoslovakia split into the Czech Republic and Slovakia); note - although 1 January is the day the Czech Republic came into being, the Czechs generally consider 28 October 1918, the day the former Czechoslovakia declared its independence from the Austro-Hungarian Empire, as their independence day</independence>
		<national-holiday>Czechoslovak Founding Day, 28 October (1918)</national-holiday>
		<legal-system>civil law system based on former Austro-Hungarian civil codes and socialist theory; note - legislation is actively modernizing the legal system</legal-system>
		<suffrage>18 years of age; universal</suffrage>
		<executive>
			<head-of-state>President Vaclav KLAUS (since 7 March 2003)</head-of-state>
			<head-of-government>Prime Minister Petr NECAS (since 28 June 2010); First Deputy Prime Minister Karel SCHWARZENBERG (since 13 July 2010), Deputy Prime Minister Radek JOHN (since 13 July 2010)</head-of-government>
			<cabinet>Cabinet appointed by the president on the recommendation of the prime minister</cabinet>
			<elections>president elected by Parliament for a five-year term (eligible for a second term); last successful election held on 15 February 2008 (after earlier elections held 8 and 9 February 2008 were inconclusive; next election to be held in 2013); prime minister appointed by the president</elections>
			<election-results>Vaclav KLAUS reelected president on 15 February 2008; Vaclav KLAUS 141 votes, Jan SVEJNAR 111 votes (third round; combined votes of both chambers of parliament)</election-results>
		</executive>
		<legislative>
			<description>bicameral Parliament or Parlament consists of the Senate or Senat (81 seats; members elected by popular vote to serve six-year terms; one-third elected every two years) and the Chamber of Deputies or Poslanecka Snemovna (200 seats; members are elected by popular vote to serve four-year terms)</description>
			<elections>Senate - last held in two rounds on 15-16 and 22-23 October 2010 (next to be held by October 2012); Chamber of Deputies - last held on 28-29 May 2010 (next to be held by 2014)</elections>
			<election-results>Senate - percent of vote by party - NA; seats by party - CSSD 41, ODS 25, KDU-CSL 6, TOP 09 5, others 4; Chamber of Deputies - percent of vote by party - CSSD 22.1%, ODS 20.2%, TOP 09 16.7%, KSCM 11.3%, VV 10.9%; seats by party - CSSD 56, ODS 53, TOP 09 41, KSCM 26, VV 24</election-results>
		</legislative>
		<judicial>Supreme Court; judges are appointed by the president for an unlimited term; Constitutional Court; 15 judges are appointed by the president and confirmed by the Senate for a ten-year term; Supreme Administrative Court; chairman and deputy chairmen are appointed by the president for a 10-year term; judges are appointed by the president for an unlimited term</judicial>
		<parties>Association of Independent Candidates-European Democrats or SNK-ED [Zdenka MARKOVA]; Christian Democratic Union-Czechoslovak People's Party or KDU-CSL [Pavel BELOBRADEK]; Civic Democratic Party or ODS [Petr NECAS]; Communist Party of Bohemia and Moravia or KSCM [Vojtech FILIP]; Czech Social Democratic Party or CSSD [Bohuslav SOBOTKA (acting)]; Green Party [Ondrej LISKA]; Public Affairs or VV [Radek JOHN]; Tradice Odpovednost Prosperita 09 or TOP 09 [Karel SCHWARZENBERG]; Union of Freedom-Democratic Union or US-DEU [Jan CERNY]</parties>
		<pressure-groups>TO DO</pressure-groups>
		<membership>Australia Group, BIS, BSEC (observer), CD, CE, CEI, CERN, EAPC, EBRD, EIB, ESA, EU, FAO, IAEA, IBRD, ICAO, ICC, ICRM, IDA, IEA, IFC, IFRCS, ILO, IMF, IMO, IMSO, Interpol, IOC, IOM, IPU, ISO, ITSO, ITU, ITUC, MIGA, MONUSCO, NATO, NEA, NSG, OAS (observer), OECD, OIF (observer), OPCW, OSCE, PCA, Schengen Convention, SECI (observer), UN, UNCTAD, UNESCO, UNIDO, UNWTO, UPU, WCO, WFTU, WHO, WIPO, WMO, WTO, ZC</membership>
		<representation-in-usa>
			<chief>Ambassador Norman EISEN</chief>
			<chancery>3900 Spring of Freedom Street NW, Washington, DC 20008</chancery>
			<telephone>[1] (202) 274-9100</telephone>
			<FAX>[1] (202) 966-8540</FAX>
			<consulates>Chicago, Los Angeles, New York</consulates>
		</representation-in-usa>
		<representation-from-usa>
			<chief>Ambassador Norman EISEN</chief>
			<embassy>Trziste 15, 118 01 Prague 1</embassy>
			<mailing-address>use embassy street address</mailing-address>
			<telephone>[420] 257 022 000</telephone>
			<FAX>[420] 257 022 809</FAX>
		</representation-from-usa>
		<flag>[object Object]</flag>
		<anthem>
			<name>&quot;Kde domov muj?&quot; (Where is My Home?)</name>
			<by>Josef Kajetan TYL/Frantisek Jan SKROUP</by>
		</anthem>
	</government>
	<economy>
		<overview>The Czech Republic is a stable and prosperous market economy, which harmonized its laws and regulations with those of the EU prior to its EU accession in 2004. While the conservative, inward looking Czech financial system has remained relative healthy, the small, open, export-driven Czech economy remains very sensitive to changes in the economic performance of its main export markets, especially Germany. When Western Europe and Germany fell into recession in late 2008, demand for Czech goods plunged, leading to double digit drops in industrial production and exports. As a result, real GDP fell 4.1% in 2009, with most of the decline occurring during the first quarter. Real GDP, however, has slowly recovered with positive quarter-on-quarter growth starting in the second half of 2009 and continuing throughout 2010. The auto industry remains the largest single industry and, together with its suppliers, accounts for as much as 20% of Czech manufacturing. The Czech Republic produced more than a million cars for the first time in 2010, over 80% of which were exported. Foreign and domestic businesses alike voice concerns about corruption, especially in public procurement. Other long term challenges include dealing with a rapidly aging population, funding an unsustainable pension and health care system, and diversifying away from manufacturing and toward a more high-tech, services-based, knowledge economy.</overview>
		<gdp>
			<purchasing-power-parity></purchasing-power-parity>
			<official-exchange-rate>192200000000</official-exchange-rate>
			<real-growth-rate unit="%">2.3</real-growth-rate>
			<per-capita></per-capita>
			<sector unit="%">
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
		</gdp>
		<labour>
			<force>5370000</force>
			<sector>
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
			<unemployment unit="%">7.1</unemployment>
		</labour>
		<poverty>NA%</poverty>
		<household-income>TO DO</household-income>
		<budget>
			<revenue unit="USD"></revenue>
			<expenditure unit="USD"></expenditure>
		</budget>
		<public-debt unit="% of GDP">40</public-debt>
		<consumer-inflation unit="%">1.5</consumer-inflation>
		<central-bank-discount-rate unit="%"></central-bank-discount-rate>
		<commercial-prime-lending-rate unit="%">3.9</commercial-prime-lending-rate>
		<narrow-money-stock unit="USD">96820000000</narrow-money-stock>
		<broad-money-stock unit="USD">138600000000</broad-money-stock>
		<domestic-credit-stock unit="USD">119500000000</domestic-credit-stock>
		<agriculture-products>wheat, potatoes, sugar beets, hops, fruit; pigs, poultry</agriculture-products>
		<industries>motor vehicles, metallurgy, machinery and equipment, glass, armaments</industries>
		<industrial-production-growth>[object Object]</industrial-production-growth>
		<electricity unit="kWh">
			<production>82250000000</production>
			<consumption>53420000000</consumption>
			<exports>22230000000</exports>
			<imports>8580000000</imports>
		</electricity>
		<oil>
			<production unit="bbl/day">10970</production>
			<consumption unit="bbl/day">207600</consumption>
			<exports unit="bbl/day">29670</exports>
			<imports unit="bbl/day">219900</imports>
			<reserves unit="bbl">15000000</reserves>
		</oil>
		<natural-gas>
			<production unit="cu m">178000000</production>
			<consumption unit="cu m">8164000000</consumption>
			<exports unit="cu m">1111000000</exports>
			<imports unit="cu m">9683000000</imports>
			<reserves unit="cu m">3072000000</reserves>
		</natural-gas>
		<exports>
			<total unit="USD"></total>
			<commodities>machinery and transport equipment, raw materials and fuel, chemicals</commodities>
			<partners>Germany 31.7%, Slovakia 8.7%, Poland 6.2%, France 5.5%, UK 4.9%, Austria 4.7%, Italy 4.5% (2010 est.)</partners>
		</exports>
		<imports>
			<total unit="USD">109200000000</total>
			<commodities>machinery and transport equipment, raw materials and fuels, chemicals</commodities>
			<partners>Germany 25.6%, China 11.9%, Poland 6.5%, Russia 5.4%, Slovakia 5.2% (2010 est.)</partners>
		</imports>
		<external-debt unit="USD">86790000000</external-debt>
		<exchange-rates>koruny (CZK) per US dollar -</exchange-rates>
	</economy>
	<communications>
		<telephones>
			<assessment>privatization and modernization of the Czech telecommunication system got a late start but is advancing steadily; virtually all exchanges now digital; existing copper subscriber systems enhanced with Asymmetric Digital Subscriber Line (ADSL) equipment to accommodate Internet and other digital signals; trunk systems include fiber-optic cable and microwave radio relay</assessment>
			<domestic>access to the fixed-line telephone network expanded throughout the 1990s but the number of fixed line connections has been dropping since then; mobile telephone usage increased sharply beginning in the mid-1990s and the number of cellular telephone subscriptions now greatly exceeds the population</domestic>
			<international>country code - 420; satellite earth stations - 6 (2 Intersputnik - Atlantic and Indian Ocean regions, 1 Intelsat, 1 Eutelsat, 1 Inmarsat, 1 Globalstar) (2009)</international>
			<land-lines>2092000</land-lines>
			<mobile>14258000</mobile>
		</telephones>
		<broadcast>roughly 130 television broadcasters operating some 350 television channels with 4 publicly operated and the remainder in private hands; 13 television stations have national coverage with 4 being publicly operated; cable and satellite TV subscription services are available; about 70 radio broadcasters are registered operating roughly 85 radio stations with 15 stations publicly operated; 16 radio stations provide national coverage with the remainder local or regional (2008)</broadcast>
		<internet>
			<tld>.cz</tld>
			<hosts>3494000</hosts>
			<users>6681000</users>
		</internet>
	</communications>
	<transport>
		<airports>
			<total>122</total>
			<paved>
				<altitude min="*" max="*"></altitude>
				<altitude min="3047m" max="*">2</altitude>
				<altitude min="2438m" max="3047m">9</altitude>
				<altitude min="1524m" max="2437m">12</altitude>
				<altitude min="914m" max="1524m">3</altitude>
				<altitude min="*" max="914m"></altitude>
			</paved>
		</airports>
		<ports-and-terminals>Decin, Prague, Usti nad Labem</ports-and-terminals>
	</transport>
	<military>
		<branches>Army of the Czech Republic (ACR): Joint Forces Command (includes Land Forces and Air Forces), Support and Training Forces Command (2011)</branches>
		<manpower>
			<population-available>
				<male>2506</male>
				<female>2407</female>
			</population-available>
			<fit-for-service>
				<male>2072</male>
				<female>1988</female>
			</fit-for-service>
			<reaching-maturity>
				<male>49999</male>
				<female>47501</female>
			</reaching-maturity>
			<notes></notes>
		</manpower>
	</military>
	<issues>
		<disputes>while threats of international legal action never materialized in 2007, 915,220 Austrians, with the support of the popular Freedom Party, signed a petition in January 2008, demanding that Austria block the Czech Republic's accession to the EU unless Prague closes its controversial Soviet-style nuclear plant in Temelin, bordering Austria</disputes>
		<drugs>transshipment point for Southwest Asian heroin and minor transit point for Latin American cocaine to Western Europe; producer of synthetic drugs for local and regional markets; susceptible to money laundering related to drug trafficking, organized crime; significant consumer of ecstasy (2008)</drugs>
	</issues>
</country>