<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<country>
	<code>gv</code>
	<name>Guinea</name>
	<region>Africa</region>
	<background>Guinea has had a history of authoritarian rule since gaining its independence from France in 1958. Lansana CONTE came to power in 1984 when the military seized the government after the death of the first president, Sekou TOURE. Guinea did not hold democratic elections until 1993 when Gen. CONTE (head of the military government) was elected president of the civilian government. He was reelected in 1998 and again in 2003, though all the polls were marred by irregularities. History repeated itself in December 2008 when following President CONTE's death, Capt. Moussa Dadis CAMARA led a military coup, seizing power and suspending the constitution. His unwillingness to yield to domestic and international pressure to step down led to heightened political tensions that culminated in September 2009 when presidential guards opened fire on an opposition rally killing more than 150 people, and in early December 2009 when CAMARA was wounded in an assassination attempt and evacuated to Morocco and subsequently to Burkina Faso. A transitional government led by General Sekouba KONATE held democratic elections in 2010 and Alpha CONDE was elected president in the country's first free and fair elections since independence.

</background>
	<geo>
		<note>the Niger and its important tributary the Milo have their sources in the Guinean highlands</note>
		<location>
			<desc>Western Africa, bordering the North Atlantic Ocean, between Guinea-Bissau and Sierra Leone</desc>
			<coordinates>TO DO</coordinates>
		</location>
		<area>
			<total unit="sq km">245857</total>
			<land unit="sq km">245717</land>
			<water unit="sq km">140</water>
			<comparison>slightly smaller than Oregon</comparison>
		</area>
		<boundaries>
			<borders unit=""></borders>
			<coastline unit="km">320</coastline>
		</boundaries>
		<maritime-claims>
			<territorial unit="nm">12</territorial>
			<contiguous unit=""></contiguous>
			<economic unit="nm">200</economic>
			<continental-shelf></continental-shelf>
		</maritime-claims>
		<climate>generally hot and humid; monsoonal-type rainy season (June to November) with southwesterly winds; dry season (December to May) with northeasterly harmattan winds</climate>
		<terrain>generally flat coastal plain, hilly to mountainous interior</terrain>
		<elevation>
			<high>Mont Nimba 1,752 m</high>
			<low>Atlantic Ocean 0 m</low>
		</elevation>
		<resources>bauxite, iron ore, diamonds, gold, uranium, hydropower, fish, salt</resources>
		<land-use>
			<arable unit="%">4.47</arable>
			<crops unit="%">2.64</crops>
			<other unit="%">92.89</other>
		</land-use>
		<hazards>hot, dry, dusty harmattan haze may reduce visibility during dry season</hazards>
		<issues>deforestation; inadequate supplies of potable water; desertification; soil contamination and erosion; overfishing, overpopulation in forest region; poor mining practices have led to environmental damage</issues>
		<water>
			<irrigated-land unit="sq km">950</irrigated-land>
			<renewable-water unit="cu km">226</renewable-water>
			<freshwater-withdrawal>
				<total unit="cu km/yr">1.51</total>
				<per-capita unit="cu m/yr">161</per-capita>
			</freshwater-withdrawal>
		</water>
		<!--
"geo": {

		"Natural hazards": "flooding is a threat in some areas of the country (e.g., parts of Jutland, along the southern coast of the island of Lolland) that are protected from the sea by a system of dikes",
		"Environment - current issues": "air pollution, principally from vehicle and power plant emissions; nitrogen and phosphorus pollution of the North Sea; drinking and surface water becoming polluted from animal wastes and pesticides",
		"Environment - international agreements": {
			"party to:": "Air Pollution, Air Pollution-Nitrogen Oxides, Air Pollution-Persistent Organic Pollutants, Air Pollution-Sulfur 85, Air Pollution-Sulfur 94, Air Pollution-Volatile Organic Compounds, Antarctic Treaty, Biodiversity, Climate Change, Climate Change-Kyoto Protocol, Desertification, Endangered Species, Environmental Modification, Hazardous Wastes, Law of the Sea, Marine Dumping, Marine Life Conservation, Ozone Layer Protection, Ship Pollution, Tropical Timber 83, Tropical Timber 94, Wetlands, Whaling",
			"signed, but not ratified:": "none of the selected agreements"
		},
		"Geography - note": "controls Danish Straits (Skagerrak and Kattegat) linking Baltic and North Seas; about one-quarter of the population lives in greater Copenhagen"

		-->
	</geo>
	<people>
		<population>
			<total>10601</total>
			<birth unit="births/1,000 population">36.9</birth>
			<death unit="deaths/1,000 population">10.45</birth>
			<migration unit="migrant(s)/1,000 population">0</migration>
			<growth unit="%">2.645</growth>
		</population>
		<age-distribution unit="percent">
			<group min="0" max="14">42.5</group>
			<group min="15" max="64">54</group>
			<group min="65"></group>
		</age-distribution>
		<median-age unit="years">
			<total>18.6</total>
			<male>18.3</male>
			<female>18.8</female>
		</median-age>
		<urbanization>
			<urban unit="% of total population">35</urban>
			<rate unit="% annual rate of change">4.3</urban>
			<cities>CONAKRY (capital) 1.597 million (2009)</cities>
		</urbanization>
		<sex unit="male(s)/female">
			<group name="at birth" max="0">1.03</group>
			<group name="0 to 14" min="0" max="14">1.02</group>
			<group name="15 to 64" min="15" max="64">1</group>
			<group name="65 and over" min="65" max="0">0.78</group>
			<group name="total" min="0">1</group>
		</sex>
		<infant-mortality>
			<total unit="deaths/1,000 live births">61.03</total>
			<male unit="deaths/1,000 live births">64.29</male>
			<female unit="deaths/1,000 live births">57.68</female>
		</infant-mortality>
		<life-expectancy-at-birth>
			<total unit="years">58.11</total>
			<male unit="years">56.63</male>
			<female unit="years">59.64</female>
		</life-expectancy-at-birth>
		<fertility-rate unit="5.1">children born/woman</fertility-rate>
		<hiv>
			<prevalence>[object Object]</prevalence>
			<total>79000</total>
			<deaths>4700</deaths>
		</hiv>
		<infectious-disease risk="very high">
			<food-or-waterborne>bacterial and protozoal diarrhea, hepatitis A, and typhoid fever</food-or-waterborne>
			<vectorborne>malaria and yellow fever</vectorborne>
			<water-contact></water-contact>
		</infectious-disease>
		<drinking-water-source>[object Object]</drinking-water-source>
		<sanitation-access>[object Object]</sanitation-access>
		<nationality>
			<noun>Guinean(s)</noun>
			<adjective>Guinean</adjective>
		</nationality>
		<ethnic-groups>Peuhl 40%, Malinke 30%, Soussou 20%, smaller ethnic groups 10%</ethnic-groups>
		<religions>Muslim 85%, Christian 8%, indigenous beliefs 7%</religions>
		<languages>[object Object]</languages>
		<literacy>
			<definition>age 15 and over can read and write</definition>
			<total unit="%">29.5</total>
			<male unit="%">42.6</male>
			<female unit="%">18.1</female>
		</literacy>
		<school-expectancy unit="years">9</school-expectancy>
		<education-expenditure unit="% of GDP">2.4</school-expectancy>
	</people>
	<government>
		<country-name>
			<long>Republic of Guinea</long>
			<short>Guinea</short>
		</country-name>
		<dependency></dependency>
		<government-type>republic</government-type>
		<capital>
			<name>Conakry</name>
			<coordinates>9° 33' N, 13° 42' W</coordinates>
			<time-difference>UTC 0 (5 hours ahead of Washington, DC during Standard Time)</time-difference>
		</capital>
		<administrative-divisions>33 prefectures and 1 special zone (zone special)*; Beyla, Boffa, Boke, Conakry*, Coyah, Dabola, Dalaba, Dinguiraye, Dubreka, Faranah, Forecariah, Fria, Gaoual, Gueckedou, Kankan, Kerouane, Kindia, Kissidougou, Koubia, Koundara, Kouroussa, Labe, Lelouma, Lola, Macenta, Mali, Mamou, Mandiana, Nzerekore, Pita, Siguiri, Telimele, Tougue, Yomou</administrative-divisions>
		<independence>2 October 1958 (from France)</independence>
		<national-holiday>Independence Day, 2 October (1958)</national-holiday>
		<legal-system>civil law system based on the French  model</legal-system>
		<suffrage>18 years of age; universal</suffrage>
		<executive>
			<head-of-state>President Alpha CONDE (since 21 December 2010)</head-of-state>
			<head-of-government>Prime Minister Mohamed Said FOFANA (since 24 December 2010)</head-of-government>
			<cabinet>Council of Ministers appointed by the president</cabinet>
			<elections>president elected by popular vote for a five-year term (eligible for a second term); candidate must receive a majority of the votes cast to be elected president; election last held on 27 June 2010 with a runoff election held on 7 November 2010</elections>
			<election-results>Alpha CONDE elected president in a runoff election; percent of vote Alpha CONDE 52.5%, Cellou Dalein DIALLO 47.5%</election-results>
		</executive>
		<legislative>
			<description>the legislature was dissolved by junta leader Moussa Dadis CAMARA in December 2008 and in February 2010, the Transition Government appointed a 155 member National Transition Council (CNT) that has since acted in the legislature's place</description>
			<elections>last held on 30 June 2002</elections>
			<election-results></election-results>
		</legislative>
		<judicial>Constitutional Court; Court of First Instance or Tribunal de Premiere Instance; Court of Appeal or Cour d'Appel; Supreme Court or Cour Supreme</judicial>
		<parties>[object Object]</parties>
		<pressure-groups>TO DO</pressure-groups>
		<membership>ACP, AfDB, AU (suspended), ECOWAS (suspended), FAO, G-77, IBRD, ICAO, ICRM, IDA, IDB, IFAD, IFC, IFRCS, ILO, IMF, IMO, Interpol, IOC, IOM, ISO (correspondent), ITSO, ITU, ITUC, MIGA, MINURSO, NAM, OIC, OIF, OPCW, UN, UNCTAD, UNESCO, UNHCR, UNIDO, UNMIS, UNOCI, UNWTO, UPU, WCO, WFTU, WHO, WIPO, WMO, WTO</membership>
		<representation-in-usa>
			<chief>Ambassador Mory Karamoko KABA</chief>
			<chancery>2112 Leroy Place NW, Washington, DC 20008</chancery>
			<telephone>[1] (202) 986-4300</telephone>
			<FAX>[1] (202) 483-8688</FAX>
			<consulates></consulates>
		</representation-in-usa>
		<representation-from-usa>
			<chief>Ambassador Patricia Newton MOLLER</chief>
			<embassy>Koloma, Conakry, east of Hamdallaye Circle</embassy>
			<mailing-address>B. P. 603, Transversale No. 2, Centre Administratif de Koloma, Commune de Ratoma, Conakry</mailing-address>
			<telephone>[224] 65-10-40-00</telephone>
			<FAX>[224] 65-10-42-97</FAX>
		</representation-from-usa>
		<flag>[object Object]</flag>
		<anthem>
			<name>&quot;Liberte&quot; (Liberty)</name>
			<by>unknown/Fodeba KEITA</by>
		</anthem>
	</government>
	<economy>
		<overview>Guinea is a poor country that possesses major mineral, hydropower, and agricultural resources. The country has almost half of the world's bauxite reserves and significant iron ore, gold, and diamond reserves. However, Guinea has been unable to profit from this potential, as rampant corruption, dilapidated electricity and other degraded infrastructure, and political uncertainty have drained investor confidence. In the time since a 2008 coup following the death of long-term President Lansana CONTE, international donors, including the G-8, the IMF, and the World Bank, have significantly curtailed their development programs. Throughout 2009, policies of the ruling military junta severely weakened the economy. The junta leaders spent and printed money at an accelerated rate, driving inflation and debt to perilously high levels. In early 2010, the junta collapsed and was replaced by a Transition Government, which ceded power in December 2010 to the country's first-ever democratically elected president, Alpha CONDE. International assistance and investment are expected to return to Guinea, but the levels will depend upon the ability of the new government to combat corruption and reform its banking system. IMF and World Bank programs will be especially critical as Guinea attempts to gain debt relief. Since the 2009 global economic downturn, the price and value of bauxite and alumina exports has steadily risen. Export levels will likely continue to grow as investor confidence returns. International investors have expressed keen interest in Guinea's vast iron ore reserves, which could further propel the country's growth.</overview>
		<gdp>
			<purchasing-power-parity></purchasing-power-parity>
			<official-exchange-rate>4633000000</official-exchange-rate>
			<real-growth-rate unit="%">1.9</real-growth-rate>
			<per-capita></per-capita>
			<sector unit="%">
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
		</gdp>
		<labour>
			<force>4392000</force>
			<sector>
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
			<unemployment unit=""></unemployment>
		</labour>
		<poverty>[object Object]</poverty>
		<household-income>TO DO</household-income>
		<budget>
			<revenue unit="USD"></revenue>
			<expenditure unit="USD"></expenditure>
		</budget>
		<public-debt unit=""></public-debt>
		<consumer-inflation unit="%">15</consumer-inflation>
		<central-bank-discount-rate unit="%"></central-bank-discount-rate>
		<commercial-prime-lending-rate unit="%"></commercial-prime-lending-rate>
		<narrow-money-stock unit="USD">496200000</narrow-money-stock>
		<broad-money-stock unit="USD">830000000</broad-money-stock>
		<domestic-credit-stock unit="USD">734400000</domestic-credit-stock>
		<agriculture-products>rice, coffee, pineapples, palm kernels, cassava (tapioca), bananas, sweet potatoes; cattle, sheep, goats; timber</agriculture-products>
		<industries>bauxite, gold, diamonds, iron; alumina refining; light manufacturing, and agricultural processing</industries>
		<industrial-production-growth>[object Object]</industrial-production-growth>
		<electricity unit="kWh">
			<production></production>
			<consumption>790500000</consumption>
			<exports>0</exports>
			<imports>0</imports>
		</electricity>
		<oil>
			<production unit="bbl/day">0</production>
			<consumption unit="bbl/day">9000</consumption>
			<exports unit="bbl/day">0</exports>
			<imports unit="bbl/day">8674</imports>
			<reserves unit="bbl">0</reserves>
		</oil>
		<natural-gas>
			<production unit="cu m">0</production>
			<consumption unit="cu m">0</consumption>
			<exports unit="cu m">0</exports>
			<imports unit="cu m">0</imports>
			<reserves unit="cu m">0</reserves>
		</natural-gas>
		<exports>
			<total unit="USD"></total>
			<commodities>bauxite, alumina, gold, diamonds, coffee, fish, agricultural products</commodities>
			<partners>India 19.68%, Spain 13.18%, Russia 7.24%, Germany 6.86%, Ireland 5.87%, US 5.71%, Ukraine 5.6% (2009)</partners>
		</exports>
		<imports>
			<total unit="USD">1551000000</total>
			<commodities>petroleum products, metals, machinery, transport equipment, textiles, grain and other foodstuffs</commodities>
			<partners>China 8.67%, Netherlands 6.67%, France 4.33%, UK 4.22% (2009)</partners>
		</imports>
		<external-debt unit="USD">3072000000</external-debt>
		<exchange-rates>Guinean francs (GNF) per US dollar -</exchange-rates>
	</economy>
	<communications>
		<telephones>
			<assessment>inadequate system of open-wire lines, small radiotelephone communication stations, and new microwave radio relay system</assessment>
			<domestic>Conakry reasonably well served; coverage elsewhere remains inadequate and large companies tend to rely on their own systems for nationwide links; fixed-line teledensity less than 1 per 100 persons; mobile-cellular subscribership is expanding and exceeded 50 per 100 persons in 2009</domestic>
			<international>country code - 224; satellite earth station - 1 Intelsat (Atlantic Ocean)</international>
			<land-lines>22000</land-lines>
			<mobile>5607000</mobile>
		</telephones>
		<broadcast>government maintains marginal control over broadcast media; single state-run TV station; state-run radio broadcast station also operates several stations in rural areas; a steadily increasing number of privately-owned radio stations, nearly all in Conakry, and about a dozen community radio stations; foreign television programming available via satellite and cable subscription services (2011)</broadcast>
		<internet>
			<tld>.gn</tld>
			<hosts>14</hosts>
			<users>95000</users>
		</internet>
	</communications>
	<transport>
		<airports>
			<total>16</total>
			<paved>
				<altitude min="*" max="*"></altitude>
				<altitude min="3047m" max="*">1</altitude>
				<altitude min="2438m" max="3047m"></altitude>
				<altitude min="1524m" max="2437m">3</altitude>
				<altitude min="914m" max="1524m"></altitude>
				<altitude min="*" max="914m"></altitude>
			</paved>
		</airports>
		<ports-and-terminals>Conakry, Kamsar</ports-and-terminals>
	</transport>
	<military>
		<branches>National Armed Forces: Army, Navy (Armee de Mer or Marine Guineenne, includes Marines), Guinean Air Force (Force Aerienne de Guinee) (2009)</branches>
		<manpower>
			<population-available>
				<male>2359</male>
				<female>2329</female>
			</population-available>
			<fit-for-service>
				<male>1493</male>
				<female>1535</female>
			</fit-for-service>
			<reaching-maturity>
				<male>118443</male>
				<female>115901</female>
			</reaching-maturity>
			<notes></notes>
		</manpower>
	</military>
	<issues>
		<disputes>conflicts among rebel groups, warlords, and youth gangs in neighboring states have spilled over into Guinea resulting in domestic instability; Sierra Leone considers Guinea's definition of the flood plain limits to define the left bank boundary of the Makona and Moa rivers excessive and protests Guinea's continued occupation of these lands, including the hamlet of Yenga, occupied since 1998</disputes>
		<drugs></drugs>
	</issues>
</country>