<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<country>
	<code>ic</code>
	<name>Iceland</name>
	<region>Europe</region>
	<background>Settled by Norwegian and Celtic (Scottish and Irish) immigrants during the late 9th and 10th centuries A.D., Iceland boasts the world's oldest functioning legislative assembly, the Althing, established in 930. Independent for over 300 years, Iceland was subsequently ruled by Norway and Denmark. Fallout from the Askja volcano of 1875 devastated the Icelandic economy and caused widespread famine. Over the next quarter century, 20% of the island's population emigrated, mostly to Canada and the US. Limited home rule from Denmark was granted in 1874 and complete independence attained in 1944. The second half of the 20th century saw substantial economic growth driven primarily by the fishing industry. The economy diversified greatly after the country joined the European Economic Area in 1994, but Iceland was especially hard hit by the global financial crisis in the years following 2008. Literacy, longevity, and social cohesion are first rate by world standards.</background>
	<geo>
		<note>strategic location between Greenland and Europe; westernmost European country; Reykjavik is the northernmost national capital in the world; more land covered by glaciers than in all of continental Europe</note>
		<location>
			<desc>Northern Europe, island between the Greenland Sea and the North Atlantic Ocean, northwest of the United Kingdom</desc>
			<coordinates>TO DO</coordinates>
		</location>
		<area>
			<total unit="sq km">103000</total>
			<land unit="sq km">100250</land>
			<water unit="sq km">2750</water>
			<comparison>slightly smaller than Kentucky</comparison>
		</area>
		<boundaries>
			<borders unit="km">0</borders>
			<coastline unit="km">4970</coastline>
		</boundaries>
		<maritime-claims>
			<territorial unit="nm">12</territorial>
			<contiguous unit=""></contiguous>
			<economic unit="nm">200</economic>
			<continental-shelf>200 nm or to the edge of the continental margin</continental-shelf>
		</maritime-claims>
		<climate>temperate; moderated by North Atlantic Current; mild, windy winters; damp, cool summers</climate>
		<terrain>mostly plateau interspersed with mountain peaks, icefields; coast deeply indented by bays and fiords</terrain>
		<elevation>
			<high>Hvannadalshnukur 2,110 m (at Vatnajokull glacier)</high>
			<low>Atlantic Ocean 0 m</low>
		</elevation>
		<resources>fish, hydropower, geothermal power, diatomite</resources>
		<land-use>
			<arable unit="%">0.07</arable>
			<crops unit="%">0</crops>
			<other unit="%">99.93</other>
		</land-use>
		<hazards>[object Object]</hazards>
		<issues>water pollution from fertilizer runoff; inadequate wastewater treatment</issues>
		<water>
			<irrigated-land unit=""></irrigated-land>
			<renewable-water unit="cu km">170</renewable-water>
			<freshwater-withdrawal>
				<total unit="cu km/yr">0.17</total>
				<per-capita unit="cu m/yr">567</per-capita>
			</freshwater-withdrawal>
		</water>
		<!--
"geo": {

		"Natural hazards": "flooding is a threat in some areas of the country (e.g., parts of Jutland, along the southern coast of the island of Lolland) that are protected from the sea by a system of dikes",
		"Environment - current issues": "air pollution, principally from vehicle and power plant emissions; nitrogen and phosphorus pollution of the North Sea; drinking and surface water becoming polluted from animal wastes and pesticides",
		"Environment - international agreements": {
			"party to:": "Air Pollution, Air Pollution-Nitrogen Oxides, Air Pollution-Persistent Organic Pollutants, Air Pollution-Sulfur 85, Air Pollution-Sulfur 94, Air Pollution-Volatile Organic Compounds, Antarctic Treaty, Biodiversity, Climate Change, Climate Change-Kyoto Protocol, Desertification, Endangered Species, Environmental Modification, Hazardous Wastes, Law of the Sea, Marine Dumping, Marine Life Conservation, Ozone Layer Protection, Ship Pollution, Tropical Timber 83, Tropical Timber 94, Wetlands, Whaling",
			"signed, but not ratified:": "none of the selected agreements"
		},
		"Geography - note": "controls Danish Straits (Skagerrak and Kattegat) linking Baltic and North Seas; about one-quarter of the population lives in greater Copenhagen"

		-->
	</geo>
	<people>
		<population>
			<total>311058</total>
			<birth unit="births/1,000 population">13.29</birth>
			<death unit="deaths/1,000 population">6.96</birth>
			<migration unit="migrant(s)/1,000 population">0.53</migration>
			<growth unit="%">0.687</growth>
		</population>
		<age-distribution unit="percent">
			<group min="0" max="14">20.2</group>
			<group min="15" max="64">67.1</group>
			<group min="65"></group>
		</age-distribution>
		<median-age unit="years">
			<total>35.6</total>
			<male>35.2</male>
			<female>36.1</female>
		</median-age>
		<urbanization>
			<urban unit="% of total population">93</urban>
			<rate unit="% annual rate of change">1.5</urban>
			<cities>REYKJAVIK (capital) 198,000 (2009)</cities>
		</urbanization>
		<sex unit="male(s)/female">
			<group name="at birth" max="0">1.04</group>
			<group name="0 to 14" min="0" max="14">1.03</group>
			<group name="15 to 64" min="15" max="64">1.02</group>
			<group name="65 and over" min="65" max="0">0.83</group>
			<group name="total" min="0">1</group>
		</sex>
		<infant-mortality>
			<total unit="deaths/1,000 live births">3.2</total>
			<male unit="deaths/1,000 live births">3.34</male>
			<female unit="deaths/1,000 live births">3.05</female>
		</infant-mortality>
		<life-expectancy-at-birth>
			<total unit="years">80.9</total>
			<male unit="years">78.72</male>
			<female unit="years">83.17</female>
		</life-expectancy-at-birth>
		<fertility-rate unit="1.89">children born/woman</fertility-rate>
		<hiv>
			<prevalence>[object Object]</prevalence>
			<total>fewer than 1,000 (2009 est.)</total>
			<deaths>fewer than 100 (2009 est.)</deaths>
		</hiv>
		<infectious-disease risk="">
			<food-or-waterborne></food-or-waterborne>
			<vectorborne></vectorborne>
			<water-contact></water-contact>
		</infectious-disease>
		<drinking-water-source>[object Object]</drinking-water-source>
		<sanitation-access>[object Object]</sanitation-access>
		<nationality>
			<noun>Icelander(s)</noun>
			<adjective>Icelandic</adjective>
		</nationality>
		<ethnic-groups>homogeneous mixture of descendants of Norse and Celts 94%, population of foreign origin 6%</ethnic-groups>
		<religions>Lutheran Church of Iceland (official) 80.7%, Roman Catholic Church 2.5%, Reykjavik Free Church 2.4%, Hafnarfjorour Free Church 1.6%, other religions 3.6%, unaffiliated 3%, other or unspecified 6.2% (2006 est.)</religions>
		<languages>Icelandic, English, Nordic languages, German widely spoken</languages>
		<literacy>
			<definition>age 15 and over can read and write</definition>
			<total unit="%">99</total>
			<male unit="%">99</male>
			<female unit="%">99</female>
		</literacy>
		<school-expectancy unit="years">18</school-expectancy>
		<education-expenditure unit="% of GDP">7.4</school-expectancy>
	</people>
	<government>
		<country-name>
			<long>Republic of Iceland</long>
			<short>Iceland</short>
		</country-name>
		<dependency></dependency>
		<government-type>constitutional republic</government-type>
		<capital>
			<name>Reykjavik</name>
			<coordinates>64° 9' N, 21° 57' W</coordinates>
			<time-difference>UTC 0 (5 hours ahead of Washington, DC during Standard Time)</time-difference>
		</capital>
		<administrative-divisions>8 regions; Austurland, Hofudhborgarsvaedhi, Nordhurland Eystra, Nordhurland Vestra, Sudhurland, Sudhurnes, Vestfirdhir, Vesturland</administrative-divisions>
		<independence>1 December 1918 (became a sovereign state under the Danish Crown); 17 June 1944 (from Denmark)</independence>
		<national-holiday>Independence Day, 17 June (1944)</national-holiday>
		<legal-system>civil law system influenced by the Danish model</legal-system>
		<suffrage>18 years of age; universal</suffrage>
		<executive>
			<head-of-state>President Olafur Ragnar GRIMSSON (since 1 August 1996)</head-of-state>
			<head-of-government>Prime Minister Johanna SIGURDARDOTTIR (since 1 February 2009);</head-of-government>
			<cabinet>Cabinet appointed by the prime minister</cabinet>
			<elections>president, a largely ceremonial post, elected by popular vote for a four-year term (no term limits); election last held on 28 June 2004 (next to be held in June 2012); note - the presidential election of 28 June 2008 was not held because Olafur Ragnar GRIMSSON had no challengers; he was sworn in on 1 August 2008; following legislative elections, the leader of the majority party or the leader of the majority coalition usually the prime minister</elections>
			<election-results>Olafur Ragnar GRIMSSON elected president; percent of vote - Olafur Ragnar GRIMSSON 85.6%, Baldur AGUSTSSON 12.5%, Astthor MAGNUSSON 1.9%;</election-results>
		</executive>
		<legislative>
			<description>unicameral Althingi (parliament) (63 seats; members elected by popular vote to serve four-year terms)</description>
			<elections>last held on 25 April 2009 (next to be held in 2013)</elections>
			<election-results>percent of vote by party - Social Democratic Alliance 29.8%, Independence Party 23.7%, Left-Green Movement 21.7%, Progressive Party 14.8%, Citizens' Movement 7.2%, other 2.8%; seats by party - Social Democratic Alliance 20, Independence Party 16, Left-Green Alliance 14, Progressive Party 9, Citizens' Movement 4</election-results>
		</legislative>
		<judicial>Supreme Court or Haestirettur (justices are appointed for life by the Minister of Justice); eight district courts (justices are appointed for life by the Minister of Justice)</judicial>
		<parties>Independence Party or IP [Bjarni BENEDIKTSSON]; Left-Green Movement or LGM [Steingrimur SIGFUSSON]; Progressive Party or PP [Sigmundur David GUNNLAUGSSON]; Social Democratic Alliance or SDA [Johanna SIGURDARDOTTIR]; The Movement [Birgitta JONSDOTTIR]</parties>
		<pressure-groups>TO DO</pressure-groups>
		<membership>Arctic Council, Australia Group, BIS, CBSS, CE, EAPC, EBRD, EFTA, EU (candidate country), FAO, FATF, IAEA, IBRD, ICAO, ICC, ICRM, IDA, IFAD, IFC, IFRCS, IHO, ILO, IMF, IMO, IMSO, Interpol, IOC, IPU, ISO, ITSO, ITU, ITUC, MIGA, NATO, NC, NEA, NIB, NSG, OAS (observer), OECD, OPCW, OSCE, PCA, Schengen Convention, UN, UNCTAD, UNESCO, UPU, WCO, WHO, WIPO, WMO, WTO</membership>
		<representation-in-usa>
			<chief>Ambassador Hjalmar W. HANNESSON</chief>
			<chancery>House of Sweden, 2900 K Street NW #509, Washington, DC 20007</chancery>
			<telephone>[1] (202) 265-6653</telephone>
			<FAX>[1] (202) 265-6656</FAX>
			<consulates>New York</consulates>
		</representation-in-usa>
		<representation-from-usa>
			<chief>Ambassador Luis E. ARREAGA</chief>
			<embassy>Laufasvegur 21, 101 Reykjavik</embassy>
			<mailing-address>US Department of State, 5640 Reykjavik Place, Washington, D.C. 20521-5640</mailing-address>
			<telephone>[354] 562-9100</telephone>
			<FAX>[354] 562-9118</FAX>
		</representation-from-usa>
		<flag>blue with a red cross outlined in white extending to the edges of the flag; the vertical part of the cross is shifted to the hoist side in the style of the Dannebrog (Danish flag); the colors represent three of the elements that make up the island: red is for the island's volcanic fires, white recalls the snow and ice fields of the island, and blue is for the surrounding ocean</flag>
		<anthem>
			<name>&quot;Lofsongur&quot; (Song of Praise)</name>
			<by>Matthias JOCHUMSSON/Sveinbjorn SVEINBJORNSSON</by>
		</anthem>
	</government>
	<economy>
		<overview>Iceland's Scandinavian-type social-market economy combines a capitalist structure and free-market principles with an extensive welfare system. Prior to the 2008 crisis, Iceland had achieved high growth, low unemployment, and a remarkably even distribution of income. The economy depends heavily on the fishing industry, which provides 40% of export earnings, more than 12% of GDP, and employs 7% of the work force. It remains sensitive to declining fish stocks as well as to fluctuations in world prices for its main exports: fish and fish products, aluminum, and ferrosilicon. Iceland's economy has been diversifying into manufacturing and service industries in the last decade, particularly within the fields of software production, biotechnology, and tourism. Abundant geothermal and hydropower sources have attracted substantial foreign investment in the aluminum sector and boosted economic growth, although the financial crisis has put several investment projects on hold. Much of Iceland's economic growth in recent years came as the result of a boom in domestic demand following the rapid expansion of the country's financial sector. Domestic banks expanded aggressively in foreign markets, and consumers and businesses borrowed heavily in foreign currencies, following the privatization of the banking sector in the early 2000s. Worsening global financial conditions throughout 2008 resulted in a sharp depreciation of the krona vis-a-vis other major currencies. The foreign exposure of Icelandic banks, whose loans and other assets totaled more than 10 times the country's GDP, became unsustainable. Iceland's three largest banks collapsed in late 2008. The country secured over $10 billion in loans from the IMF and other countries to stabilize its currency and financial sector, and to back government guarantees for foreign deposits in Icelandic banks. GDP fell 6.8% in 2009, and unemployment peaked at 9.4% in February 2009. GDP fell 3.4% in 2010. Since the collapse of Iceland's financial sector, government economic priorities have included: stabilizing the krona, reducing Iceland's high budget deficit, containing inflation, restructuring the financial sector, and diversifying the economy. Three new banks were established to take over the domestic assets of the collapsed banks. Two of them have foreign majority ownership, while the State holds a majority of the shares of the third. British and Dutch authorities have pressed claims totaling over $5 billion against Iceland to compensate their citizens for losses suffered on deposits held in the failed Icelandic bank, Landsbanki Islands. Iceland agreed to new terms with the UK and the Netherlands to compensate British and Dutch depositors, but the agreement must first be approved by the Icelandic President. Iceland began accession negotiations with the EU in July 2010; however, public support has dropped substantially because of concern about losing control over fishing resources and in reaction to measures taken by Brussels during the ongoing Eurozone crisis.</overview>
		<gdp>
			<purchasing-power-parity></purchasing-power-parity>
			<official-exchange-rate>12590000000</official-exchange-rate>
			<real-growth-rate unit=""></real-growth-rate>
			<per-capita></per-capita>
			<sector unit="%">
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
		</gdp>
		<labour>
			<force>178800</force>
			<sector>
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
			<unemployment unit="%">8.3</unemployment>
		</labour>
		<poverty>NA%</poverty>
		<household-income>TO DO</household-income>
		<budget>
			<revenue unit="USD"></revenue>
			<expenditure unit="USD"></expenditure>
		</budget>
		<public-debt unit="% of GDP">123.8</public-debt>
		<consumer-inflation unit="%">5.5</consumer-inflation>
		<central-bank-discount-rate unit="%">14.55</central-bank-discount-rate>
		<commercial-prime-lending-rate unit="%">18.99</commercial-prime-lending-rate>
		<narrow-money-stock unit="USD">4413000000</narrow-money-stock>
		<broad-money-stock unit="USD">19970000000</broad-money-stock>
		<domestic-credit-stock unit="USD">46030000000</domestic-credit-stock>
		<agriculture-products>potatoes, green vegetables; mutton, chicken, pork, beef, dairy products; fish</agriculture-products>
		<industries>fish processing; aluminum smelting, ferrosilicon production; geothermal power, hydropower, tourism</industries>
		<industrial-production-growth>-1% (2010 est.)</industrial-production-growth>
		<electricity unit="kWh">
			<production>16840000000</production>
			<consumption>16480000000</consumption>
			<exports>0</exports>
			<imports>0</imports>
		</electricity>
		<oil>
			<production unit="bbl/day">0</production>
			<consumption unit="bbl/day">18900</consumption>
			<exports unit="bbl/day">1915</exports>
			<imports unit="bbl/day">16390</imports>
			<reserves unit="bbl">0</reserves>
		</oil>
		<natural-gas>
			<production unit="cu m">0</production>
			<consumption unit="cu m">0</consumption>
			<exports unit="cu m">0</exports>
			<imports unit="cu m">0</imports>
			<reserves unit="cu m">0</reserves>
		</natural-gas>
		<exports>
			<total unit="USD"></total>
			<commodities>fish and fish products 40%, aluminum, animal products, ferrosilicon, diatomite</commodities>
			<partners>Netherlands 30.71%, UK 12.73%, Germany 11.21%, Norway 5.75%, Spain 4.82% (2009)</partners>
		</exports>
		<imports>
			<total unit="USD">3677000000</total>
			<commodities>machinery and equipment, petroleum products, foodstuffs, textiles</commodities>
			<partners>Norway 12.97%, Netherlands 8.62%, Germany 8.3%, Sweden 8.03%, Denmark 7.27%, US 6.94%, China 4.98%, UK 4.55%, Brazil 4.09% (2009)</partners>
		</imports>
		<external-debt unit="USD">3073000000</external-debt>
		<exchange-rates>Icelandic kronur (ISK) per US dollar -</exchange-rates>
	</economy>
	<communications>
		<telephones>
			<assessment>telecommunications infrastructure is modern and fully digitized, with satellite-earth stations, fiber-optic cables, and an extensive broadband network</assessment>
			<domestic>liberalization of the telecommunications sector beginning in the late 1990s has led to increased competition especially in the mobile services segment of the market</domestic>
			<international>country code - 354; the CANTAT-3 and FARICE-1 submarine cable systems provide connectivity to Canada, the Faroe Islands, UK, Denmark, and Germany; a planned new section of the Hibernia-Atlantic submarine cable will provide additional connectivity to Canada, US, and Ireland; satellite earth stations - 2 Intelsat (Atlantic Ocean), 1 Inmarsat (Atlantic and Indian Ocean regions); note - Iceland shares the Inmarsat earth station with the other Nordic countries (Denmark, Finland, Norway, and Sweden)</international>
			<land-lines>185200</land-lines>
			<mobile>349000</mobile>
		</telephones>
		<broadcast>state-owned public television broadcaster operates 1 TV channel nationally; several privately-owned TV stations broadcast nationally and roughly another half-dozen operate locally; about half the households utilize multi-channel cable or satellite TV services; state-owned public radio broadcaster operates 2 national networks and 4 regional stations; 2 privately-owned radio stations operate nationally and another 15 provide more limited coverage (2007)</broadcast>
		<internet>
			<tld>.is</tld>
			<hosts>344748</hosts>
			<users>301600</users>
		</internet>
	</communications>
	<transport>
		<airports>
			<total>99</total>
			<paved>
				<altitude min="*" max="*"></altitude>
				<altitude min="3047m" max="*">1</altitude>
				<altitude min="2438m" max="3047m"></altitude>
				<altitude min="1524m" max="2437m">3</altitude>
				<altitude min="914m" max="1524m">2</altitude>
				<altitude min="*" max="914m"></altitude>
			</paved>
		</airports>
		<ports-and-terminals>Grundartangi, Hafnarfjordur, Reykjavik</ports-and-terminals>
	</transport>
	<military>
		<branches>no regular military forces; Icelandic National Police (2008)</branches>
		<manpower>
			<population-available>
				<male>75337</male>
				<female></female>
			</population-available>
			<fit-for-service>
				<male>62781</male>
				<female>61511</female>
			</fit-for-service>
			<reaching-maturity>
				<male>2277</male>
				<female>2200</female>
			</reaching-maturity>
			<notes>Iceland has no standing military force; under a 1951 bilateral agreement - still valid - its defense was provided by the US-manned Icelandic Defense Force (IDF) headquartered at Keflavik; however, all US military forces in Iceland were withdrawn as of October 2006; although wartime defense of Iceland remains a NATO commitment, in April 2007, Iceland and Norway signed a bilateral agreement providing for Norwegian aerial surveillance and defense of Icelandic airspace (2008)</notes>
		</manpower>
	</military>
	<issues>
		<disputes>Iceland, the UK, and Ireland dispute Denmark's claim that the Faroe Islands' continental shelf extends beyond 200 nm</disputes>
		<drugs></drugs>
	</issues>
</country>