<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<country>
	<code>ke</code>
	<name>Kenya</name>
	<region>Africa</region>
	<background>Founding president and liberation struggle icon Jomo KENYATTA led Kenya from independence in 1963 until his death in 1978, when President Daniel Toroitich arap MOI took power in a constitutional succession. The country was a de facto one-party state from 1969 until 1982 when the ruling Kenya African National Union (KANU) made itself the sole legal party in Kenya. MOI acceded to internal and external pressure for political liberalization in late 1991. The ethnically fractured opposition failed to dislodge KANU from power in elections in 1992 and 1997, which were marred by violence and fraud, but were viewed as having generally reflected the will of the Kenyan people. President MOI stepped down in December 2002 following fair and peaceful elections. Mwai KIBAKI, running as the candidate of the multiethnic, united opposition group, the National Rainbow Coalition (NARC), defeated KANU candidate Uhuru KENYATTA and assumed the presidency following a campaign centered on an anticorruption platform. KIBAKI's NARC coalition splintered in 2005 over a constitutional review process. Government defectors joined with KANU to form a new opposition coalition, the Orange Democratic Movement, which defeated the government's draft constitution in a popular referendum in November 2005. KIBAKI's reelection in December 2007 brought charges of vote rigging from ODM candidate Raila ODINGA and unleashed two months of violence in which as many as 1,500 people died. UN-sponsored talks in late February produced a powersharing accord bringing ODINGA into the government in the restored position of prime minister. Kenya in August 2010 adopted a new constitution that eliminates the role of prime minister after the next presidential election.</background>
	<geo>
		<note>the Kenyan Highlands comprise one of the most successful agricultural production regions in Africa; glaciers are found on Mount Kenya, Africa's second highest peak; unique physiography supports abundant and varied wildlife of scientific and economic value</note>
		<location>
			<desc>Eastern Africa, bordering the Indian Ocean, between Somalia and Tanzania</desc>
			<coordinates>TO DO</coordinates>
		</location>
		<area>
			<total unit="sq km">580367</total>
			<land unit="sq km">569140</land>
			<water unit="sq km">11227</water>
			<comparison>slightly more than twice the size of Nevada</comparison>
		</area>
		<boundaries>
			<borders unit=""></borders>
			<coastline unit="km">536</coastline>
		</boundaries>
		<maritime-claims>
			<territorial unit="nm">12</territorial>
			<contiguous unit=""></contiguous>
			<economic unit="nm">200</economic>
			<continental-shelf>200 m depth or to the depth of exploitation</continental-shelf>
		</maritime-claims>
		<climate>varies from tropical along coast to arid in interior</climate>
		<terrain>low plains rise to central highlands bisected by Great Rift Valley; fertile plateau in west</terrain>
		<elevation>
			<high>Mount Kenya 5,199 m</high>
			<low>Indian Ocean 0 m</low>
		</elevation>
		<resources>limestone, soda ash, salt, gemstones, fluorspar, zinc, diatomite, gypsum, wildlife, hydropower</resources>
		<land-use>
			<arable unit="%">8.01</arable>
			<crops unit="%">0.97</crops>
			<other unit="%">91.02</other>
		</land-use>
		<hazards>[object Object]</hazards>
		<issues>water pollution from urban and industrial wastes; degradation of water quality from increased use of pesticides and fertilizers; water hyacinth infestation in Lake Victoria; deforestation; soil erosion; desertification; poaching</issues>
		<water>
			<irrigated-land unit="sq km">1030</irrigated-land>
			<renewable-water unit="cu km">30.2</renewable-water>
			<freshwater-withdrawal>
				<total unit="cu km/yr">1.58</total>
				<per-capita unit="cu m/yr">46</per-capita>
			</freshwater-withdrawal>
		</water>
		<!--
"geo": {

		"Natural hazards": "flooding is a threat in some areas of the country (e.g., parts of Jutland, along the southern coast of the island of Lolland) that are protected from the sea by a system of dikes",
		"Environment - current issues": "air pollution, principally from vehicle and power plant emissions; nitrogen and phosphorus pollution of the North Sea; drinking and surface water becoming polluted from animal wastes and pesticides",
		"Environment - international agreements": {
			"party to:": "Air Pollution, Air Pollution-Nitrogen Oxides, Air Pollution-Persistent Organic Pollutants, Air Pollution-Sulfur 85, Air Pollution-Sulfur 94, Air Pollution-Volatile Organic Compounds, Antarctic Treaty, Biodiversity, Climate Change, Climate Change-Kyoto Protocol, Desertification, Endangered Species, Environmental Modification, Hazardous Wastes, Law of the Sea, Marine Dumping, Marine Life Conservation, Ozone Layer Protection, Ship Pollution, Tropical Timber 83, Tropical Timber 94, Wetlands, Whaling",
			"signed, but not ratified:": "none of the selected agreements"
		},
		"Geography - note": "controls Danish Straits (Skagerrak and Kattegat) linking Baltic and North Seas; about one-quarter of the population lives in greater Copenhagen"

		-->
	</geo>
	<people>
		<population>
			<total>41070</total>
			<birth unit="births/1,000 population">33.54</birth>
			<death unit="deaths/1,000 population">8.93</birth>
			<migration unit="migrant(s)/1,000 population">0</migration>
			<growth unit="%">2.462</growth>
		</population>
		<age-distribution unit="percent">
			<group min="0" max="14">42.2</group>
			<group min="15" max="64">55.1</group>
			<group min="65"></group>
		</age-distribution>
		<median-age unit="years">
			<total>18.9</total>
			<male>18.8</male>
			<female>19</female>
		</median-age>
		<urbanization>
			<urban unit="% of total population">22</urban>
			<rate unit="% annual rate of change">4.2</urban>
			<cities>NAIROBI (capital) 3.375 million; Mombassa 966,000 (2009)</cities>
		</urbanization>
		<sex unit="male(s)/female">
			<group name="at birth" max="0">1.02</group>
			<group name="0 to 14" min="0" max="14">1.01</group>
			<group name="15 to 64" min="15" max="64">1.01</group>
			<group name="65 and over" min="65" max="0">0.83</group>
			<group name="total" min="0">1.01</group>
		</sex>
		<infant-mortality>
			<total unit="deaths/1,000 live births">52.29</total>
			<male unit="deaths/1,000 live births">55.03</male>
			<female unit="deaths/1,000 live births">49.49</female>
		</infant-mortality>
		<life-expectancy-at-birth>
			<total unit="years">59.48</total>
			<male unit="years">58.91</male>
			<female unit="years">60.07</female>
		</life-expectancy-at-birth>
		<fertility-rate unit="4.19">children born/woman</fertility-rate>
		<hiv>
			<prevalence>[object Object]</prevalence>
			<total>1500000</total>
			<deaths>80000</deaths>
		</hiv>
		<infectious-disease risk="high">
			<food-or-waterborne>bacterial and protozoal diarrhea, hepatitis A, and typhoid fever</food-or-waterborne>
			<vectorborne></vectorborne>
			<water-contact></water-contact>
		</infectious-disease>
		<drinking-water-source>[object Object]</drinking-water-source>
		<sanitation-access>[object Object]</sanitation-access>
		<nationality>
			<noun>Kenyan(s)</noun>
			<adjective>Kenyan</adjective>
		</nationality>
		<ethnic-groups>Kikuyu 22%, Luhya 14%, Luo 13%, Kalenjin 12%, Kamba 11%, Kisii 6%, Meru 6%, other African 15%, non-African (Asian, European, and Arab) 1%</ethnic-groups>
		<religions>[object Object]</religions>
		<languages>English (official), Kiswahili (official), numerous indigenous languages</languages>
		<literacy>
			<definition>age 15 and over can read and write</definition>
			<total unit="%">85.1</total>
			<male unit="%">90.6</male>
			<female unit="%">79.7</female>
		</literacy>
		<school-expectancy unit="years">11</school-expectancy>
		<education-expenditure unit="% of GDP">7</school-expectancy>
	</people>
	<government>
		<country-name>
			<long>Republic of Kenya</long>
			<short>Kenya</short>
		</country-name>
		<dependency></dependency>
		<government-type>republic</government-type>
		<capital>
			<name>Nairobi</name>
			<coordinates>1° 17' S, 36° 49' E</coordinates>
			<time-difference>UTC+3 (8 hours ahead of Washington, DC during Standard Time)</time-difference>
		</capital>
		<administrative-divisions>7 provinces and 1 area*; Central, Coast, Eastern, Nairobi Area*, North Eastern, Nyanza, Rift Valley, Western; note - the constitution promulgated in August 2010 designates 47 yet-to-be-defined counties as first-order administrative units</administrative-divisions>
		<independence>12 December 1963 (from the UK)</independence>
		<national-holiday>Independence Day, 12 December (1963); Madaraka Day, 1 June; Mashujaa Day, 20 October</national-holiday>
		<legal-system>mixed legal system of English common law, Islamic law, and customary law; judicial review in High Court</legal-system>
		<suffrage>18 years of age; universal</suffrage>
		<executive>
			<head-of-state>President Mwai KIBAKI (since 30 December 2002); Vice President Stephen Kalonzo MUSYOKA (since 10 January 2008);</head-of-state>
			<head-of-government>President Mwai KIBAKI (since 30 December 2002); Vice President Stephen Kalonzo MUSYOKA (since 10 January 2008); Prime Minister Raila Amolo ODINGA (since 17 April 2008); note - according to the 2008 powersharing agreement the role of the prime minister was not well defined; constitutionally, the president remains chief of state and head of government, but the prime minister is charged with coordinating government business</head-of-government>
			<cabinet>Cabinet appointed by the president and chaired by the prime minister, who is the leader of the largest party in parliament</cabinet>
			<elections>president elected by popular vote for a five-year term (eligible for a second term); in addition to receiving the largest number of votes in absolute terms, the presidential candidate must also win 25% or more of the vote in at least five of Kenya's seven provinces and one area to avoid a runoff; election last held on 27 December 2007 (next to be held in December 2012); vice president appointed by the president; note - the new constitution sets elections for August 2011 but this date is expected to slip</elections>
			<election-results>President Mwai KIBAKI reelected; percent of vote - Mwai KIBAKI 46%, Raila ODINGA 44%, Kalonzo MUSYOKA 9%, other 3.4%</election-results>
		</executive>
		<legislative>
			<description>unicameral National Assembly or Bunge usually referred to as Parliament (224 seats; 210 members elected by popular vote to serve five-year terms, 12 nominated members appointed by the president but selected by the parties in proportion to their parliamentary vote totals, 2 ex-officio members); note - the constitution promulgated in August 2010 changes the legislature to a bicameral parliament consisting of a 290 member National Assembly and a 94 member Senate; parliament members will serve five year terms</description>
			<elections>last held on 27 December 2007 (next to be held in December 2012)</elections>
			<election-results>percent of vote by party - NA; seats by party - ODM 99, PNU 46, ODM-K 16, KANU 14 other 35; ex-officio 2; seats appointed by the president - ODM 6, PNU 3, ODM-K 2, KANU 1</election-results>
		</legislative>
		<judicial>Court of Appeal (chief justice is appointed by the president); High Court; note - the constitution promulgated in August 2010 specifies three superior courts consisting of a Supreme Court, Court of Appeals, and High Court, and three subordinate courts consisting of Magistrate courts, Kadhis courts (sentences according to Muslim law), and Courts Martial</judicial>
		<parties>Forum for the Restoration of Democracy-Kenya or FORD-Kenya [Musikari KOMBO]; Forum for the Restoration of Democracy-People or FORD-People [Reuben OYONDI]; Kenya African National Union or KANU [Uhuru KENYATTA]; National Rainbow Coalition-Kenya or NARC-Kenya [Martha KARUA]; Orange Democratic Movement or ODM [Raila ODINGA]; Orange Democratic Movement-Kenya or ODM-K [Kalonzo MUSYOKA]; Party of National Unity or PNU [Mwai KIBAKI]; Shirikisho Party of Kenya or SPK [Chirau Ali MWAKWERE]</parties>
		<pressure-groups>TO DO</pressure-groups>
		<membership>ACP, AfDB, AU, C, COMESA, EAC, EADB, FAO, G-15, G-77, IAEA, IBRD, ICAO, ICRM, IDA, IFAD, IFC, IFRCS, IGAD, ILO, IMF, IMO, IMSO, Interpol, IOC, IOM, IPU, ISO, ITSO, ITU, ITUC, MIGA, MONUSCO, NAM, OPCW, PCA, UN, UNAMID, UNCTAD, UNESCO, UNHCR, UNIDO, UNMIS, UNWTO, UPU, WCO, WHO, WIPO, WMO, WTO</membership>
		<representation-in-usa>
			<chief>Ambassador Elkanah ODEMBO Absalom</chief>
			<chancery>2249 R Street NW, Washington, DC 20008</chancery>
			<telephone>[1] (202) 387-6101</telephone>
			<FAX>[1] (202) 462-3829</FAX>
			<consulates>Los Angeles</consulates>
		</representation-in-usa>
		<representation-from-usa>
			<chief>Ambassador Michael E. RANNEBERGER</chief>
			<embassy>US Embassy, United Nations Avenue, Nairobi; P. O. Box 606 Village Market, Nairobi 00621</embassy>
			<mailing-address>Box 21A, Unit 64100, APO AE 09831</mailing-address>
			<telephone>[254] (20) 363-6000</telephone>
			<FAX>[254] (20) 363-410</FAX>
		</representation-from-usa>
		<flag>three equal horizontal bands of black (top), red, and green; the red band is edged in white; a large Maasai warrior's shield covering crossed spears is superimposed at the center; black symbolizes the majority population, red the blood shed in the struggle for freedom, green stands for natural wealth, and white for peace; the shield and crossed spears symbolize the defense of freedom</flag>
		<anthem>
			<name>&quot;Ee Mungu Nguvu Yetu&quot; (Oh God of All Creation)</name>
			<by>Graham HYSLOP, Thomas KALUME, Peter KIBUKOSYA, Washington OMONDI, and George W. SENOGA-ZAKE/traditional, adapted by Graham HYSLOP, Thomas KALUME, Peter KIBUKOSYA, Washington OMONDI, and George W. SENOGA-ZAKE</by>
		</anthem>
	</government>
	<economy>
		<overview>Although the regional hub for trade and finance in East Africa, Kenya has been hampered by corruption and by reliance upon several primary goods whose prices have remained low. In 1997, the IMF suspended Kenya's Enhanced Structural Adjustment Program due to the government's failure to maintain reforms and curb corruption. The IMF, which had resumed loans in 2000 to help Kenya through a drought, again halted lending in 2001 when the government failed to institute several anticorruption measures. In the key December 2002 elections, Daniel Arap MOI's 24-year-old reign ended, and a new opposition government took on the formidable economic problems facing the nation. After some early progress in rooting out corruption and encouraging donor support, the KIBAKI government was rocked by high-level graft scandals in 2005 and 2006. In 2006, the World Bank and IMF delayed loans pending action by the government on corruption. The international financial institutions and donors have since resumed lending, despite little action on the government's part to deal with corruption. Post-election violence in early 2008, coupled with the effects of the global financial crisis on remittance and exports, reduced GDP growth to 1.7 in 2008, but the economy rebounded in 2009-10.</overview>
		<gdp>
			<purchasing-power-parity></purchasing-power-parity>
			<official-exchange-rate>32159999999.999996</official-exchange-rate>
			<real-growth-rate unit="%">5</real-growth-rate>
			<per-capita></per-capita>
			<sector unit="%">
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
		</gdp>
		<labour>
			<force>17940000</force>
			<sector>
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
			<unemployment unit="%">40</unemployment>
		</labour>
		<poverty>[object Object]</poverty>
		<household-income>TO DO</household-income>
		<budget>
			<revenue unit="USD"></revenue>
			<expenditure unit="USD"></expenditure>
		</budget>
		<public-debt unit="% of GDP">50.9</public-debt>
		<consumer-inflation unit="%">4.2</consumer-inflation>
		<central-bank-discount-rate unit="%"></central-bank-discount-rate>
		<commercial-prime-lending-rate unit="%">14.8</commercial-prime-lending-rate>
		<narrow-money-stock unit="USD">6333000000</narrow-money-stock>
		<broad-money-stock unit="USD">15380000000</broad-money-stock>
		<domestic-credit-stock unit="USD">14110000000</domestic-credit-stock>
		<agriculture-products>tea, coffee, corn, wheat, sugarcane, fruit, vegetables; dairy products, beef, pork, poultry, eggs</agriculture-products>
		<industries>small-scale consumer goods (plastic, furniture, batteries, textiles, clothing, soap, cigarettes, flour), agricultural products, horticulture, oil refining; aluminum, steel, lead; cement, commercial ship repair, tourism</industries>
		<industrial-production-growth>[object Object]</industrial-production-growth>
		<electricity unit="kWh">
			<production>5223000000</production>
			<consumption>4863000000</consumption>
			<exports>58300000</exports>
			<imports>22500000</imports>
		</electricity>
		<oil>
			<production unit="bbl/day">0</production>
			<consumption unit="bbl/day">76000</consumption>
			<exports unit="bbl/day">7270</exports>
			<imports unit="bbl/day">80530</imports>
			<reserves unit="bbl">0</reserves>
		</oil>
		<natural-gas>
			<production unit="cu m">0</production>
			<consumption unit="cu m">0</consumption>
			<exports unit="cu m">0</exports>
			<imports unit="cu m">0</imports>
			<reserves unit="cu m">0</reserves>
		</natural-gas>
		<exports>
			<total unit="USD"></total>
			<commodities>tea, horticultural products, coffee, petroleum products, fish, cement</commodities>
			<partners>UK 11.31%, Netherlands 9.81%, Uganda 9.07%, Tanzania 8.83%, US 5.93%, Pakistan 5.63% (2009)</partners>
		</exports>
		<imports>
			<total unit="USD">10400000000</total>
			<commodities>machinery and transportation equipment, petroleum products, motor vehicles, iron and steel, resins and plastics</commodities>
			<partners>India 11.67%, China 10.58%, UAE 9.32%, South Africa 8.36%, Saudi Arabia 6.53%, US 6.25%, Japan 5.1% (2009)</partners>
		</imports>
		<external-debt unit="USD">7935000000</external-debt>
		<exchange-rates>Kenyan shillings (KES) per US dollar -</exchange-rates>
	</economy>
	<communications>
		<telephones>
			<assessment>inadequate; fixed-line telephone system is small and inefficient; trunks are primarily microwave radio relay; business data commonly transferred by a very small aperture terminal (VSAT) system</assessment>
			<domestic>sole fixed-line provider, Telkom Kenya, is slated for privatization; multiple providers in the mobile-cellular segment of the market fostering a boom in mobile-cellular telephone usage with teledensity reaching 50 per 100 persons in 2009</domestic>
			<international>country code - 254; The East Africa Marine System (TEAMS) and the SEACOM undersea fiber-optic cable systems; satellite earth stations - 4 Intelsat</international>
			<land-lines>664100</land-lines>
			<mobile>19365000</mobile>
		</telephones>
		<broadcast>about a half-dozen privately-owned TV stations and a state-owned television broadcaster that operates 2 channels; satellite and cable TV subscription services are available; state-owned radio broadcaster operates 2 national radio channels and provides regional and local radio services in multiple languages; a large number of private radio broadcasters, including provincial stations broadcasting in local languages; transmissions of several international broadcasters are available (2007)</broadcast>
		<internet>
			<tld>.ke</tld>
			<hosts>47676</hosts>
			<users>3996000</users>
		</internet>
	</communications>
	<transport>
		<airports>
			<total>191</total>
			<paved>
				<altitude min="*" max="*"></altitude>
				<altitude min="3047m" max="*">4</altitude>
				<altitude min="2438m" max="3047m">2</altitude>
				<altitude min="1524m" max="2437m">4</altitude>
				<altitude min="914m" max="1524m">6</altitude>
				<altitude min="*" max="914m"></altitude>
			</paved>
		</airports>
		<ports-and-terminals>Kisumu, Mombasa</ports-and-terminals>
	</transport>
	<military>
		<branches>Kenya Armed Forces: Kenya Army, Kenya Navy, Kenya Air Force (2010)</branches>
		<manpower>
			<population-available>
				<male>9768</male>
				<female>9466</female>
			</population-available>
			<fit-for-service>
				<male>6361</male>
				<female>6106</female>
			</fit-for-service>
			<reaching-maturity>
				<male>422104</male>
				<female>416927</female>
			</reaching-maturity>
			<notes></notes>
		</manpower>
	</military>
	<issues>
		<disputes>Kenya served as an important mediator in brokering Sudan's north-south separation in February 2005; Kenya provides shelter to almost a quarter of a million refugees, including Ugandans who flee across the border periodically to seek protection from Lord's Resistance Army (LRA) rebels; Kenya works hard to prevent the clan and militia fighting in Somalia from spreading across the border, which has long been open to nomadic pastoralists; the boundary that separates Kenya's and Sudan's sovereignty is unclear in the &quot;Ilemi Triangle,&quot; which Kenya has administered since colonial times</disputes>
		<drugs>widespread harvesting of small plots of marijuana; transit country for South Asian heroin destined for Europe and North America; Indian methaqualone also transits on way to South Africa; significant potential for money-laundering activity given the country's status as a regional financial center; massive corruption, and relatively high levels of narcotics-associated activities</drugs>
	</issues>
</country>