<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<country>
	<code>ks</code>
	<name>Korea, South</name>
	<region>East &amp; Southeast Asia</region>
	<background>An independent Korean state or collection of states has existed almost continuously for several millennia. Between its initial unification in the 7th century - from three predecessor Korean states - until the 20th century, Korea existed as a single independent country. In 1905, following the Russo-Japanese War, Korea became a protectorate of imperial Japan, and in 1910 it was annexed as a colony. Korea regained its independence following Japan's surrender to the United States in 1945. After World War II, a Republic of Korea (ROK) was set up in the southern half of the Korean Peninsula while a Communist-style government was installed in the north (the DPRK). During the Korean War (1950-53), US troops and UN forces fought alongside soldiers from the ROK to defend South Korea from DPRK attacks supported by China and the Soviet Union. An armistice was signed in 1953, splitting the peninsula along a demilitarized zone at about the 38th parallel. Thereafter, South Korea achieved rapid economic growth with per capita income rising to roughly 17 times the level of North Korea. In 1993, KIM Young-sam became South Korea's first civilian president following 32 years of military rule. South Korea today is a fully functioning modern democracy. President LEE Myung-bak has pursued a policy of global engagement since taking office in February 2008, highlighted by Seoul's hosting of the G-20 summit in November 2010. Serious tensions with North Korea have punctuated inter-Korean relations in recent years, including the North's sinking of the South Korean warship Cheonan in March 2010 and its artillery attack on South Korean soldiers and citizens in November 2010.</background>
	<geo>
		<note>strategic location on Korea Strait</note>
		<location>
			<desc>Eastern Asia, southern half of the Korean Peninsula bordering the Sea of Japan and the Yellow Sea</desc>
			<coordinates>TO DO</coordinates>
		</location>
		<area>
			<total unit="sq km">99720</total>
			<land unit="sq km">96920</land>
			<water unit="sq km">2800</water>
			<comparison>slightly larger than Indiana</comparison>
		</area>
		<boundaries>
			<borders unit=""></borders>
			<coastline unit="km">2413</coastline>
		</boundaries>
		<maritime-claims>
			<territorial unit=""></territorial>
			<contiguous unit="nm">24</contiguous>
			<economic unit="nm">200</economic>
			<continental-shelf>not specified</continental-shelf>
		</maritime-claims>
		<climate>temperate, with rainfall heavier in summer than winter</climate>
		<terrain>mostly hills and mountains; wide coastal plains in west and south</terrain>
		<elevation>
			<high>Halla-san 1,950 m</high>
			<low>Sea of Japan 0 m</low>
		</elevation>
		<resources>coal, tungsten, graphite, molybdenum, lead, hydropower potential</resources>
		<land-use>
			<arable unit="%">16.58</arable>
			<crops unit="%">2.01</crops>
			<other unit="%">81.41</other>
		</land-use>
		<hazards>[object Object]</hazards>
		<issues>air pollution in large cities; acid rain; water pollution from the discharge of sewage and industrial effluents; drift net fishing</issues>
		<water>
			<irrigated-land unit="sq km">8320</irrigated-land>
			<renewable-water unit="cu km">69.7</renewable-water>
			<freshwater-withdrawal>
				<total unit="cu km/yr">18.59</total>
				<per-capita unit="cu m/yr">389</per-capita>
			</freshwater-withdrawal>
		</water>
		<!--
"geo": {

		"Natural hazards": "flooding is a threat in some areas of the country (e.g., parts of Jutland, along the southern coast of the island of Lolland) that are protected from the sea by a system of dikes",
		"Environment - current issues": "air pollution, principally from vehicle and power plant emissions; nitrogen and phosphorus pollution of the North Sea; drinking and surface water becoming polluted from animal wastes and pesticides",
		"Environment - international agreements": {
			"party to:": "Air Pollution, Air Pollution-Nitrogen Oxides, Air Pollution-Persistent Organic Pollutants, Air Pollution-Sulfur 85, Air Pollution-Sulfur 94, Air Pollution-Volatile Organic Compounds, Antarctic Treaty, Biodiversity, Climate Change, Climate Change-Kyoto Protocol, Desertification, Endangered Species, Environmental Modification, Hazardous Wastes, Law of the Sea, Marine Dumping, Marine Life Conservation, Ozone Layer Protection, Ship Pollution, Tropical Timber 83, Tropical Timber 94, Wetlands, Whaling",
			"signed, but not ratified:": "none of the selected agreements"
		},
		"Geography - note": "controls Danish Straits (Skagerrak and Kattegat) linking Baltic and North Seas; about one-quarter of the population lives in greater Copenhagen"

		-->
	</geo>
	<people>
		<population>
			<total>48754</total>
			<birth unit="births/1,000 population">8.55</birth>
			<death unit="deaths/1,000 population">6.26</birth>
			<migration unit="migrant(s)/1,000 population">0</migration>
			<growth unit="%">0.23</growth>
		</population>
		<age-distribution unit="percent">
			<group min="0" max="14">15.7</group>
			<group min="15" max="64">72.9</group>
			<group min="65"></group>
		</age-distribution>
		<median-age unit="years">
			<total>38.4</total>
			<male>37</male>
			<female>39.8</female>
		</median-age>
		<urbanization>
			<urban unit="% of total population">83</urban>
			<rate unit="% annual rate of change">0.6</urban>
			<cities>SEOUL (capital) 9.778 million; Busan (Pusan) 3.439 million; Incheon (Inch'on) 2.572 million; Daegu (Taegu) 2.458 million; Daejon (Taejon) 1.497 million (2009)</cities>
		</urbanization>
		<sex unit="male(s)/female">
			<group name="at birth" max="0">1.069</group>
			<group name="0 to 14" min="0" max="14">1.1</group>
			<group name="15 to 64" min="15" max="64">1.04</group>
			<group name="65 and over" min="65" max="0">0.67</group>
			<group name="total" min="0">1</group>
		</sex>
		<infant-mortality>
			<total unit="deaths/1,000 live births">4.16</total>
			<male unit="deaths/1,000 live births">4.37</male>
			<female unit="deaths/1,000 live births">3.93</female>
		</infant-mortality>
		<life-expectancy-at-birth>
			<total unit="years">79.05</total>
			<male unit="years">75.84</male>
			<female unit="years">82.49</female>
		</life-expectancy-at-birth>
		<fertility-rate unit="1.23">children born/woman</fertility-rate>
		<hiv>
			<prevalence>less than 0.1% (2009 est.)</prevalence>
			<total>9500</total>
			<deaths>fewer than 500 (2009 est.)</deaths>
		</hiv>
		<infectious-disease risk="">
			<food-or-waterborne></food-or-waterborne>
			<vectorborne></vectorborne>
			<water-contact></water-contact>
		</infectious-disease>
		<drinking-water-source>[object Object]</drinking-water-source>
		<sanitation-access>[object Object]</sanitation-access>
		<nationality>
			<noun>Korean(s)</noun>
			<adjective>Korean</adjective>
		</nationality>
		<ethnic-groups>homogeneous (except for about 20,000 Chinese)</ethnic-groups>
		<religions>Christian 26.3% (Protestant 19.7%, Roman Catholic 6.6%), Buddhist 23.2%, other or unknown 1.3%, none 49.3% (1995 census)</religions>
		<languages>Korean, English (widely taught in junior high and high school)</languages>
		<literacy>
			<definition>age 15 and over can read and write</definition>
			<total unit="%">97.9</total>
			<male unit="%">99.2</male>
			<female unit="%">96.6</female>
		</literacy>
		<school-expectancy unit="years">17</school-expectancy>
		<education-expenditure unit="% of GDP">4.2</school-expectancy>
	</people>
	<government>
		<country-name>
			<long>Republic of Korea</long>
			<short>South Korea</short>
		</country-name>
		<dependency></dependency>
		<government-type>republic</government-type>
		<capital>
			<name>Seoul</name>
			<coordinates>37° 33' N, 126° 59' E</coordinates>
			<time-difference>UTC+9 (14 hours ahead of Washington, DC during Standard Time)</time-difference>
		</capital>
		<administrative-divisions>[object Object]</administrative-divisions>
		<independence>15 August 1945 (from Japan)</independence>
		<national-holiday>Liberation Day, 15 August (1945)</national-holiday>
		<legal-system>mixed legal system combining European civil law, Anglo-American law, and Chinese classical thought</legal-system>
		<suffrage>19 years of age; universal</suffrage>
		<executive>
			<head-of-state>President LEE Myung-bak (since 25 February 2008)</head-of-state>
			<head-of-government>Prime Minister KIM Hwang-sik (since 1 October 2010)</head-of-government>
			<cabinet>State Council appointed by the president on the prime minister's recommendation</cabinet>
			<elections>president elected by popular vote for a single five-year term; election last held on 19 December 2007 (next to be held in December 2012); prime minister appointed by president with consent of National Assembly</elections>
			<election-results>LEE Myung-bak elected president on 19 December 2007; percent of vote - LEE Myung-bak (GNP) 48.7%; CHUNG Dong-young (UNDP) 26.1%); LEE Hoi-chang (independent) 15.1; others 10.1%</election-results>
		</executive>
		<legislative>
			<description>unicameral National Assembly or Kukhoe (299 seats; 245 members elected in single-seat constituencies, 54 elected by proportional representation; members serve four-year terms)</description>
			<elections>last held on 9 April 2008 (next to be held in April 2012)</elections>
			<election-results>percent of vote by party - NA; seats by party - GNP 172, UDP 83, LFP 20, PPA 8, DLP 5, RKP 1, independents 9</election-results>
		</legislative>
		<judicial>Supreme Court (justices appointed by the president with consent of National Assembly); Constitutional Court (justices appointed by the president based partly on nominations by National Assembly and Chief Justice of the court)</judicial>
		<parties>Democratic Party or DP [CHUNG Sye-kyun] (formerly the United Democratic Party or UDP); Democratic Labor Party or DLP [KANG Ki-kap]; Grand National Party or GNP [AHN Sang-soo]; Liberty Forward Party or LFP [LEE Hoi-chang]; New Progressive Party or NPP [ROH Hoe-chan]; Pro-Park Alliance or PPA [SUH Choung-won]; Renewal Korea Party or RKP [SONG Yong-o]</parties>
		<pressure-groups>TO DO</pressure-groups>
		<membership>ADB, AfDB (nonregional member), APEC, ARF, ASEAN (dialogue partner), Australia Group, BIS, CD, CICA, CP, EAS, EBRD, FAO, FATF, G-20, IADB, IAEA, IBRD, ICAO, ICC, ICRM, IDA, IEA, IFAD, IFC, IFRCS, IHO, ILO, IMF, IMO, IMSO, Interpol, IOC, IOM, IPU, ISO, ITSO, ITU, ITUC, LAIA (observer), MIGA, MINURSO, NEA, NSG, OAS (observer), OECD, OPCW, OSCE (partner), Paris Club (associate), PCA, PIF (partner), SAARC (observer), UN, UNAMID, UNCTAD, UNESCO, UNHCR, UNIDO, UNIFIL, UNMIL, UNMOGIP, UNOCI, UNWTO, UPU, WCO, WHO, WIPO, WMO, WTO, ZC</membership>
		<representation-in-usa>
			<chief>Ambassador HAN Duck-soo</chief>
			<chancery>2450 Massachusetts Avenue NW, Washington, DC 20008</chancery>
			<telephone>[1] (202) 939-5600</telephone>
			<FAX>[1] (202) 387-0205</FAX>
			<consulates>Agana (Guam), Atlanta, Boston, Chicago, Honolulu, Houston, Los Angeles, New York, San Francisco, Seattle</consulates>
		</representation-in-usa>
		<representation-from-usa>
			<chief>Ambassador Kathleen STEPHENS</chief>
			<embassy>32 Sejongno, Jongno-gu, Seoul 110-710</embassy>
			<mailing-address>US Embassy Seoul, APO AP 96205-5550</mailing-address>
			<telephone>[82] (2) 397-4114</telephone>
			<FAX>[82] (2) 738-8845</FAX>
		</representation-from-usa>
		<flag>white with a red (top) and blue yin-yang symbol in the center; there is a different black trigram from the ancient I Ching (Book of Changes) in each corner of the white field; the Korean national flag is called Taegukki; white is a traditional Korean color and represents peace and purity; the blue section represents the negative cosmic forces of the yin, while the red symbolizes the opposite positive forces of the yang; each trigram (kwae) denotes one of the four universal elements, which together express the principle of movement and harmony</flag>
		<anthem>
			<name>&quot;Aegukga&quot; (Patriotic Song)</name>
			<by>YUN Ch'i-Ho or AN Ch'ang-Ho/AHN Eaktay</by>
		</anthem>
	</government>
	<economy>
		<overview>Since the 1960s, South Korea has achieved an incredible record of growth and global integration to become a high-tech industrialized economy. Four decades ago, GDP per capita was comparable with levels in the poorer countries of Africa and Asia. In 2004, South Korea joined the trillion dollar club of world economies, and currently is among the world's 20 largest economies. Initially, a system of close government and business ties, including directed credit and import restrictions, made this success possible. The government promoted the import of raw materials and technology at the expense of consumer goods, and encouraged savings and investment over consumption. The Asian financial crisis of 1997-98 exposed longstanding weaknesses in South Korea's development model including high debt/equity ratios and massive short-term foreign borrowing. GDP plunged by 6.9% in 1998, and then recovered by 9% in 1999-2000. Korea adopted numerous economic reforms following the crisis, including greater openness to foreign investment and imports. Growth moderated to about 4-5% annually between 2003 and 2007. With the global economic downturn in late 2008, South Korean GDP growth slowed to 0.2% in 2009. In the third quarter of 2009, the economy began to recover, in large part due to export growth, low interest rates, and an expansionary fiscal policy, and growth exceeded 6% in 2010. The South Korean economy's long term challenges include a rapidly aging population, inflexible labor market, and overdependence on manufacturing exports to drive economic growth.</overview>
		<gdp>
			<purchasing-power-parity></purchasing-power-parity>
			<official-exchange-rate>1006999999999.9999</official-exchange-rate>
			<real-growth-rate unit="%">6.1</real-growth-rate>
			<per-capita></per-capita>
			<sector unit="%">
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
		</gdp>
		<labour>
			<force>24620000</force>
			<sector>
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
			<unemployment unit="%">3.3</unemployment>
		</labour>
		<poverty>[object Object]</poverty>
		<household-income>TO DO</household-income>
		<budget>
			<revenue unit="USD"></revenue>
			<expenditure unit="USD"></expenditure>
		</budget>
		<public-debt unit="% of GDP">23.7</public-debt>
		<consumer-inflation unit="%">3</consumer-inflation>
		<central-bank-discount-rate unit="%">1.25</central-bank-discount-rate>
		<commercial-prime-lending-rate unit="%">5.65</commercial-prime-lending-rate>
		<narrow-money-stock unit="USD">101900000000</narrow-money-stock>
		<broad-money-stock unit="USD">1346000000000</broad-money-stock>
		<domestic-credit-stock unit="USD">1057000000000</domestic-credit-stock>
		<agriculture-products>rice, root crops, barley, vegetables, fruit; cattle, pigs, chickens, milk, eggs; fish</agriculture-products>
		<industries>electronics, telecommunications, automobile production, chemicals, shipbuilding, steel</industries>
		<industrial-production-growth>[object Object]</industrial-production-growth>
		<electricity unit="kWh">
			<production>417000000000</production>
			<consumption>402000000000</consumption>
			<exports>0</exports>
			<imports>0</imports>
		</electricity>
		<oil>
			<production unit="bbl/day">48180</production>
			<consumption unit="bbl/day">2185000</consumption>
			<exports unit=""></exports>
			<imports unit="bbl/day">3074000</imports>
			<reserves unit="bbl">0</reserves>
		</oil>
		<natural-gas>
			<production unit="cu m">651000000</production>
			<consumption unit="cu m">34090000000.000004</consumption>
			<exports unit="cu m">0</exports>
			<imports unit="cu m">32689999999.999996</imports>
			<reserves unit="cu m">50000000000</reserves>
		</natural-gas>
		<exports>
			<total unit="USD"></total>
			<commodities>semiconductors, wireless telecommunications equipment, motor vehicles, computers, steel, ships, petrochemicals</commodities>
			<partners>China 23.2%, US 10.1%, Japan 5.8%, Hong Kong 5.3% (2009 est.)</partners>
		</exports>
		<imports>
			<total unit="USD">417900000000</total>
			<commodities>machinery, electronics and electronic equipment, oil, steel, transport equipment, organic chemicals, plastics</commodities>
			<partners>China 16.8%, Japan 15.3%, US 9%, Saudi Arabia 6.1%, Australia 4.6% (2009 est.)</partners>
		</imports>
		<external-debt unit="USD">370100000000</external-debt>
		<exchange-rates>South Korean won (KRW) per US dollar -</exchange-rates>
	</economy>
	<communications>
		<telephones>
			<assessment>excellent domestic and international services featuring rapid incorporation of new technologies</assessment>
			<domestic>fixed-line and mobile-cellular services widely available with a combined telephone subscribership of roughly 140 per 100 persons; rapid assimilation of a full range of telecommunications technologies leading to a boom in e-commerce</domestic>
			<international>country code - 82; numerous submarine cables provide links throughout Asia, Australia, the Middle East, Europe, and US; satellite earth stations - 66</international>
			<land-lines>19289000</land-lines>
			<mobile>47944000</mobile>
		</telephones>
		<broadcast>multiple national television networks with 2 of the 3 largest networks publicly operated; the largest privately-owned network, Seoul Broadcasting Service (SBS), has ties with other commercial TV networks; cable and satellite TV subscription services are available; publicly-operated radio broadcast networks and a large number of privately-owned radio broadcasting networks, each with multiple affiliates, and independent local stations (2010)</broadcast>
		<internet>
			<tld>.kr</tld>
			<hosts>291329</hosts>
			<users>39400000</users>
		</internet>
	</communications>
	<transport>
		<airports>
			<total>116</total>
			<paved>
				<altitude min="*" max="*"></altitude>
				<altitude min="3047m" max="*">4</altitude>
				<altitude min="2438m" max="3047m">21</altitude>
				<altitude min="1524m" max="2437m">13</altitude>
				<altitude min="914m" max="1524m">12</altitude>
				<altitude min="*" max="914m"></altitude>
			</paved>
		</airports>
		<ports-and-terminals>Incheon (Inch'on), Pohang (P'ohang), Busan (Pusan), Ulsan, Yeosu (Yosu)</ports-and-terminals>
	</transport>
	<military>
		<branches>Republic of Korea Army, Navy (includes Marine Corps), Air Force (2011)</branches>
		<manpower>
			<population-available>
				<male>13185</male>
				<female>12423</female>
			</population-available>
			<fit-for-service>
				<male>10864</male>
				<female>10168</female>
			</fit-for-service>
			<reaching-maturity>
				<male>365760</male>
				<female>321225</female>
			</reaching-maturity>
			<notes></notes>
		</manpower>
	</military>
	<issues>
		<disputes>Military Demarcation Line within the 4-km wide Demilitarized Zone has separated North from South Korea since 1953; periodic incidents with North Korea in the Yellow Sea over the Northern Limit Line, which South Korea claims as a maritime boundary; South Korea and Japan claim Liancourt Rocks (Tok-do/Take-shima), occupied by South Korea since 1954</disputes>
		<drugs></drugs>
	</issues>
</country>