<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<country>
	<code>lo</code>
	<name>Slovakia</name>
	<region>Europe</region>
	<background>Slovakia's roots can be traced to the 9th century state of Great Moravia. Subsequently, the Slovaks became part of the Hungarian Kingdom, where they remained for the next 1,000 years. Following the formation of the dual Austro-Hungarian monarchy in 1867, language and education policies favoring the use of Hungarian (Magyarization) resulted in a strengthening of Slovak nationalism and a cultivation of cultural ties with the closely related Czechs, who were themselves ruled by the Austrians. After the dissolution of the Austro-Hungarian Empire at the close of World War I, the Slovaks joined the Czechs to form Czechoslovakia. Following the chaos of World War II, Czechoslovakia became a Communist nation within Soviet-dominated Eastern Europe. Soviet influence collapsed in 1989 and Czechoslovakia once more became free. The Slovaks and the Czechs agreed to separate peacefully on 1 January 1993. Slovakia joined both NATO and the EU in the spring of 2004 and the euro area on 1 January 2009.</background>
	<geo>
		<note>landlocked; most of the country is rugged and mountainous; the Tatra Mountains in the north are interspersed with many scenic lakes and valleys</note>
		<location>
			<desc>Central Europe, south of Poland</desc>
			<coordinates>TO DO</coordinates>
		</location>
		<area>
			<total unit="sq km">49035</total>
			<land unit="sq km">48105</land>
			<water unit="sq km">930</water>
			<comparison>about twice the size of New Hampshire</comparison>
		</area>
		<boundaries>
			<borders unit=""></borders>
			<coastline unit="km">0</coastline>
		</boundaries>
		<maritime-claims>
			<territorial unit=""></territorial>
			<contiguous unit=""></contiguous>
			<economic unit=""></economic>
			<continental-shelf></continental-shelf>
		</maritime-claims>
		<climate>temperate; cool summers; cold, cloudy, humid winters</climate>
		<terrain>rugged mountains in the central and northern part and lowlands in the south</terrain>
		<elevation>
			<high>Gerlachovsky Stit 2,655 m</high>
			<low>Bodrok River 94 m</low>
		</elevation>
		<resources>brown coal and lignite; small amounts of iron ore, copper and manganese ore; salt; arable land</resources>
		<land-use>
			<arable unit="%">29.23</arable>
			<crops unit="%">2.67</crops>
			<other unit="%">68.1</other>
		</land-use>
		<hazards>NA</hazards>
		<issues>air pollution from metallurgical plants presents human health risks; acid rain damaging forests</issues>
		<water>
			<irrigated-land unit="sq km">1660</irrigated-land>
			<renewable-water unit="cu km">50.1</renewable-water>
			<freshwater-withdrawal>
				<total unit=""></total>
				<per-capita unit="cu m/yr">193</per-capita>
			</freshwater-withdrawal>
		</water>
		<!--
"geo": {

		"Natural hazards": "flooding is a threat in some areas of the country (e.g., parts of Jutland, along the southern coast of the island of Lolland) that are protected from the sea by a system of dikes",
		"Environment - current issues": "air pollution, principally from vehicle and power plant emissions; nitrogen and phosphorus pollution of the North Sea; drinking and surface water becoming polluted from animal wastes and pesticides",
		"Environment - international agreements": {
			"party to:": "Air Pollution, Air Pollution-Nitrogen Oxides, Air Pollution-Persistent Organic Pollutants, Air Pollution-Sulfur 85, Air Pollution-Sulfur 94, Air Pollution-Volatile Organic Compounds, Antarctic Treaty, Biodiversity, Climate Change, Climate Change-Kyoto Protocol, Desertification, Endangered Species, Environmental Modification, Hazardous Wastes, Law of the Sea, Marine Dumping, Marine Life Conservation, Ozone Layer Protection, Ship Pollution, Tropical Timber 83, Tropical Timber 94, Wetlands, Whaling",
			"signed, but not ratified:": "none of the selected agreements"
		},
		"Geography - note": "controls Danish Straits (Skagerrak and Kattegat) linking Baltic and North Seas; about one-quarter of the population lives in greater Copenhagen"

		-->
	</geo>
	<people>
		<population>
			<total>5477</total>
			<birth unit="births/1,000 population">10.48</birth>
			<death unit="deaths/1,000 population">9.6</birth>
			<migration unit="migrant(s)/1,000 population">0.29</migration>
			<growth unit="%">0.117</growth>
		</population>
		<age-distribution unit="percent">
			<group min="0" max="14">15.6</group>
			<group min="15" max="64">71.6</group>
			<group min="65"></group>
		</age-distribution>
		<median-age unit="years">
			<total>37.6</total>
			<male>36.1</male>
			<female>39.2</female>
		</median-age>
		<urbanization>
			<urban unit="% of total population">55</urban>
			<rate unit="% annual rate of change">0.1</urban>
			<cities>BRATISLAVA (capital) 428,000 (2009)</cities>
		</urbanization>
		<sex unit="male(s)/female">
			<group name="at birth" max="0">1.051</group>
			<group name="0 to 14" min="0" max="14">1.05</group>
			<group name="15 to 64" min="15" max="64">0.99</group>
			<group name="65 and over" min="65" max="0">0.6</group>
			<group name="total" min="0">0.94</group>
		</sex>
		<infant-mortality>
			<total unit="deaths/1,000 live births">6.59</total>
			<male unit="deaths/1,000 live births">7.69</male>
			<female unit="deaths/1,000 live births">5.43</female>
		</infant-mortality>
		<life-expectancy-at-birth>
			<total unit="years">75.83</total>
			<male unit="years">71.92</male>
			<female unit="years">79.93</female>
		</life-expectancy-at-birth>
		<fertility-rate unit="1.37">children born/woman</fertility-rate>
		<hiv>
			<prevalence>less than 0.1% (2009 est.)</prevalence>
			<total>fewer than 500 (2009 est.)</total>
			<deaths>fewer than 100 (2009 est.)</deaths>
		</hiv>
		<infectious-disease risk="">
			<food-or-waterborne></food-or-waterborne>
			<vectorborne></vectorborne>
			<water-contact></water-contact>
		</infectious-disease>
		<drinking-water-source>[object Object]</drinking-water-source>
		<sanitation-access>[object Object]</sanitation-access>
		<nationality>
			<noun>Slovak(s)</noun>
			<adjective>Slovak</adjective>
		</nationality>
		<ethnic-groups>Slovak 85.8%, Hungarian 9.7%, Roma 1.7%, Ruthenian/Ukrainian 1%, other and unspecified 1.8% (2001 census)</ethnic-groups>
		<religions>Roman Catholic 68.9%, Protestant 10.8%, Greek Catholic 4.1%, other or unspecified 3.2%, none 13% (2001 census)</religions>
		<languages>Slovak (official) 83.9%, Hungarian 10.7%, Roma 1.8%, Ukrainian 1%, other or unspecified 2.6% (2001 census)</languages>
		<literacy>
			<definition>age 15 and over can read and write</definition>
			<total unit="%">99.6</total>
			<male unit="%">99.7</male>
			<female unit="%">99.6</female>
		</literacy>
		<school-expectancy unit="years">15</school-expectancy>
		<education-expenditure unit="% of GDP">3.6</school-expectancy>
	</people>
	<government>
		<country-name>
			<long>Slovak Republic</long>
			<short>Slovakia</short>
		</country-name>
		<dependency></dependency>
		<government-type>parliamentary democracy</government-type>
		<capital>
			<name>Bratislava</name>
			<coordinates>48° 9' N, 17° 7' E</coordinates>
			<time-difference>UTC+1 (6 hours ahead of Washington, DC during Standard Time)</time-difference>
		</capital>
		<administrative-divisions>8 regions (kraje, singular - kraj); Banskobystricky, Bratislavsky, Kosicky, Nitriansky, Presovsky, Trenciansky, Trnavsky, Zilinsky</administrative-divisions>
		<independence>1 January 1993 (Czechoslovakia split into the Czech Republic and Slovakia)</independence>
		<national-holiday>Constitution Day, 1 September (1992)</national-holiday>
		<legal-system>civil law system based on Austro-Hungarian codes; note - legal code modified to comply with the obligations of Organization on Security and Cooperation in Europe and to expunge Marxist-Leninist legal system</legal-system>
		<suffrage>18 years of age; universal</suffrage>
		<executive>
			<head-of-state>President Ivan GASPAROVIC (since 15 June 2004)</head-of-state>
			<head-of-government>Prime Minister Iveta RADICOVA (since 8 July 2010); Deputy Prime Ministers Jan FIGEL, Ivan MIKLOS, Jozef MIHAL, Rudolf CHMEL (since 9 July 2010)</head-of-government>
			<cabinet>Cabinet appointed by the president on the recommendation of the prime minister</cabinet>
			<elections>president elected by popular vote for a five-year term (eligible for a second term); election last held on 21 March and 4 April 2009 (next to be held no later than April 2014); following National Council elections, the leader of the majority party or the leader of a majority coalition usually appointed prime minister by the president</elections>
			<election-results>Ivan GASPAROVIC reelected president in runoff; percent of vote - Ivan GASPAROVIC 55.5%, Iveta RADICOVA 44.5%</election-results>
		</executive>
		<legislative>
			<description>unicameral National Council of the Slovak Republic or Narodna Rada Slovenskej Republiky (150 seats; members elected on the basis of proportional representation to serve four-year terms)</description>
			<elections>last held on 12 June 2010 (next to be held in June 2014)</elections>
			<election-results>percent of vote by party - Smer 34.8%, SDKU-DS 15%, SaS 12.1%, KDH 8.5%, Most-Hid 8.1%, SNS 5.1%, other 16.2%; seats by party - Smer 62, SDKU-DS 28, SaS 22, KDH 15, Most-Hid 14, SNS 9</election-results>
		</legislative>
		<judicial>Supreme Court (judges are elected by the National Council); Constitutional Court (judges appointed by president from group of nominees approved by the National Council); Special Court (judges elected by a council of judges and appointed by president)</judicial>
		<parties>[object Object]</parties>
		<pressure-groups>TO DO</pressure-groups>
		<membership>Australia Group, BIS, BSEC (observer), CBSS (observer), CE, CEI, CERN, EAPC, EBRD, EIB, EMU, EU, FAO, IAEA, IBRD, ICAO, ICC, ICRM, IDA, IEA, IFC, IFRCS, ILO, IMF, IMO, IMSO, Interpol, IOC, IOM, IPU, ISO, ITU, ITUC, MIGA, NATO, NEA, NSG, OAS (observer), OECD, OIF (observer), OPCW, OSCE, PCA, Schengen Convention, SECI (observer), UN, UNCTAD, UNESCO, UNFICYP, UNIDO, UNTSO, UNWTO, UPU, WCO, WFTU, WHO, WIPO, WMO, WTO, ZC</membership>
		<representation-in-usa>
			<chief>Ambassador Peter BURIAN</chief>
			<chancery>3523 International Court NW, Washington, DC 20008</chancery>
			<telephone>[1] (202) 237-1054</telephone>
			<FAX>[1] (202) 237-6438</FAX>
			<consulates>Los Angeles, New York</consulates>
		</representation-in-usa>
		<representation-from-usa>
			<chief>Ambassador Theodore SEDGWICK</chief>
			<embassy>Hviezdoslavovo Namestie 4, 81102 Bratislava</embassy>
			<mailing-address>P.O. Box 309, 814 99 Bratislava</mailing-address>
			<telephone>[421] (2) 5443-3338</telephone>
			<FAX>[421] (2) 5441-8861</FAX>
		</representation-from-usa>
		<flag>[object Object]</flag>
		<anthem>
			<name>&quot;Nad Tatrou sa blyska&quot; (Storm Over the Tatras)</name>
			<by>Janko MATUSKA/traditional</by>
		</anthem>
	</government>
	<economy>
		<overview>Slovakia has made significant economic reforms since its separation from the Czech Republic in 1993. Reforms to the taxation, healthcare, pension, and social welfare systems helped Slovakia consolidate its budget and get on track to join the EU in 2004 and to adopt the euro in January 2009. Major privatizations are nearly complete, the banking sector is almost entirely in foreign hands, and the government has helped facilitate a foreign investment boom with business friendly policies. Slovakia's economic growth exceeded expectations in 2001-08 despite a general European slowdown. Unemployment, at an unacceptable 18% in 2003-04, dropped to 7.7% in 2008 but remains the economy's Achilles heel. Foreign direct investment (FDI) accounted for much of the growth until 2008. Cheap and skilled labor, low taxes, a 19% flat tax for corporations and individuals, no dividend taxes, a relatively liberal labor code and a favorable geographical location are Slovakia's main advantages for foreign investors. Foreign investment in the automotive and electronic sectors has been especially strong. To maintain a stable operating environment for investors, the European Bank for Reconstruction and Development advised the Slovak government to refrain from intervening in important sectors of the economy. However, Bratislava's approach to mitigating the economic slowdown has included substantial government intervention and the option to nationalize strategic companies. RADICOVA's government, in power since July 2010, has allowed the budget deficit to rise slightly, to 7.4% of GDP in 2010. GDP fell nearly 5% in 2009 before gaining back 4% in 2010, and unemployment rose above 12% in 2010, as the global recession impacted many segments of the economy.</overview>
		<gdp>
			<purchasing-power-parity></purchasing-power-parity>
			<official-exchange-rate>87450000000</official-exchange-rate>
			<real-growth-rate unit="%">4</real-growth-rate>
			<per-capita></per-capita>
			<sector unit="%">
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
		</gdp>
		<labour>
			<force>2673000</force>
			<sector>
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
			<unemployment unit="%">13.5</unemployment>
		</labour>
		<poverty>[object Object]</poverty>
		<household-income>TO DO</household-income>
		<budget>
			<revenue unit="USD"></revenue>
			<expenditure unit="USD"></expenditure>
		</budget>
		<public-debt unit="% of GDP">41</public-debt>
		<consumer-inflation unit="%">1</consumer-inflation>
		<central-bank-discount-rate unit="%"></central-bank-discount-rate>
		<commercial-prime-lending-rate unit="%"></commercial-prime-lending-rate>
		<narrow-money-stock unit="USD"></narrow-money-stock>
		<broad-money-stock unit="USD">52630000000</broad-money-stock>
		<domestic-credit-stock unit="USD">65090000000</domestic-credit-stock>
		<agriculture-products>grains, potatoes, sugar beets, hops, fruit; pigs, cattle, poultry; forest products</agriculture-products>
		<industries>metal and metal products; food and beverages; electricity, gas, coke, oil, nuclear fuel; chemicals and manmade fibers; machinery; paper and printing; earthenware and ceramics; transport vehicles; textiles; electrical and optical apparatus; rubber products</industries>
		<industrial-production-growth>[object Object]</industrial-production-growth>
		<electricity unit="kWh">
			<production>25900000000</production>
			<consumption>28750000000</consumption>
			<exports>8891000000</exports>
			<imports>9412000000</imports>
		</electricity>
		<oil>
			<production unit="bbl/day">4114</production>
			<consumption unit="bbl/day">79930</consumption>
			<exports unit="bbl/day">75110</exports>
			<imports unit="bbl/day">144000</imports>
			<reserves unit="bbl">9000000</reserves>
		</oil>
		<natural-gas>
			<production unit="cu m">103000000</production>
			<consumption unit="cu m">6493000000</consumption>
			<exports unit="cu m">15000000</exports>
			<imports unit="cu m">6974000000</imports>
			<reserves unit="cu m">14160000000</reserves>
		</natural-gas>
		<exports>
			<total unit="USD"></total>
			<commodities>machinery and electrical equipment 35.9%, vehicles 21%, base metals 11.3%, chemicals and minerals 8.1%, plastics 4.9% (2009 est.)</commodities>
			<partners>Germany 20.1%, Czech Republic 12.9%, France 7.8%, Poland 7.2%, Hungary 6.3%, Italy 6.1%, Austria 5.8%, UK 4.8% (2009 est.)</partners>
		</exports>
		<imports>
			<total unit="USD">62430000000</total>
			<commodities>machinery and transport equipment 31%, mineral products 13%, vehicles 12%, base metals 9%, chemicals 8%, plastics 6% (2009 est.)</commodities>
			<partners>Germany 16.8%, Czech Republic 12.3%, Russia 9%, South Korea 6.8%, China 5.8%, Hungary 5.3%, Poland 4% (2009 est.)</partners>
		</imports>
		<external-debt unit="USD">59330000000</external-debt>
		<exchange-rates>Slovak koruny (SKK) per US dollar -</exchange-rates>
	</economy>
	<communications>
		<telephones>
			<assessment>Slovakia has a modern telecommunications system that has expanded dramatically in recent years with the growth in cellular services</assessment>
			<domestic>analog system is now receiving digital equipment and is being enlarged with fiber-optic cable, especially in the larger cities; 3 companies provide nationwide cellular services</domestic>
			<international>country code - 421; 3 international exchanges (1 in Bratislava and 2 in Banska Bystrica) are available; Slovakia is participating in several international telecommunications projects that will increase the availability of external services</international>
			<land-lines>1022000</land-lines>
			<mobile>5498000</mobile>
		</telephones>
		<broadcast>state-owned public broadcaster, Slovak Television (STV), operates 3 national TV stations; roughly 35 privately-owned television broadcast stations operating nationally, regionally, and locally; about 40% of households are connected to multi-channel cable or satellite TV systems; channels from the Czech Republic and Hungary are widely viewed; state-owned public radio operates multiple national and regional networks; more than 20 privately-owned radio stations (2008)</broadcast>
		<internet>
			<tld>.sk</tld>
			<hosts>1133000</hosts>
			<users>4062999.9999999995</users>
		</internet>
	</communications>
	<transport>
		<airports>
			<total>36</total>
			<paved>
				<altitude min="*" max="*"></altitude>
				<altitude min="3047m" max="*">1</altitude>
				<altitude min="2438m" max="3047m">3</altitude>
				<altitude min="1524m" max="2437m">3</altitude>
				<altitude min="914m" max="1524m">3</altitude>
				<altitude min="*" max="914m"></altitude>
			</paved>
		</airports>
		<ports-and-terminals>Bratislava, Komarno</ports-and-terminals>
	</transport>
	<military>
		<branches>Armed Forces of the Slovak Republic (Ozbrojene Sily Slovenskej Republiky): Land Forces (Pozemne Sily), Air Forces (Vzdusne Sily) (2010)</branches>
		<manpower>
			<population-available>
				<male>1405</male>
				<female>1369</female>
			</population-available>
			<fit-for-service>
				<male>1156</male>
				<female>1139</female>
			</fit-for-service>
			<reaching-maturity>
				<male>31646</male>
				<female>30219</female>
			</reaching-maturity>
			<notes></notes>
		</manpower>
	</military>
	<issues>
		<disputes>bilateral government, legal, technical and economic working group negotiations continued in 2006 between Slovakia and Hungary over Hungary's completion of its portion of the Gabcikovo-Nagymaros hydroelectric dam project along the Danube; as a member state that forms part of the EU's external border, Slovakia has implemented the strict Schengen border rules</disputes>
		<drugs>transshipment point for Southwest Asian heroin bound for Western Europe; producer of synthetic drugs for regional market; consumer of ecstasy</drugs>
	</issues>
</country>