<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<country>
	<code>mo</code>
	<name>Morocco</name>
	<region>Africa</region>
	<background>In 788, about a century after the Arab conquest of North Africa, successive Moorish dynasties began to rule in Morocco. In the 16th century, the Sa'adi monarchy, particularly under Ahmad AL-MANSUR (1578-1603), repelled foreign invaders and inaugurated a golden age. The Alaouite dynasty, to which the current Moroccan royal family belongs, established a sultanate in Morocco beginning in the 17th century. In 1860, Spain occupied northern Morocco and ushered in a half century of trade rivalry among European powers that saw Morocco's sovereignty steadily erode; in 1912, the French imposed a protectorate over the country. A protracted independence struggle with France ended successfully in 1956. The internationalized city of Tangier and most Spanish possessions were turned over to the new country that same year. Sultan MOHAMMED V, the current monarch's grandfather, organized the new state as a constitutional monarchy and in 1957 assumed the title of king. Morocco annexed Western Sahara during the late 1970s, but final resolution on the status of the territory remains unresolved. Gradual political reforms in the 1990s resulted in the establishment of a bicameral legislature, which first met in 1997. Under King MOHAMMED VI - who in 1999 succeeded his father to the throne - human rights have improved. Morocco enjoys a moderately free press, but the government occasionally takes action against journalists who report on three broad subjects considered to be taboo: the monarchy, Islam, and the status of Western Sahara. Despite the continuing reforms, ultimate authority remains in the hands of the monarch. Influenced by protests elsewhere in the Middle East and North Africa, thousands of Moroccans in February 2011 rallied in Rabat and several other major cities to demand constitutional reform and more democracy and to protest government corruption and high food prices. A number of similar demonstrations and marches continued through March. Police response to most of the protests was subdued compared to the violence noted in protests elsewhere in the region. In early March, in response to demonstrator demands, King MOHAMMED VI announced the formation of a commission to reform the country's constitution. A draft constitution is to be presented by June 2011, followed by a popular referendum. 

</background>
	<geo>
		<note>strategic location along Strait of Gibraltar</note>
		<location>
			<desc>Northern Africa, bordering the North Atlantic Ocean and the Mediterranean Sea, between Algeria and Western Sahara</desc>
			<coordinates>TO DO</coordinates>
		</location>
		<area>
			<total unit="sq km">446550</total>
			<land unit="sq km">446300</land>
			<water unit="sq km">250</water>
			<comparison>slightly larger than California</comparison>
		</area>
		<boundaries>
			<borders unit=""></borders>
			<coastline unit="km">1835</coastline>
		</boundaries>
		<maritime-claims>
			<territorial unit="nm">12</territorial>
			<contiguous unit="nm">24</contiguous>
			<economic unit="nm">200</economic>
			<continental-shelf>200 m depth or to the depth of exploitation</continental-shelf>
		</maritime-claims>
		<climate>Mediterranean, becoming more extreme in the interior</climate>
		<terrain>northern coast and interior are mountainous with large areas of bordering plateaus, intermontane valleys, and rich coastal plains</terrain>
		<elevation>
			<high>Jebel Toubkal 4,165 m</high>
			<low>Sebkha Tah -55 m</low>
		</elevation>
		<resources>phosphates, iron ore, manganese, lead, zinc, fish, salt</resources>
		<land-use>
			<arable unit="%">19</arable>
			<crops unit="%">2</crops>
			<other unit="%">79</other>
		</land-use>
		<hazards>northern mountains geologically unstable and subject to earthquakes; periodic droughts</hazards>
		<issues>land degradation/desertification (soil erosion resulting from farming of marginal areas, overgrazing, destruction of vegetation); water supplies contaminated by raw sewage; siltation of reservoirs; oil pollution of coastal waters</issues>
		<water>
			<irrigated-land unit="sq km">14570</irrigated-land>
			<renewable-water unit="cu km">29</renewable-water>
			<freshwater-withdrawal>
				<total unit="cu km/yr">12.6</total>
				<per-capita unit="cu m/yr">400</per-capita>
			</freshwater-withdrawal>
		</water>
		<!--
"geo": {

		"Natural hazards": "flooding is a threat in some areas of the country (e.g., parts of Jutland, along the southern coast of the island of Lolland) that are protected from the sea by a system of dikes",
		"Environment - current issues": "air pollution, principally from vehicle and power plant emissions; nitrogen and phosphorus pollution of the North Sea; drinking and surface water becoming polluted from animal wastes and pesticides",
		"Environment - international agreements": {
			"party to:": "Air Pollution, Air Pollution-Nitrogen Oxides, Air Pollution-Persistent Organic Pollutants, Air Pollution-Sulfur 85, Air Pollution-Sulfur 94, Air Pollution-Volatile Organic Compounds, Antarctic Treaty, Biodiversity, Climate Change, Climate Change-Kyoto Protocol, Desertification, Endangered Species, Environmental Modification, Hazardous Wastes, Law of the Sea, Marine Dumping, Marine Life Conservation, Ozone Layer Protection, Ship Pollution, Tropical Timber 83, Tropical Timber 94, Wetlands, Whaling",
			"signed, but not ratified:": "none of the selected agreements"
		},
		"Geography - note": "controls Danish Straits (Skagerrak and Kattegat) linking Baltic and North Seas; about one-quarter of the population lives in greater Copenhagen"

		-->
	</geo>
	<people>
		<population>
			<total>31968</total>
			<birth unit="births/1,000 population">19.19</birth>
			<death unit="deaths/1,000 population">4.75</birth>
			<migration unit=""></migration>
			<growth unit="%">1.067</growth>
		</population>
		<age-distribution unit="percent">
			<group min="0" max="14">27.8</group>
			<group min="15" max="64">66.1</group>
			<group min="65"></group>
		</age-distribution>
		<median-age unit="years">
			<total>26.9</total>
			<male>26.3</male>
			<female>27.4</female>
		</median-age>
		<urbanization>
			<urban unit="% of total population">58</urban>
			<rate unit="% annual rate of change">2.1</urban>
			<cities>Casablanca 3.245 million; RABAT (capital) 1.77 million; Fes 1.044 million; Marrakech 909,000; Tangier 768,000 (2009)</cities>
		</urbanization>
		<sex unit="male(s)/female">
			<group name="at birth" max="0">1.05</group>
			<group name="0 to 14" min="0" max="14">1.03</group>
			<group name="15 to 64" min="15" max="64">0.96</group>
			<group name="65 and over" min="65" max="0">0.83</group>
			<group name="total" min="0">0.97</group>
		</sex>
		<infant-mortality>
			<total unit="deaths/1,000 live births">27.53</total>
			<male unit="deaths/1,000 live births">32.32</male>
			<female unit="deaths/1,000 live births">22.51</female>
		</infant-mortality>
		<life-expectancy-at-birth>
			<total unit="years">75.9</total>
			<male unit="years">72.84</male>
			<female unit="years">79.11</female>
		</life-expectancy-at-birth>
		<fertility-rate unit="2.21">children born/woman</fertility-rate>
		<hiv>
			<prevalence>[object Object]</prevalence>
			<total>26000</total>
			<deaths>1200</deaths>
		</hiv>
		<infectious-disease risk="">
			<food-or-waterborne></food-or-waterborne>
			<vectorborne></vectorborne>
			<water-contact></water-contact>
		</infectious-disease>
		<drinking-water-source>[object Object]</drinking-water-source>
		<sanitation-access>[object Object]</sanitation-access>
		<nationality>
			<noun>Moroccan(s)</noun>
			<adjective>Moroccan</adjective>
		</nationality>
		<ethnic-groups>Arab-Berber 99.1%, other 0.7%, Jewish 0.2%</ethnic-groups>
		<religions>Muslim 98.7%, Christian 1.1%, Jewish 0.2%</religions>
		<languages>Arabic (official), Berber dialects, French (often the language of business, government, and diplomacy)</languages>
		<literacy>
			<definition>age 15 and over can read and write</definition>
			<total unit="%">52.3</total>
			<male unit="%">65.7</male>
			<female unit="%">39.6</female>
		</literacy>
		<school-expectancy unit="years">10</school-expectancy>
		<education-expenditure unit="% of GDP">5.6</school-expectancy>
	</people>
	<government>
		<country-name>
			<long>Kingdom of Morocco</long>
			<short>Morocco</short>
		</country-name>
		<dependency></dependency>
		<government-type>constitutional monarchy</government-type>
		<capital>
			<name>Rabat</name>
			<coordinates>34° 1' N, 6° 49' W</coordinates>
			<time-difference>UTC 0 (5 hours ahead of Washington, DC during Standard Time)</time-difference>
		</capital>
		<administrative-divisions>[object Object]</administrative-divisions>
		<independence>2 March 1956 (from France)</independence>
		<national-holiday>Throne Day (accession of King MOHAMMED VI to the throne), 30 July (1999)</national-holiday>
		<legal-system>mixed legal system of civil law based on French law and Islamic law; judicial review of legislative acts by Supreme Court</legal-system>
		<suffrage>18 years of age; universal</suffrage>
		<executive>
			<head-of-state>King MOHAMMED VI (since 30 July 1999)</head-of-state>
			<head-of-government>Prime Minister Abbas EL FASSI (since 19 September 2007)</head-of-government>
			<cabinet>Council of Ministers appointed by the monarch</cabinet>
			<elections>the monarchy is hereditary; prime minister appointed by the monarch following legislative elections</elections>
			<election-results></election-results>
		</executive>
		<legislative>
			<description>bicameral Parliament consists of the Chamber of Counselors (or upper house) (270 seats; members elected indirectly by local councils, professional organizations, and labor syndicates to serve nine-year terms; one-third of the members are elected every three years) and Chamber of Representatives (or lower house) (325 seats; 295 members elected by multi-seat constituencies and 30 from national lists of women; members elected by popular vote to serve five-year terms)</description>
			<elections>Chamber of Counselors - last held on 3 October 2009 (next to be held in 2012); Chamber of Representatives - last held on 7 September 2007 (next to be held in 2012)</elections>
			<election-results>Chamber of Counselors - percent of vote by party - NA; seats by party - NA; Chamber of Representatives - percent of vote by party - NA; seats by party - PI 52, PJD 46, MP 41, RNI 39, USFP 38, UC 27, PPS 17, FFD 9, MDS 9, Al Ahd 8, other 39</election-results>
		</legislative>
		<judicial>Supreme Court (judges are appointed on the recommendation of the Supreme Council of the Judiciary, presided over by the monarch)</judicial>
		<parties>Action Party or PA [Mohammed EL IDRISSI]; Al Ahd (The Covenant) Party [Najib EL OUAZZANI]; Alliance des Libert'es (Alliance of Liberty) or ADL [Ali BELHAJ]; An-Nahj Ad-Dimocrati or An-Nahj [Abdellah EL HARIF]; Authenticity and Modernity Party or PAM [Mohamed Cheikh BIADILLAH, secretary general]; Choura et Istiqlal (Consultation and Independence) Party or PCI [Abdelwahed MAACH]; Citizens' Forces or FC [Abderrahman LAHJOUJI]; Citizenship and Development Initiative or ICD [Mohamed BENHAMOU]; Constitutional Union Party or UC [Mohammed ABIED]; Democratic and Social Movement or MDS [Mahmoud ARCHANE]; Democratic Forces Front or FFD [Touhami EL KHIARI]; Democratic Socialist Vanguard Party or PADS [Ahmed BENJELLOUN]; Democratic Society Party or PSD [Zhor CHEKKAFI]; Democratic Union or UD [Bouazza IKKEN]; Environment and Development Party or PED [Ahmed EL ALAMI]; Istiqlal (Independence) Party or PI [Abbas EL FASSI]; Justice and Development Party or PJD [Abdelilah BENKIRANE]; Labor Party or PT [Abdelkrim BENATIK]; Moroccan Liberal Party or PML [Mohamed ZIANE]; National Democratic Party or PND [Abdallah KADIRI]; National Ittihadi Congress Party or CNI [Abdelmajid BOUZOUBAA]; National Popular Movement or MNP [Mahjoubi AHERDANE]; National Rally of Independents or RNI [Mustapha EL MANSOURI]; National Union of Popular Forces or UNFP [Abdellah IBRAHIM]; Popular Movement or MP [Mohamed LAENSER]; Progress and Socialism Party or PPS [Ismail ALAOUI]; Reform and Development Party or PRD [Abderrahmane EL KOUHEN]; Renaissance and Virtue Party or PRV [Mohamed KHALIDI]; Renewal and Equity Party or PRE [Chakir ACHABAR]; Social Center Party or PSC [Lahcen MADIH]; Socialist Democratic Party or PSD [Aissa OUARDIGHI]; Socialist Union of Popular Forces or USFP [Abdelwahed RADI]; Unified Socialist Left Party or PGSU [Mohamed Ben Said AIT IDDER]</parties>
		<pressure-groups>TO DO</pressure-groups>
		<membership>ABEDA, AfDB, AFESD, AMF, AMU, CD, EBRD, FAO, G-11, G-77, IAEA, IBRD, ICAO, ICC, ICRM, IDA, IDB, IFAD, IFC, IFRCS, IHO, ILO, IMF, IMO, IMSO, Interpol, IOC, IOM, IPU, ISO, ITSO, ITU, ITUC, LAS, MIGA, MONUSCO, NAM, OAS (observer), OIC, OIF, OPCW, OSCE (partner), Paris Club (associate), PCA, UN, UNCTAD, UNESCO, UNHCR, UNIDO, UNMIS, UNOCI, UNWTO, UPU, WCO, WHO, WIPO, WMO, WTO</membership>
		<representation-in-usa>
			<chief>Ambassador Aziz MEKOUAR</chief>
			<chancery>1601 21st Street NW, Washington, DC 20009</chancery>
			<telephone>[1] (202) 462-7979</telephone>
			<FAX>[1] (202) 265-0161</FAX>
			<consulates>New York</consulates>
		</representation-in-usa>
		<representation-from-usa>
			<chief>Ambassador Samuel L. KAPLAN</chief>
			<embassy>2 Avenue de Mohamed El Fassi, Rabat</embassy>
			<mailing-address>PSC 74, Box 021, APO AE 09718</mailing-address>
			<telephone>[212] (37) 76 22 65</telephone>
			<FAX>[212] (37) 76 56 61</FAX>
		</representation-from-usa>
		<flag>red with a green pentacle (five-pointed, linear star) known as Sulayman's (Solomon's) seal in the center of the flag; red and green are traditional colors in Arab flags, although the use of red is more commonly associated with the Arab states of the Persian gulf; the pentacle represents the five pillars of Islam and signifies the association between God and the nation; design dates to 1912</flag>
		<anthem>
			<name>&quot;Hymne Cherifien&quot; (Hymn of the Sharif)</name>
			<by>Ali Squalli HOUSSAINI/Leo MORGAN</by>
		</anthem>
	</government>
	<economy>
		<overview>Morocco's market economy benefits from the country's relatively low labor costs and proximity to Europe, which aid key areas of the economy such as agriculture, light manufacturing, tourism, and remittances. Morocco is also the world's largest exporter of phosphate, which has long provided a source of export earnings and economic stability. Economic policies pursued since 2003 by King MOHAMMED VI have brought macroeconomic stability to the country with generally low inflation, improved financial performance, and steady progress in developing the service and industrial sectors. In 2006, Morocco entered a Free Trade Agreement (FTA) with the US, and in 2008 entered into an advanced status in its 2000 Association Agreement with the EU. However, poverty, illiteracy, and unemployment rates remain high. In response to these challenges, King MOHAMMED in 2005 launched a National Initiative for Human Development, a $2 billion program aimed at alleviating poverty and underdevelopment by expanding electricity to rural areas and replacing urban slums with public and subsidized housing, among other policies. Morocco's trade and budget deficits widened in 2010, and reducing government spending and adapting to sluggish economic growth in Europe will be challenges in 2011. Morocco's long-term challenges include improving education and job prospects for young Moroccans, closing the disparity in wealth between the rich and the poor, confronting corruption, and expanding and diversifying exports beyond phosphates and low-value-added products.</overview>
		<gdp>
			<purchasing-power-parity></purchasing-power-parity>
			<official-exchange-rate>103500000000</official-exchange-rate>
			<real-growth-rate unit="%">3.2</real-growth-rate>
			<per-capita></per-capita>
			<sector unit="%">
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
		</gdp>
		<labour>
			<force>11630000</force>
			<sector>
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
			<unemployment unit="%">9.8</unemployment>
		</labour>
		<poverty>[object Object]</poverty>
		<household-income>TO DO</household-income>
		<budget>
			<revenue unit="USD"></revenue>
			<expenditure unit="USD"></expenditure>
		</budget>
		<public-debt unit="% of GDP">58.2</public-debt>
		<consumer-inflation unit="%">2.5</consumer-inflation>
		<central-bank-discount-rate unit="%">3.31</central-bank-discount-rate>
		<commercial-prime-lending-rate unit="%">6.5</commercial-prime-lending-rate>
		<narrow-money-stock unit="USD">67330000000</narrow-money-stock>
		<broad-money-stock unit="USD">108700000000</broad-money-stock>
		<domestic-credit-stock unit="USD">93210000000</domestic-credit-stock>
		<agriculture-products>barley, wheat, citrus fruits, grapes, vegetables, olives; livestock; wine</agriculture-products>
		<industries>phosphate rock mining and processing, food processing, leather goods, textiles, construction, energy, tourism</industries>
		<industrial-production-growth>[object Object]</industrial-production-growth>
		<electricity unit="kWh">
			<production>19780000000</production>
			<consumption>20780000000</consumption>
			<exports>0</exports>
			<imports>3429000000</imports>
		</electricity>
		<oil>
			<production unit="bbl/day">4053</production>
			<consumption unit="bbl/day">187000</consumption>
			<exports unit="bbl/day">17420</exports>
			<imports unit="bbl/day">195800</imports>
			<reserves unit="bbl">100000000</reserves>
		</oil>
		<natural-gas>
			<production unit="cu m">60000000</production>
			<consumption unit="cu m">560000000</consumption>
			<exports unit="cu m">0</exports>
			<imports unit="cu m">500000000</imports>
			<reserves unit="cu m">1501000000</reserves>
		</natural-gas>
		<exports>
			<total unit="USD"></total>
			<commodities>clothing and textiles, electric components, inorganic chemicals, transistors, crude minerals, fertilizers (including phosphates), petroleum products, citrus fruits, vegetables, fish</commodities>
			<partners>Spain 22.02%, France 20.22%, India 4.91%, Italy 4% (2009)</partners>
		</exports>
		<imports>
			<total unit="USD">34189999999.999996</total>
			<commodities>crude petroleum, textile fabric, telecommunications equipment, wheat, gas and electricity, transistors, plastics</commodities>
			<partners>France 16.95%, Spain 14.72%, China 7.1%, Italy 6.76%, Germany 6.28%, US 5.66%, Saudi Arabia 5.11% (2009)</partners>
		</imports>
		<external-debt unit="USD">22690000000</external-debt>
		<exchange-rates>Moroccan dirhams (MAD) per US dollar -</exchange-rates>
	</economy>
	<communications>
		<telephones>
			<assessment>good system composed of open-wire lines, cables, and microwave radio relay links; principal switching centers are Casablanca and Rabat; national network nearly 100% digital using fiber-optic links; improved rural service employs microwave radio relay; Internet available but expensive</assessment>
			<domestic>fixed-line teledensity is roughly 10 per 100 persons; mobile-cellular subscribership approached 75 per 100 persons in 2009</domestic>
			<international>country code - 212; landing point for the Atlas Offshore, Estepona-Tetouan, Euroafrica, Spain-Morocco, and SEA-ME-WE-3 fiber-optic telecommunications undersea cables that provide connectivity to Asia, the Middle East, and Europe; satellite earth stations - 2 Intelsat (Atlantic Ocean) and 1 Arabsat; microwave radio relay to Gibraltar, Spain, and Western Sahara; coaxial cable and microwave radio relay to Algeria; participant in Medarabtel; fiber-optic cable link from Agadir to Algeria and Tunisia (2009)</international>
			<land-lines>3516000</land-lines>
			<mobile>25311000</mobile>
		</telephones>
		<broadcast>2 television broadcast networks with state-run Radio-Television Marocaine (RTM) operating one network and the state partially owning the other; foreign TV broadcasts are available via satellite dish; 3 radio broadcast networks with RTM operating one; the government-owned network includes 10 regional radio channels in addition to its national service (2007)</broadcast>
		<internet>
			<tld>.ma</tld>
			<hosts>277793</hosts>
			<users>13213000</users>
		</internet>
	</communications>
	<transport>
		<airports>
			<total>58</total>
			<paved>
				<altitude min="*" max="*"></altitude>
				<altitude min="3047m" max="*">11</altitude>
				<altitude min="2438m" max="3047m">7</altitude>
				<altitude min="1524m" max="2437m">10</altitude>
				<altitude min="914m" max="1524m">4</altitude>
				<altitude min="*" max="914m"></altitude>
			</paved>
		</airports>
		<ports-and-terminals>Casablanca, Jorf Lasfar, Mohammedia, Safi, Tangier</ports-and-terminals>
	</transport>
	<military>
		<branches>Royal Armed Forces (Forces Armees Royales, FAR): Royal Moroccan Army (includes Air Defense), Royal Moroccan Navy (includes Coast Guard, Marines), Royal Moroccan Air Force (Al Quwwat al Jawyiya al Malakiya Marakishiya; Force Aerienne Royale Marocaine) (2010)</branches>
		<manpower>
			<population-available>
				<male>8252</male>
				<female>8691</female>
			</population-available>
			<fit-for-service>
				<male>7026</male>
				<female>7377</female>
			</fit-for-service>
			<reaching-maturity>
				<male>300327</male>
				<female>298366</female>
			</reaching-maturity>
			<notes></notes>
		</manpower>
	</military>
	<issues>
		<disputes>claims and administers Western Sahara whose sovereignty remains unresolved; Morocco protests Spain's control over the coastal enclaves of Ceuta, Melilla, and Penon de Velez de la Gomera, the islands of Penon de Alhucemas and Islas Chafarinas, and surrounding waters; both countries claim Isla Perejil (Leila Island); discussions have not progressed on a comprehensive maritime delimitation, setting limits on resource exploration and refugee interdiction, since Morocco's 2002 rejection of Spain's unilateral designation of a median line from the Canary Islands; Morocco serves as one of the primary launching areas of illegal migration into Spain from North Africa; Algeria's border with Morocco remains an irritant to bilateral relations, each nation accusing the other of harboring militants and arms smuggling; the FLN's assertions of a claim to Chirac Pastures in southeastern Morocco is a dormant dispute</disputes>
		<drugs>one of the world's largest producers of illicit hashish; shipments of hashish mostly directed to Western Europe; transit point for cocaine from South America destined for Western Europe; significant consumer of cannabis</drugs>
	</issues>
</country>