<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<country>
	<code>mv</code>
	<name>Maldives</name>
	<region>South Asia</region>
	<background>Maldives was long a sultanate, first under Dutch and then under British protection. It became a republic in 1968, three years after independence. President Maumoon Abdul GAYOOM dominated the islands' political scene for 30 years, elected to six successive terms by single-party referendums. Following riots in the capital Male in August 2004, the president and his government pledged to embark upon democratic reforms including a more representative political system and expanded political freedoms. Progress was sluggish, however, and many promised reforms were slow to be realized. Nonetheless, political parties were legalized in 2005. In June 2008, a constituent assembly - termed the &quot;Special Majlis&quot; - finalized a new constitution, which was ratified by the president in August. The first-ever presidential elections under a multi-candidate, multi-party system were held in October 2008. GAYOOM was defeated in a runoff poll by Mohamed NASHEED, a political activist who had been jailed several years earlier by the former regime. Challenges facing President NASHEED include strengthening democracy and combating poverty and drug abuse. Maldives officials have played a prominent role in the international climate change discussion (due to the islands' low elevation and the threat from sea-level rise) and on the United Nations Human Rights Council.</background>
	<geo>
		<note>1,190 coral islands grouped into 26 atolls (200 inhabited islands, plus 80 islands with tourist resorts); archipelago with strategic location astride and along major sea lanes in Indian Ocean</note>
		<location>
			<desc>Southern Asia, group of atolls in the Indian Ocean, south-southwest of India</desc>
			<coordinates>TO DO</coordinates>
		</location>
		<area>
			<total unit="sq km">298</total>
			<land unit="sq km">298</land>
			<water unit="sq km">0</water>
			<comparison>about 1.7 times the size of Washington, DC</comparison>
		</area>
		<boundaries>
			<borders unit="km">0</borders>
			<coastline unit="km">644</coastline>
		</boundaries>
		<maritime-claims>
			<territorial unit="nm">12</territorial>
			<contiguous unit="nm">24</contiguous>
			<economic unit="nm">200</economic>
			<continental-shelf></continental-shelf>
		</maritime-claims>
		<climate>tropical; hot, humid; dry, northeast monsoon (November to March); rainy, southwest monsoon (June to August)</climate>
		<terrain>flat, with white sandy beaches</terrain>
		<elevation>
			<high>unnamed location on Viligili in the Addu Atholhu 2.4 m</high>
			<low>Indian Ocean 0 m</low>
		</elevation>
		<resources>fish</resources>
		<land-use>
			<arable unit="%">13.33</arable>
			<crops unit="%">30</crops>
			<other unit="%">56.67</other>
		</land-use>
		<hazards>tsunamis; low elevation of islands makes them sensitive to sea level rise</hazards>
		<issues>depletion of freshwater aquifers threatens water supplies; global warming and sea level rise; coral reef bleaching</issues>
		<water>
			<irrigated-land unit=""></irrigated-land>
			<renewable-water unit="cu km">0.03</renewable-water>
			<freshwater-withdrawal>
				<total unit="cu km/yr">0.003</total>
				<per-capita unit="cu m/yr">9</per-capita>
			</freshwater-withdrawal>
		</water>
		<!--
"geo": {

		"Natural hazards": "flooding is a threat in some areas of the country (e.g., parts of Jutland, along the southern coast of the island of Lolland) that are protected from the sea by a system of dikes",
		"Environment - current issues": "air pollution, principally from vehicle and power plant emissions; nitrogen and phosphorus pollution of the North Sea; drinking and surface water becoming polluted from animal wastes and pesticides",
		"Environment - international agreements": {
			"party to:": "Air Pollution, Air Pollution-Nitrogen Oxides, Air Pollution-Persistent Organic Pollutants, Air Pollution-Sulfur 85, Air Pollution-Sulfur 94, Air Pollution-Volatile Organic Compounds, Antarctic Treaty, Biodiversity, Climate Change, Climate Change-Kyoto Protocol, Desertification, Endangered Species, Environmental Modification, Hazardous Wastes, Law of the Sea, Marine Dumping, Marine Life Conservation, Ozone Layer Protection, Ship Pollution, Tropical Timber 83, Tropical Timber 94, Wetlands, Whaling",
			"signed, but not ratified:": "none of the selected agreements"
		},
		"Geography - note": "controls Danish Straits (Skagerrak and Kattegat) linking Baltic and North Seas; about one-quarter of the population lives in greater Copenhagen"

		-->
	</geo>
	<people>
		<population>
			<total>394999</total>
			<birth unit="births/1,000 population">14.83</birth>
			<death unit="deaths/1,000 population">3.71</birth>
			<migration unit=""></migration>
			<growth unit=""></growth>
		</population>
		<age-distribution unit="percent">
			<group min="0" max="14">21.5</group>
			<group min="15" max="64">74.4</group>
			<group min="65"></group>
		</age-distribution>
		<median-age unit="years">
			<total>26.2</total>
			<male>26.8</male>
			<female>25.2</female>
		</median-age>
		<urbanization>
			<urban unit="% of total population">40</urban>
			<rate unit="% annual rate of change">4.2</urban>
			<cities>MALE (capital) 120,000 (2009)</cities>
		</urbanization>
		<sex unit="male(s)/female">
			<group name="at birth" max="0">1.05</group>
			<group name="0 to 14" min="0" max="14">1.04</group>
			<group name="15 to 64" min="15" max="64">1.57</group>
			<group name="65 and over" min="65" max="0">0.98</group>
			<group name="total" min="0">1.4</group>
		</sex>
		<infant-mortality>
			<total unit="deaths/1,000 live births">27.45</total>
			<male unit="deaths/1,000 live births">29.93</male>
			<female unit="deaths/1,000 live births">24.84</female>
		</infant-mortality>
		<life-expectancy-at-birth>
			<total unit="years">74.45</total>
			<male unit="years">72.22</male>
			<female unit="years">76.8</female>
		</life-expectancy-at-birth>
		<fertility-rate unit="1.81">children born/woman</fertility-rate>
		<hiv>
			<prevalence>less than 0.1% (2009 est.)</prevalence>
			<total>fewer than 100 (2009 est.)</total>
			<deaths>fewer than 100 (2009 est.)</deaths>
		</hiv>
		<infectious-disease risk="">
			<food-or-waterborne></food-or-waterborne>
			<vectorborne></vectorborne>
			<water-contact></water-contact>
		</infectious-disease>
		<drinking-water-source>[object Object]</drinking-water-source>
		<sanitation-access>[object Object]</sanitation-access>
		<nationality>
			<noun>Maldivian(s)</noun>
			<adjective>Maldivian</adjective>
		</nationality>
		<ethnic-groups>South Indians, Sinhalese, Arabs</ethnic-groups>
		<religions>Sunni Muslim</religions>
		<languages>Dhivehi (official, dialect of Sinhala, script derived from Arabic), English (spoken by most government officials)</languages>
		<literacy>
			<definition>age 15 and over can read and write</definition>
			<total unit="%">93.8</total>
			<male unit="%">93</male>
			<female unit="%">94.7</female>
		</literacy>
		<school-expectancy unit="years">12</school-expectancy>
		<education-expenditure unit="% of GDP">11.2</school-expectancy>
	</people>
	<government>
		<country-name>
			<long>Republic of Maldives</long>
			<short>Maldives</short>
		</country-name>
		<dependency></dependency>
		<government-type>republic</government-type>
		<capital>
			<name>Male</name>
			<coordinates>4° 10' N, 73° 30' E</coordinates>
			<time-difference>UTC+5 (10 hours ahead of Washington, DC during Standard Time)</time-difference>
		</capital>
		<administrative-divisions>19 atolls (atholhu, singular and plural) and the capital city*; Alifu, Baa, Dhaalu, Faafu, Gaafu Alifu, Gaafu Dhaalu, Gnaviyani, Haa Alifu, Haa Dhaalu, Kaafu, Laamu, Lhaviyani, Maale (Male)*, Meemu, Noonu, Raa, Seenu, Shaviyani, Thaa, Vaavu</administrative-divisions>
		<independence>26 July 1965 (from the UK)</independence>
		<national-holiday>Independence Day, 26 July (1965)</national-holiday>
		<legal-system>Islamic religious legal system with English common law influences, primarily in commercial matters</legal-system>
		<suffrage>18 years of age; universal</suffrage>
		<executive>
			<head-of-state>President Mohamed &quot;Anni&quot; NASHEED (since 11 November 2008); Vice President Mohamed WAHEED Hassan Maniku (since 11 November 2008); note - the president is both the chief of state and head of government</head-of-state>
			<head-of-government>President Mohamed &quot;Anni&quot; NASHEED (since 11 November 2008); Vice President Mohamed WAHEED Hassan Maniku (since 11 November 2008)</head-of-government>
			<cabinet>Cabinet of Ministers is appointed by the president</cabinet>
			<elections>under the new constitution, the president elected by direct vote; president elected for a five-year term (eligible for a second term); election last held on 8 and 28 October 2008 (next to be held in 2013)</elections>
			<election-results>Mohamed NASHEED elected president; percent of vote - Mohamed NASHEED 54.3%, Maumoon Abdul GAYOOM 45.7%</election-results>
		</executive>
		<legislative>
			<description>unicameral People's Council or People's Majlis (77 seats; members elected by direct vote to serve five-year terms); note - the Majlis in February 2009 passed legislation that increased the number of seats to 77 from 50</description>
			<elections>last held on 9 May 2009 (next to be held in 2014)</elections>
			<election-results>percent of vote - DRP 36.4%, MDP 33.8 %, PA 9.1%, DQP 2.6% Republican Party 1.2%, independents 16.9%; seats by party as of 23 February 2011 - DRP 27, MDP 33, PA 7, DQP 1, Republican Party 2, independents 7</election-results>
		</legislative>
		<judicial>Supreme Court; Supreme Court judges are appointed by the president with approval of voting members of the People's Council; High Court; Trial Courts; all lower court judges are appointed by the Judicial Service Commission</judicial>
		<parties>Adhaalath (Justice) Party or AP [Shaykh Hussein RASHEED Ahmed]; Dhivehi Quamee Party or DQP [Hassan SAEED]; Dhivehi Rayyithunge Party (Maldivian People's Party) or DRP [THASMEEN Ali]; Gaumii Ithihaad (National Alliance) or GI [Mohamed WAHEED]; Islamic Democratic Party or IDP; Maldivian Democratic Party or MDP [Mariya Ahmed DIDI]; Maldives National Congress or MNC; Maldives Social Democratic Party or MSDP; People's Alliance or PA [Abdullah YAMEEN]; People's Party or PP; Poverty Alleviation Party or PAP; Republican (Jumhooree) Party or JP [Gasim IBRAHIM]; Social Liberal Party or SLP [Ibrahim ISMAIL]</parties>
		<pressure-groups>TO DO</pressure-groups>
		<membership>ADB, AOSIS, C, CP, FAO, G-77, IBRD, ICAO, IDA, IDB, IFAD, IFC, IFRCS (observer), ILO, IMF, IMO, Interpol, IOC, IPU, ITU, MIGA, NAM, OIC, OPCW, SAARC, SACEP, UN, UNCTAD, UNESCO, UNIDO, UNWTO, UPU, WCO, WHO, WIPO, WMO, WTO</membership>
		<representation-in-usa>
			<chief>Ambassador Abdul GHAFOOR Mohamed</chief>
			<chancery>800 2nd Avenue, Suite 400E, New York, NY 10017</chancery>
			<telephone>[1] (212) 599-6195</telephone>
			<FAX>[1] (212) 661-6405</FAX>
			<consulates></consulates>
		</representation-in-usa>
		<representation-from-usa>
			<chief></chief>
			<embassy></embassy>
			<mailing-address></mailing-address>
			<telephone></telephone>
			<FAX></FAX>
		</representation-from-usa>
		<flag>red with a large green rectangle in the center bearing a vertical white crescent moon; the closed side of the crescent is on the hoist side of the flag; red recalls those who have sacrificed their lives in defense of their country, the green rectangle represents peace and prosperity, and the white crescent signifies Islam</flag>
		<anthem>
			<name>&quot;Gaumee Salaam&quot; (National Salute)</name>
			<by>Mohamed Jameel DIDI/Wannakuwattawaduge DON AMARADEVA</by>
		</anthem>
	</government>
	<economy>
		<overview>Tourism, Maldives' largest economic activity, accounts for 28% of GDP and more than 60% of foreign exchange receipts. Over 90% of government tax revenue comes from import duties and tourism-related taxes. Fishing is the second leading sector, but the fish catch has dropped sharply in recent years. Agriculture and manufacturing continue to play a lesser role in the economy, constrained by the limited availability of cultivable land and the shortage of domestic labor. Most staple foods must be imported. In the last decade, real GDP growth averaged around 6% per year except for 2005, when GDP declined following the Indian Ocean tsunami, and in 2009, when GDP shrank by 3% as tourist arrivals declined and capital flows plunged in the wake of the global financial crisis. Falling tourist arrivals and fish exports, combined with high government spending on social needs, subsidies, and civil servant salaries contributed to a balance of payments crisis, which was eased with a December 2009, $79.3 million dollar IMF standby agreement. However, after the first two disbursements, the IMF withheld subsequent disbursements due to concerns over Maldives' growing budget deficit. Maldives has had chronic budget deficits in recent years and the government's plans to cut expenditures have not progressed well. A new Goods and Services Tax on Tourism (GST) was introduced in January 2011 and a new Business Profit Tax is to be introduced during the year. These taxes are expected to increase government revenue by about 25%. The government has privatized the main airport and is partially privatizing the energy sector. Tourism will remain the engine of the economy. The Government of the Maldives has aggressively promoted building new island resorts. Due to increasing tourist arrivals, the government expects GDP growth around 4.0% in 2011. Diversifying the economy beyond tourism and fishing, reforming public finance, and increasing employment opportunities are major challenges facing the government. Over the longer term Maldivian authorities worry about the impact of erosion and possible global warming on their low-lying country; 80% of the area is 1 meter or less above sea level.</overview>
		<gdp>
			<purchasing-power-parity></purchasing-power-parity>
			<official-exchange-rate>1870000000</official-exchange-rate>
			<real-growth-rate unit="%">8</real-growth-rate>
			<per-capita></per-capita>
			<sector unit="%">
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
		</gdp>
		<labour>
			<force>110000</force>
			<sector>
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
			<unemployment unit="%">14.5</unemployment>
		</labour>
		<poverty>[object Object]</poverty>
		<household-income>TO DO</household-income>
		<budget>
			<revenue unit="USD"></revenue>
			<expenditure unit="USD"></expenditure>
		</budget>
		<public-debt unit=""></public-debt>
		<consumer-inflation unit="%">6</consumer-inflation>
		<central-bank-discount-rate unit="%">13</central-bank-discount-rate>
		<commercial-prime-lending-rate unit="%">13</commercial-prime-lending-rate>
		<narrow-money-stock unit="USD">588000000</narrow-money-stock>
		<broad-money-stock unit="USD">1239000000</broad-money-stock>
		<domestic-credit-stock unit="USD">1548000000</domestic-credit-stock>
		<agriculture-products>coconuts, corn, sweet potatoes; fish</agriculture-products>
		<industries>tourism, fish processing, shipping, boat building, coconut processing, garments, woven mats, rope, handicrafts, coral and sand mining</industries>
		<industrial-production-growth>-0.9% (2004 est.)</industrial-production-growth>
		<electricity unit="kWh">
			<production>542000000</production>
			<consumption>542000000</consumption>
			<exports>0</exports>
			<imports>0</imports>
		</electricity>
		<oil>
			<production unit="bbl/day">0</production>
			<consumption unit="bbl/day">6000</consumption>
			<exports unit="bbl/day">0</exports>
			<imports unit="bbl/day">5490</imports>
			<reserves unit="bbl">0</reserves>
		</oil>
		<natural-gas>
			<production unit="cu m">0</production>
			<consumption unit="cu m">0</consumption>
			<exports unit="cu m">0</exports>
			<imports unit="cu m">0</imports>
			<reserves unit="cu m">0</reserves>
		</natural-gas>
		<exports>
			<total unit="USD"></total>
			<commodities>fish</commodities>
			<partners>France 17.01%, Thailand 15.16%, Italy 13.49%, UK 13.13%, Sri Lanka 12.38% (2009)</partners>
		</exports>
		<imports>
			<total unit="USD">967000000</total>
			<commodities>petroleum products, ships, foodstuffs, clothing, intermediate and capital goods</commodities>
			<partners>Singapore 24.62%, UAE 15.7%, India 11.02%, Malaysia 8.98%, Sri Lanka 5.4%, Thailand 5.36% (2009)</partners>
		</imports>
		<external-debt unit="USD">943000000</external-debt>
		<exchange-rates>rufiyaa (MVR) per US dollar -</exchange-rates>
	</economy>
	<communications>
		<telephones>
			<assessment>telephone services have improved; interatoll communication through microwave links; all inhabited islands and resorts are connected with telephone and fax service</assessment>
			<domestic>each island now has at least 1 public telephone, and there are mobile-cellular networks with a rapidly expanding subscribership that exceeds 100 per 100 persons</domestic>
			<international>country code - 960; linked to international submarine cable Fiber-Optic Link Around the Globe (FLAG); satellite earth station - 3 Intelsat (Indian Ocean) (2009)</international>
			<land-lines>49913</land-lines>
			<mobile>461149</mobile>
		</telephones>
		<broadcast>state-owned radio and television monopoly until recently; state-owned TV operates 2 channels; 2 privately-owned TV stations; state owns Voice of Maldives and operates both an entertainment and a music-based station; there are 5 privately-owned radio broadcast stations operating (2009)</broadcast>
		<internet>
			<tld>.mv</tld>
			<hosts>2164</hosts>
			<users>86400</users>
		</internet>
	</communications>
	<transport>
		<airports>
			<total>5</total>
			<paved>
				<altitude min="*" max="*"></altitude>
				<altitude min="3047m" max="*">1</altitude>
				<altitude min="2438m" max="3047m">1</altitude>
				<altitude min="1524m" max="2437m"></altitude>
				<altitude min="914m" max="1524m">1</altitude>
				<altitude min="*" max="914m"></altitude>
			</paved>
		</airports>
		<ports-and-terminals>Male</ports-and-terminals>
	</transport>
	<military>
		<branches>Maldives National Defense Force (MNDF): Marine Corps, Security Protection Group, Coast Guard (2010)</branches>
		<manpower>
			<population-available>
				<male>156319</male>
				<female>98815</female>
			</population-available>
			<fit-for-service>
				<male>135374</male>
				<female>85181</female>
			</fit-for-service>
			<reaching-maturity>
				<male>4167</male>
				<female>3595</female>
			</reaching-maturity>
			<notes>the Maldives National Defense Force (MNDF), with its small size and with little serviceable equipment, is inadequate to prevent external aggression and is primarily tasked to reinforce the Maldives Police Service (MPS) and ensure security in the exclusive economic zone (2008)</notes>
		</manpower>
	</military>
	<issues>
		<disputes>none</disputes>
		<drugs></drugs>
	</issues>
</country>