<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<country>
	<code>ni</code>
	<name>Nigeria</name>
	<region>Africa</region>
	<background>British influence and control over what would become Nigeria and Africa's most populous country grew through the 19th century. A series of constitutions after World War II granted Nigeria greater autonomy; independence came in 1960. Following nearly 16 years of military rule, a new constitution was adopted in 1999, and a peaceful transition to civilian government was completed. The government continues to face the daunting task of reforming a petroleum-based economy, whose revenues have been squandered through corruption and mismanagement, and institutionalizing democracy. In addition, Nigeria continues to experience longstanding ethnic and religious tensions. Although both the 2003 and 2007 presidential elections were marred by significant irregularities and violence, Nigeria is currently experiencing its longest period of civilian rule since independence. The general elections of April 2007 marked the first civilian-to-civilian transfer of power in the country's history. In January 2010, Nigeria assumed a nonpermanent seat on the UN Security Council for the 2010-11 term.</background>
	<geo>
		<note>the Niger enters the country in the northwest and flows southward through tropical rain forests and swamps to its delta in the Gulf of Guinea</note>
		<location>
			<desc>Western Africa, bordering the Gulf of Guinea, between Benin and Cameroon</desc>
			<coordinates>TO DO</coordinates>
		</location>
		<area>
			<total unit="sq km">923768</total>
			<land unit="sq km">910768</land>
			<water unit="sq km">13000</water>
			<comparison>slightly more than twice the size of California</comparison>
		</area>
		<boundaries>
			<borders unit=""></borders>
			<coastline unit="km">853</coastline>
		</boundaries>
		<maritime-claims>
			<territorial unit="nm">12</territorial>
			<contiguous unit=""></contiguous>
			<economic unit="nm">200</economic>
			<continental-shelf>200 m depth or to the depth of exploitation</continental-shelf>
		</maritime-claims>
		<climate>varies; equatorial in south, tropical in center, arid in north</climate>
		<terrain>southern lowlands merge into central hills and plateaus; mountains in southeast, plains in north</terrain>
		<elevation>
			<high>Chappal Waddi 2,419 m</high>
			<low>Atlantic Ocean 0 m</low>
		</elevation>
		<resources>natural gas, petroleum, tin, iron ore, coal, limestone, niobium, lead, zinc, arable land</resources>
		<land-use>
			<arable unit="%">33.02</arable>
			<crops unit="%">3.14</crops>
			<other unit="%">63.84</other>
		</land-use>
		<hazards>periodic droughts; flooding</hazards>
		<issues>soil degradation; rapid deforestation; urban air and water pollution; desertification; oil pollution - water, air, and soil; has suffered serious damage from oil spills; loss of arable land; rapid urbanization</issues>
		<water>
			<irrigated-land unit="sq km">2930</irrigated-land>
			<renewable-water unit="cu km">286.2</renewable-water>
			<freshwater-withdrawal>
				<total unit="cu km/yr">8.01</total>
				<per-capita unit="cu m/yr">61</per-capita>
			</freshwater-withdrawal>
		</water>
		<!--
"geo": {

		"Natural hazards": "flooding is a threat in some areas of the country (e.g., parts of Jutland, along the southern coast of the island of Lolland) that are protected from the sea by a system of dikes",
		"Environment - current issues": "air pollution, principally from vehicle and power plant emissions; nitrogen and phosphorus pollution of the North Sea; drinking and surface water becoming polluted from animal wastes and pesticides",
		"Environment - international agreements": {
			"party to:": "Air Pollution, Air Pollution-Nitrogen Oxides, Air Pollution-Persistent Organic Pollutants, Air Pollution-Sulfur 85, Air Pollution-Sulfur 94, Air Pollution-Volatile Organic Compounds, Antarctic Treaty, Biodiversity, Climate Change, Climate Change-Kyoto Protocol, Desertification, Endangered Species, Environmental Modification, Hazardous Wastes, Law of the Sea, Marine Dumping, Marine Life Conservation, Ozone Layer Protection, Ship Pollution, Tropical Timber 83, Tropical Timber 94, Wetlands, Whaling",
			"signed, but not ratified:": "none of the selected agreements"
		},
		"Geography - note": "controls Danish Straits (Skagerrak and Kattegat) linking Baltic and North Seas; about one-quarter of the population lives in greater Copenhagen"

		-->
	</geo>
	<people>
		<population>
			<total>155215</total>
			<birth unit="births/1,000 population">35.51</birth>
			<death unit="deaths/1,000 population">16.06</birth>
			<migration unit=""></migration>
			<growth unit="%">1.935</growth>
		</population>
		<age-distribution unit="percent">
			<group min="0" max="14">40.9</group>
			<group min="15" max="64">55.9</group>
			<group min="65"></group>
		</age-distribution>
		<median-age unit="years">
			<total>19.2</total>
			<male>19.2</male>
			<female>19.3</female>
		</median-age>
		<urbanization>
			<urban unit="% of total population">50</urban>
			<rate unit="% annual rate of change">3.5</urban>
			<cities>Lagos 10.203 million; Kano 3.304 million; Ibadan 2.762 million; ABUJA (capital) 1.857 million; Kaduna 1.519 million (2009)</cities>
		</urbanization>
		<sex unit="male(s)/female">
			<group name="at birth" max="0">1.06</group>
			<group name="0 to 14" min="0" max="14">1.05</group>
			<group name="15 to 64" min="15" max="64">1.04</group>
			<group name="65 and over" min="65" max="0">0.94</group>
			<group name="total" min="0">1.04</group>
		</sex>
		<infant-mortality>
			<total unit="deaths/1,000 live births">91.54</total>
			<male unit="deaths/1,000 live births">97.42</male>
			<female unit="deaths/1,000 live births">85.31</female>
		</infant-mortality>
		<life-expectancy-at-birth>
			<total unit="years">47.56</total>
			<male unit="years">46.76</male>
			<female unit="years">48.41</female>
		</life-expectancy-at-birth>
		<fertility-rate unit="4.73">children born/woman</fertility-rate>
		<hiv>
			<prevalence>[object Object]</prevalence>
			<total>3300000</total>
			<deaths>220000</deaths>
		</hiv>
		<infectious-disease risk="very high">
			<food-or-waterborne>bacterial and protozoal diarrhea, hepatitis A and E, and typhoid fever</food-or-waterborne>
			<vectorborne></vectorborne>
			<water-contact></water-contact>
		</infectious-disease>
		<drinking-water-source>[object Object]</drinking-water-source>
		<sanitation-access>[object Object]</sanitation-access>
		<nationality>
			<noun>Nigerian(s)</noun>
			<adjective>Nigerian</adjective>
		</nationality>
		<ethnic-groups>Nigeria, Africa's most populous country, is composed of more than 250 ethnic groups; the following are the most populous and politically influential: Hausa and Fulani 29%, Yoruba 21%, Igbo (Ibo) 18%, Ijaw 10%, Kanuri 4%, Ibibio 3.5%, Tiv 2.5%</ethnic-groups>
		<religions>Muslim 50%, Christian 40%, indigenous beliefs 10%</religions>
		<languages>English (official), Hausa, Yoruba, Igbo (Ibo), Fulani, over 500 additional indigenous languages</languages>
		<literacy>
			<definition>age 15 and over can read and write</definition>
			<total unit="%">68</total>
			<male unit="%">75.7</male>
			<female unit="%">60.6</female>
		</literacy>
		<school-expectancy unit="years">9</school-expectancy>
		<education-expenditure unit=""></school-expectancy>
	</people>
	<government>
		<country-name>
			<long>Federal Republic of Nigeria</long>
			<short>Nigeria</short>
		</country-name>
		<dependency></dependency>
		<government-type>federal republic</government-type>
		<capital>
			<name>Abuja</name>
			<coordinates>9° 5' N, 7° 32' E</coordinates>
			<time-difference>UTC+1 (6 hours ahead of Washington, DC during Standard Time)</time-difference>
		</capital>
		<administrative-divisions>36 states and 1 territory*; Abia, Adamawa, Akwa Ibom, Anambra, Bauchi, Bayelsa, Benue, Borno, Cross River, Delta, Ebonyi, Edo, Ekiti, Enugu, Federal Capital Territory*, Gombe, Imo, Jigawa, Kaduna, Kano, Katsina, Kebbi, Kogi, Kwara, Lagos, Nassarawa, Niger, Ogun, Ondo, Osun, Oyo, Plateau, Rivers, Sokoto, Taraba, Yobe, Zamfara</administrative-divisions>
		<independence>1 October 1960 (from the UK)</independence>
		<national-holiday>Independence Day (National Day), 1 October (1960)</national-holiday>
		<legal-system>mixed legal system of English common law, Islamic law (in 12 northern states), and traditional law</legal-system>
		<suffrage>18 years of age; universal</suffrage>
		<executive>
			<head-of-state>President Goodluck JONATHAN (since 5 May 2010, acting since 9 February 2010); Vice President Mohammed Namadi SAMBO (since 19 May 2010); note - the president is both the chief of state and head of government; JONATHAN assumed the presidency on 5 May 2010 following the death of President YAR'ADUA; JONATHAN was declared Acting President on 9 February 2010 by the National Assembly during the extended illness of the former president</head-of-state>
			<head-of-government>President Goodluck JONATHAN (since 5 May 2010, acting since 9 February 2010); Vice President Mohammed Namadi SAMBO (since 19 May 2010)</head-of-government>
			<cabinet>Federal Executive Council</cabinet>
			<elections>president elected by popular vote for a four-year term (eligible for a second term); election last held on 16 April 2011 (next to be held in April 2015)</elections>
			<election-results>Goodluck JONATHAN elected president; percent of vote - Goodluck JONATHAN 58.9%, Muhammadu BUHARI 32.0%, Nuhu RIBADU 5.4%, Ibrahim SHEKARAU 2.4%, other 1.3%</election-results>
		</executive>
		<legislative>
			<description>bicameral National Assembly consists of the Senate (109 seats, 3 from each state plus 1 from Abuja; members elected by popular vote to serve four-year terms) and House of Representatives (360 seats; members elected by popular vote to serve four-year terms)</description>
			<elections>Senate - last held on 9 April 2011 (next to be held in 2015); House of Representatives - last held on 9 April 2011 (next to be held in 2015)</elections>
			<election-results>Senate - percent of vote by party - NA; seats by party - PDP 45, ACN 13, ANPP 7, CPC 5, other 4; House of Representatives - percent of vote by party - NA; seats by party - PDP 123, ACN 47, CPC 30, ANPP 25, other 9; note - due to logistical problems elections in a number of constituencies were postponed</election-results>
		</legislative>
		<judicial>Supreme Court (judges recommended by the National Judicial Council and appointed by the president); Federal Court of Appeal (judges are appointed by the federal government from a pool of judges recommended by the National Judicial Council)</judicial>
		<parties>Accord Party [Augustine MAZIE, acting]; Action Congress of Nigeria or ACN [Bisi AKANDE]; All Nigeria Peoples Party or ANPP [Ogbonnaya ONU]; All Progressives Grand Alliance or APGA [Victor C. UMEH]; Alliance for Democracy or AD [Mojisoluwa AKINFENWA]; Conference of Nigerian Political Parities or CNPP [Abdulkadir Balarabe MUSA]; Congress for Progressive Change or CPC; Democratic Peoples Party or DPP [Jeremiah USENI]; Fresh Democratic Party [Chris OKOTIE]; Labor Party [Dan NWANYANWU]; National Democratic Party or NDP [Aliyu Habu FARI]; Peoples Democratic Party or PDP [Dr. Okwesilieze NWODO]; Peoples Progressive Alliance [Larry ESIN]</parties>
		<pressure-groups>TO DO</pressure-groups>
		<membership>ACP, AfDB, AU, C, D-8, ECOWAS, FAO, G-15, G-24, G-77, IAEA, IBRD, ICAO, ICC, ICRM, IDA, IDB, IFAD, IFC, IFRCS, IHO, ILO, IMF, IMO, IMSO, Interpol, IOC, IOM, IPU, ISO, ITSO, ITU, ITUC, MIGA, MINURSO, MONUSCO, NAM, OAS (observer), OIC, OPCW, OPEC, PCA, UN, UN Security Council (temporary), UNAMID, UNCTAD, UNESCO, UNHCR, UNIDO, UNIFIL, UNITAR, UNMIL, UNOCI, UNWTO, UPU, WCO, WFTU, WHO, WIPO, WMO, WTO</membership>
		<representation-in-usa>
			<chief>Ambassador Adebowale Ibidapo ADEFUYE</chief>
			<chancery>3519 International Court NW, Washington, DC 20008</chancery>
			<telephone>[1] (202) 986-8400</telephone>
			<FAX>[1] (202) 775-1385</FAX>
			<consulates>Atlanta, New York</consulates>
		</representation-in-usa>
		<representation-from-usa>
			<chief>Ambassador Terence P. MCCULLEY</chief>
			<embassy>1075 Diplomatic Drive, Central District Area, Abuja</embassy>
			<mailing-address>P. O. Box 5760, Garki, Abuja</mailing-address>
			<telephone>[234] (9) 461-4000</telephone>
			<FAX>[234] (9) 461-4036</FAX>
		</representation-from-usa>
		<flag>three equal vertical bands of green (hoist side), white, and green; the color green represents the forests and abundant natural wealth of the country, white stands for peace and unity</flag>
		<anthem>
			<name>&quot;Arise Oh Compatriots, Nigeria's Call Obey&quot;</name>
			<by>John A. ILECHUKWU, Eme Etim AKPAN, B. A. OGUNNAIKE, Sotu OMOIGUI and P. O. ADERIBIGBE/Benedict Elide ODIASE</by>
		</anthem>
	</government>
	<economy>
		<overview>Oil-rich Nigeria has been hobbled by political instability, corruption, inadequate infrastructure, and poor macroeconomic management but in 2008 began pursuing economic reforms. Nigeria's former military rulers failed to diversify the economy away from its overdependence on the capital-intensive oil sector, which provides 95% of foreign exchange earnings and about 80% of budgetary revenues. Following the signing of an IMF stand-by agreement in August 2000, Nigeria received a debt-restructuring deal from the Paris Club and a $1 billion credit from the IMF, both contingent on economic reforms. Nigeria pulled out of its IMF program in April 2002, after failing to meet spending and exchange rate targets, making it ineligible for additional debt forgiveness from the Paris Club. In November 2005, Abuja won Paris Club approval for a debt-relief deal that eliminated $18 billion of debt in exchange for $12 billion in payments - a total package worth $30 billion of Nigeria's total $37 billion external debt. Since 2008 the government has begun to show the political will to implement the market-oriented reforms urged by the IMF, such as modernizing the banking system, curbing inflation by blocking excessive wage demands, and resolving regional disputes over the distribution of earnings from the oil industry. GDP rose strongly in 2007-10 because of increased oil exports and high global crude prices in 2010. President JONATHAN has pledged to continue the economic reforms of his predecessor with emphasis on infrastructure improvements. Infrastructure is the main impediment to growth and in August 2010 JONATHAN unveiled a power sector blueprint that includes privatization of the state-run electricity generation and distribution facilities. The government also is working toward developing stronger public-private partnerships for roads. Nigeria's financial sector was hurt by the global financial and economic crises and the Central Bank governor has taken measures to strengthen that sector.</overview>
		<gdp>
			<purchasing-power-parity></purchasing-power-parity>
			<official-exchange-rate>216800000000</official-exchange-rate>
			<real-growth-rate unit="%">8.4</real-growth-rate>
			<per-capita></per-capita>
			<sector unit="%">
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
		</gdp>
		<labour>
			<force>48330000</force>
			<sector>
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
			<unemployment unit="%">4.9</unemployment>
		</labour>
		<poverty>[object Object]</poverty>
		<household-income>TO DO</household-income>
		<budget>
			<revenue unit="USD"></revenue>
			<expenditure unit="USD"></expenditure>
		</budget>
		<public-debt unit="% of GDP">13.4</public-debt>
		<consumer-inflation unit="%">13.9</consumer-inflation>
		<central-bank-discount-rate unit="%">6</central-bank-discount-rate>
		<commercial-prime-lending-rate unit="%">18.36</commercial-prime-lending-rate>
		<narrow-money-stock unit="USD">40410000000</narrow-money-stock>
		<broad-money-stock unit="USD">91970000000</broad-money-stock>
		<domestic-credit-stock unit="USD">77430000000</domestic-credit-stock>
		<agriculture-products>cocoa, peanuts, cotton, palm oil, corn, rice, sorghum, millet, cassava (tapioca), yams, rubber; cattle, sheep, goats, pigs; timber; fish</agriculture-products>
		<industries>crude oil, coal, tin, columbite; rubber products, wood; hides and skins, textiles, cement and other construction materials, food products, footwear, chemicals, fertilizer, printing, ceramics, steel</industries>
		<industrial-production-growth>[object Object]</industrial-production-growth>
		<electricity unit="kWh">
			<production>21920000000</production>
			<consumption>19210000000</consumption>
			<exports>0</exports>
			<imports>0</imports>
		</electricity>
		<oil>
			<production unit="bbl/day">2211000</production>
			<consumption unit="bbl/day">280000</consumption>
			<exports unit="bbl/day">2327000</exports>
			<imports unit="bbl/day">170000</imports>
			<reserves unit="bbl">37500000000</reserves>
		</oil>
		<natural-gas>
			<production unit="cu m">32820000000</production>
			<consumption unit="cu m">12280000000</consumption>
			<exports unit="cu m">20550000000</exports>
			<imports unit="cu m">0</imports>
			<reserves unit="cu m">5246000000000</reserves>
		</natural-gas>
		<exports>
			<total unit="USD"></total>
			<commodities>petroleum and petroleum products 95%, cocoa, rubber</commodities>
			<partners>US 35.08%, India 10.43%, Brazil 9.32%, Spain 7.19%, France 4.65% (2009)</partners>
		</exports>
		<imports>
			<total unit="USD">34180000000</total>
			<commodities>machinery, chemicals, transport equipment, manufactured goods, food and live animals</commodities>
			<partners>China 14.89%, US 8.88%, Netherlands 8.18%, South Korea 5.46%, UK 4.63%, France 4.19% (2009)</partners>
		</imports>
		<external-debt unit="USD">11020000000</external-debt>
		<exchange-rates>nairas (NGN) per US dollar -</exchange-rates>
	</economy>
	<communications>
		<telephones>
			<assessment>further expansion and modernization of the fixed-line telephone network is needed; network quality remains a problem</assessment>
			<domestic>the addition of a second fixed-line provider in 2002 resulted in faster growth but subscribership remains only about 1 per 100 persons; mobile-cellular services growing rapidly, in part responding to the shortcomings of the fixed-line network; multiple cellular providers operate nationally with subscribership reaching 50 per 100 persons in 2009</domestic>
			<international>country code - 234; landing point for the SAT-3/WASC fiber-optic submarine cable that provides connectivity to Europe and Asia; satellite earth stations - 3 Intelsat (2 Atlantic Ocean and 1 Indian Ocean) (2009)</international>
			<land-lines>1419000</land-lines>
			<mobile>73099000</mobile>
		</telephones>
		<broadcast>nearly 70 federal-government-controlled national and regional TV stations; all 36 states operate TV stations; several private TV stations operational; cable and satellite TV subscription services are available; network of federal-government-controlled national, regional, and state radio stations; roughly 40 state-government-owned radio stations typically carry their own programs except for news broadcasts; about 20 private radio stations also operate; transmissions of international broadcasters are available (2007)</broadcast>
		<internet>
			<tld>.ng</tld>
			<hosts>1378</hosts>
			<users>43989000</users>
		</internet>
	</communications>
	<transport>
		<airports>
			<total>54</total>
			<paved>
				<altitude min="*" max="*"></altitude>
				<altitude min="3047m" max="*">9</altitude>
				<altitude min="2438m" max="3047m">11</altitude>
				<altitude min="1524m" max="2437m">10</altitude>
				<altitude min="914m" max="1524m">5</altitude>
				<altitude min="*" max="914m"></altitude>
			</paved>
		</airports>
		<ports-and-terminals>Bonny Inshore Terminal, Calabar, Lagos</ports-and-terminals>
	</transport>
	<military>
		<branches>Nigerian Armed Forces: Army, Navy, Air Force (2008)</branches>
		<manpower>
			<population-available>
				<male>37087</male>
				<female>35232</female>
			</population-available>
			<fit-for-service>
				<male>20839</male>
				<female>19867</female>
			</fit-for-service>
			<reaching-maturity>
				<male>1767</male>
				<female>1687</female>
			</reaching-maturity>
			<notes></notes>
		</manpower>
	</military>
	<issues>
		<disputes>Joint Border Commission with Cameroon reviewed 2002 ICJ ruling on the entire boundary and bilaterally resolved differences, including June 2006 Greentree Agreement that immediately cedes sovereignty of the Bakassi Peninsula to Cameroon with a phase-out of Nigerian control within two years while resolving patriation issues; the ICJ ruled on an equidistance settlement of Cameroon-Equatorial Guinea-Nigeria maritime boundary in the Gulf of Guinea, but imprecisely defined coordinates in the ICJ decision and a sovereignty dispute between Equatorial Guinea and Cameroon over an island at the mouth of the Ntem River all contribute to the delay in implementation; only Nigeria and Cameroon have heeded the Lake Chad Commission's admonition to ratify the delimitation treaty which also includes the Chad-Niger and Niger-Nigeria boundaries; location of Benin-Niger-Nigeria tripoint is unresolved</disputes>
		<drugs>a transit point for heroin and cocaine intended for European, East Asian, and North American markets; consumer of amphetamines; safe haven for Nigerian narcotraffickers operating worldwide; major money-laundering center; massive corruption and criminal activity; Nigeria has improved some anti-money-laundering controls, resulting in its removal from the Financial Action Task Force's (FATF's) Noncooperative Countries and Territories List in June 2006; Nigeria's anti-money-laundering regime continues to be monitored by FATF</drugs>
	</issues>
</country>