<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<country>
	<code>nu</code>
	<name>Nicaragua</name>
	<region>Central America and Caribbean</region>
	<background>The Pacific coast of Nicaragua was settled as a Spanish colony from Panama in the early 16th century. Independence from Spain was declared in 1821 and the country became an independent republic in 1838. Britain occupied the Caribbean Coast in the first half of the 19th century, but gradually ceded control of the region in subsequent decades. Violent opposition to governmental manipulation and corruption spread to all classes by 1978 and resulted in a short-lived civil war that brought the Marxist Sandinista guerrillas to power in 1979. Nicaraguan aid to leftist rebels in El Salvador caused the US to sponsor anti-Sandinista contra guerrillas through much of the 1980s. After losing free and fair elections in 1990, 1996, and 2001, former Sandinista President Daniel ORTEGA Saavedra was elected president in 2006. The 2008 municipal elections were marred by widespread irregularities. Nicaragua's infrastructure and economy - hard hit by the earlier civil war and by Hurricane Mitch in 1998 - are slowly being rebuilt, but democratic institutions have been weakened under the ORTEGA administration.</background>
	<geo>
		<note>largest country in Central America; contains the largest freshwater body in Central America, Lago de Nicaragua</note>
		<location>
			<desc>Central America, bordering both the Caribbean Sea and the North Pacific Ocean, between Costa Rica and Honduras</desc>
			<coordinates>TO DO</coordinates>
		</location>
		<area>
			<total unit="sq km">130370</total>
			<land unit="sq km">119990</land>
			<water unit="sq km">10380</water>
			<comparison>slightly smaller than New York state</comparison>
		</area>
		<boundaries>
			<borders unit=""></borders>
			<coastline unit="km">910</coastline>
		</boundaries>
		<maritime-claims>
			<territorial unit="nm">12</territorial>
			<contiguous unit="nm">24</contiguous>
			<economic unit=""></economic>
			<continental-shelf>natural prolongation</continental-shelf>
		</maritime-claims>
		<climate>tropical in lowlands, cooler in highlands</climate>
		<terrain>extensive Atlantic coastal plains rising to central interior mountains; narrow Pacific coastal plain interrupted by volcanoes</terrain>
		<elevation>
			<high>Mogoton 2,438 m</high>
			<low>Pacific Ocean 0 m</low>
		</elevation>
		<resources>gold, silver, copper, tungsten, lead, zinc, timber, fish</resources>
		<land-use>
			<arable unit="%">14.81</arable>
			<crops unit="%">1.82</crops>
			<other unit="%">83.37</other>
		</land-use>
		<hazards>[object Object]</hazards>
		<issues>deforestation; soil erosion; water pollution</issues>
		<water>
			<irrigated-land unit="sq km">610</irrigated-land>
			<renewable-water unit="cu km">196.7</renewable-water>
			<freshwater-withdrawal>
				<total unit="cu km/yr">1.3</total>
				<per-capita unit="cu m/yr">237</per-capita>
			</freshwater-withdrawal>
		</water>
		<!--
"geo": {

		"Natural hazards": "flooding is a threat in some areas of the country (e.g., parts of Jutland, along the southern coast of the island of Lolland) that are protected from the sea by a system of dikes",
		"Environment - current issues": "air pollution, principally from vehicle and power plant emissions; nitrogen and phosphorus pollution of the North Sea; drinking and surface water becoming polluted from animal wastes and pesticides",
		"Environment - international agreements": {
			"party to:": "Air Pollution, Air Pollution-Nitrogen Oxides, Air Pollution-Persistent Organic Pollutants, Air Pollution-Sulfur 85, Air Pollution-Sulfur 94, Air Pollution-Volatile Organic Compounds, Antarctic Treaty, Biodiversity, Climate Change, Climate Change-Kyoto Protocol, Desertification, Endangered Species, Environmental Modification, Hazardous Wastes, Law of the Sea, Marine Dumping, Marine Life Conservation, Ozone Layer Protection, Ship Pollution, Tropical Timber 83, Tropical Timber 94, Wetlands, Whaling",
			"signed, but not ratified:": "none of the selected agreements"
		},
		"Geography - note": "controls Danish Straits (Skagerrak and Kattegat) linking Baltic and North Seas; about one-quarter of the population lives in greater Copenhagen"

		-->
	</geo>
	<people>
		<population>
			<total>5666</total>
			<birth unit="births/1,000 population">19.46</birth>
			<death unit="deaths/1,000 population">5.03</birth>
			<migration unit=""></migration>
			<growth unit="%">1.088</growth>
		</population>
		<age-distribution unit="percent">
			<group min="0" max="14">31.7</group>
			<group min="15" max="64">63.8</group>
			<group min="65"></group>
		</age-distribution>
		<median-age unit="years">
			<total>22.9</total>
			<male>22.1</male>
			<female>23.7</female>
		</median-age>
		<urbanization>
			<urban unit="% of total population">57</urban>
			<rate unit="% annual rate of change">2</urban>
			<cities>MANAGUA (capital) 934,000 (2009)</cities>
		</urbanization>
		<sex unit="male(s)/female">
			<group name="at birth" max="0">1.05</group>
			<group name="0 to 14" min="0" max="14">1.04</group>
			<group name="15 to 64" min="15" max="64">1</group>
			<group name="65 and over" min="65" max="0">0.78</group>
			<group name="total" min="0">1</group>
		</sex>
		<infant-mortality>
			<total unit="deaths/1,000 live births">22.64</total>
			<male unit="deaths/1,000 live births">25.94</male>
			<female unit="deaths/1,000 live births">19.19</female>
		</infant-mortality>
		<life-expectancy-at-birth>
			<total unit="years">71.9</total>
			<male unit="years">69.82</male>
			<female unit="years">74.09</female>
		</life-expectancy-at-birth>
		<fertility-rate unit="2.12">children born/woman</fertility-rate>
		<hiv>
			<prevalence>[object Object]</prevalence>
			<total>6900</total>
			<deaths>fewer than 500 (2009 est.)</deaths>
		</hiv>
		<infectious-disease risk="high">
			<food-or-waterborne>bacterial diarrhea, hepatitis A, and typhoid fever</food-or-waterborne>
			<vectorborne></vectorborne>
			<water-contact></water-contact>
		</infectious-disease>
		<drinking-water-source>[object Object]</drinking-water-source>
		<sanitation-access>[object Object]</sanitation-access>
		<nationality>
			<noun>Nicaraguan(s)</noun>
			<adjective>Nicaraguan</adjective>
		</nationality>
		<ethnic-groups>mestizo (mixed Amerindian and white) 69%, white 17%, black 9%, Amerindian 5%</ethnic-groups>
		<religions>Roman Catholic 58.5%, Evangelical 21.6%, Moravian 1.6%, Jehovah's Witnesses 0.9%, other 1.7%, none 15.7% (2005 census)</religions>
		<languages>[object Object]</languages>
		<literacy>
			<definition>age 15 and over can read and write</definition>
			<total unit="%">67.5</total>
			<male unit="%">67.2</male>
			<female unit="%">67.8</female>
		</literacy>
		<school-expectancy unit="years">11</school-expectancy>
		<education-expenditure unit="% of GDP">3.1</school-expectancy>
	</people>
	<government>
		<country-name>
			<long>Republic of Nicaragua</long>
			<short>Nicaragua</short>
		</country-name>
		<dependency></dependency>
		<government-type>republic</government-type>
		<capital>
			<name>Managua</name>
			<coordinates>12° 9' N, 86° 17' W</coordinates>
			<time-difference>UTC-6 (1 hour behind Washington, DC during Standard Time)</time-difference>
		</capital>
		<administrative-divisions>15 departments (departamentos, singular - departamento) and 2 autonomous regions* (regiones autonomistas, singular - region autonoma); Atlantico Norte*, Atlantico Sur*, Boaco, Carazo, Chinandega, Chontales, Esteli, Granada, Jinotega, Leon, Madriz, Managua, Masaya, Matagalpa, Nueva Segovia, Rio San Juan, Rivas</administrative-divisions>
		<independence>15 September 1821 (from Spain)</independence>
		<national-holiday>Independence Day, 15 September (1821)</national-holiday>
		<legal-system>civil law system; Supreme Court may review administrative acts</legal-system>
		<suffrage>16 years of age; universal</suffrage>
		<executive>
			<head-of-state>President Daniel ORTEGA Saavedra (since 10 January 2007); Vice President Jaime MORALES Carazo (since 10 January 2007); note - the president is both chief of state and head of government</head-of-state>
			<head-of-government>President Daniel ORTEGA Saavedra (since 10 January 2007); Vice President Jaime MORALES Carazo (since 10 January 2007)</head-of-government>
			<cabinet>Council of Ministers appointed by the president</cabinet>
			<elections>president and vice president elected on the same ticket by popular vote for a five-year term (eligible for a second term so long as it is not consecutive); election last held on 5 November 2006 (next to be held by November 2011)</elections>
			<election-results>Daniel ORTEGA Saavedra elected president - 38.1%, Eduardo MONTEALEGRE 29%, Jose RIZO 26.2%, Edmundo JARQUIN 6.4%, other 0.3%</election-results>
		</executive>
		<legislative>
			<description>unicameral National Assembly or Asamblea Nacional (92 seats; 90 members elected by proportional representation and party lists to serve five-year terms; 1 seat for the previous president, 1 seat for the runner-up in previous presidential election)</description>
			<elections>last held on 5 November 2006 (next to be held by November 2011)</elections>
			<election-results>percent of vote by party - NA; seats by party - FSLN 38, PLC 25, ALN 24, MRS 5; note - political parties have been reorganized to reflect the following seat distribution: as of 1 March 2011 - seats by party - FSLN 37, PLC 20, BDN 13, ALN 7, MRS 4, BUN 5, Independent 6</election-results>
		</legislative>
		<judicial>Supreme Court or Corte Suprema de Justicia (16 judges elected for five-year terms by the National Assembly); note - in 2010, President Ortega directly replaced seven justices on the Supreme Court</judicial>
		<parties>Conservative Party or PC [Alejandro BOLANOS Davis]; Independent Liberal Party or PLI [Indalecio RODRIGUEZ]; Liberal Constitutionalist Party or PLC [Jorge CASTILLO Quant]; Nicaraguan Liberal Alliance or ALN [Alejandro MEJIA Ferreti]; Sandinista National Liberation Front or FSLN [Daniel ORTEGA Saavedra]; Sandinista Renovation Movement or MRS [Enrique SAENZ-NAVARRETE]</parties>
		<pressure-groups>TO DO</pressure-groups>
		<membership>BCIE, CACM, FAO, G-77, IADB, IAEA, IBRD, ICAO, ICRM, IDA, IFAD, IFC, IFRCS, ILO, IMF, IMO, Interpol, IOC, IOM, IPU, ITSO, ITU, ITUC, LAES, LAIA (observer), MIGA, NAM, OAS, OPANAL, OPCW, PCA, PetroCaribe, RG, SICA, UN, UNCTAD, UNESCO, UNHCR, UNIDO, Union Latina, UNWTO, UPU, WCO, WHO, WIPO, WMO, WTO</membership>
		<representation-in-usa>
			<chief>Ambassador Francisco Obadiah CAMPBELL Hooker</chief>
			<chancery>1627 New Hampshire Avenue NW, Washington, DC 20009</chancery>
			<telephone>[1] (202) 939-6570, 6573</telephone>
			<FAX>[1] (202) 939-6545</FAX>
			<consulates>Houston, Los Angeles, Miami, New York, San Francisco</consulates>
		</representation-in-usa>
		<representation-from-usa>
			<chief>Ambassador Robert J. CALLAHAN</chief>
			<embassy>Kilometer 5.5 Carretera Sur, Managua</embassy>
			<mailing-address>American Embassy Managua, APO AA 34021</mailing-address>
			<telephone>[505] 252-7100, 252-7888; 252-7634 (after hours)</telephone>
			<FAX>[505] 252-7304</FAX>
		</representation-from-usa>
		<flag>[object Object]</flag>
		<anthem>
			<name>&quot;Salve a ti, Nicaragua&quot; (Hail to Thee, Nicaragua)</name>
			<by>Salomon Ibarra MAYORGA/traditional, arranged by Luis Abraham DELGADILLO</by>
		</anthem>
	</government>
	<economy>
		<overview>Nicaragua, the poorest country in Central America and the second poorest in the Hemisphere, has widespread underemployment and poverty. The US-Central America Free Trade Agreement (CAFTA) has been in effect since April 2006 and has expanded export opportunities for many agricultural and manufactured goods. Textiles and apparel account for nearly 60% of Nicaragua's exports, but increases in the minimum wage during the ORTEGA administration will likely erode its comparative advantage in this industry. ORTEGA's promotion of mixed business initiatives, owned by the Nicaraguan and Venezuelan state oil firms, together with the weak rule of law, could undermine the investment climate for domestic and international private firms in the near-term. Nicaragua relies on international economic assistance to meet internal- and external-debt financing obligations. Foreign donors have curtailed this funding, however, in response to November 2008 electoral fraud. Managua has an IMF extended Credit Facility program, which could help keep the government's fiscal deficit on target during the 2011 election year and encourage transparency in the use of Venezuelan off-budget loans and assistance. In early 2004, Nicaragua secured some $4.5 billion in foreign debt reduction under the Heavily Indebted Poor Countries (HIPC) initiative, however, Managua still struggles with a high public debt burden. Nicaragua is gradually recovering from the global economic crisis as increased exports drove positive growth in 2010. The economy is expected to grow at a rate of about 3% in 2011.</overview>
		<gdp>
			<purchasing-power-parity></purchasing-power-parity>
			<official-exchange-rate>6551000000</official-exchange-rate>
			<real-growth-rate unit="%">4.5</real-growth-rate>
			<per-capita></per-capita>
			<sector unit="%">
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
		</gdp>
		<labour>
			<force>2343000</force>
			<sector>
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
			<unemployment unit=""></unemployment>
		</labour>
		<poverty>[object Object]</poverty>
		<household-income>TO DO</household-income>
		<budget>
			<revenue unit="USD"></revenue>
			<expenditure unit="USD"></expenditure>
		</budget>
		<public-debt unit="% of GDP">78</public-debt>
		<consumer-inflation unit="%">4.7</consumer-inflation>
		<central-bank-discount-rate unit="%"></central-bank-discount-rate>
		<commercial-prime-lending-rate unit="%">14.04</commercial-prime-lending-rate>
		<narrow-money-stock unit="USD">1273000000</narrow-money-stock>
		<broad-money-stock unit="USD">2900000000</broad-money-stock>
		<domestic-credit-stock unit="USD">4083000000</domestic-credit-stock>
		<agriculture-products>coffee, bananas, sugarcane, cotton, rice, corn, tobacco, sesame, soya, beans; beef, veal, pork, poultry, dairy products; shrimp, lobsters</agriculture-products>
		<industries>food processing, chemicals, machinery and metal products, knit and woven apparel, petroleum refining and distribution, beverages, footwear, wood</industries>
		<industrial-production-growth>[object Object]</industrial-production-growth>
		<electricity unit="kWh">
			<production>3286000000</production>
			<consumption>2569000000</consumption>
			<exports>0</exports>
			<imports>63950000</imports>
		</electricity>
		<oil>
			<production unit="bbl/day">0</production>
			<consumption unit="bbl/day">29000</consumption>
			<exports unit="bbl/day">212.5</exports>
			<imports unit="bbl/day">29570</imports>
			<reserves unit="bbl">0</reserves>
		</oil>
		<natural-gas>
			<production unit="cu m">0</production>
			<consumption unit="cu m">0</consumption>
			<exports unit="cu m">0</exports>
			<imports unit="cu m">0</imports>
			<reserves unit="cu m">0</reserves>
		</natural-gas>
		<exports>
			<total unit="USD"></total>
			<commodities>coffee, beef, shrimp and lobster, tobacco, sugar, gold, peanuts; textiles and apparel</commodities>
			<partners>US 61.98%, El Salvador 7.74%, Costa Rica 3.67% (2009)</partners>
		</exports>
		<imports>
			<total unit="USD">4700000000</total>
			<commodities>consumer goods, machinery and equipment, raw materials, petroleum products</commodities>
			<partners>US 22.63%, Venezuela 12.27%, Mexico 9.05%, Costa Rica 8.66%, China 7.16%, Guatemala 6.59%, El Salvador 5.63% (2009)</partners>
		</imports>
		<external-debt unit="USD">4030000000.0000005</external-debt>
		<exchange-rates>cordobas (NIO) per US dollar -</exchange-rates>
	</economy>
	<communications>
		<telephones>
			<assessment>system being upgraded by foreign investment; nearly all installed telecommunications capacity now uses digital technology, owing to investments since privatization of the formerly state-owned telecommunications company</assessment>
			<domestic>since privatization, access to fixed-line and mobile-cellular services has improved but teledensity still lags behind other Central American countries; fixed-line teledensity roughly 5 per 100 persons; mobile-cellular telephone subscribership is increasing and reached 55 per 100 persons in 2009; connected to Central American Microwave System</domestic>
			<international>country code - 505; the Americas Region Caribbean Ring System (ARCOS-1) fiber optic submarine cable provides connectivity to South and Central America, parts of the Caribbean, and the US; satellite earth stations - 1 Intersputnik (Atlantic Ocean region) and 1 Intelsat (Atlantic Ocean) (2009)</international>
			<land-lines>255000</land-lines>
			<mobile>3204000</mobile>
		</telephones>
		<broadcast>multiple privately-owned terrestrial television networks, supplemented by cable TV in most urban areas; of more than 100 radio broadcast stations, nearly all are privately owned; Radio Nicaragua is government-owned and Radio Sandino is controlled by the Sandinista National Liberation Front (FSLN) (2007)</broadcast>
		<internet>
			<tld>.ni</tld>
			<hosts>157162</hosts>
			<users>199800</users>
		</internet>
	</communications>
	<transport>
		<airports>
			<total>143</total>
			<paved>
				<altitude min="*" max="*"></altitude>
				<altitude min="3047m" max="*"></altitude>
				<altitude min="2438m" max="3047m">3</altitude>
				<altitude min="1524m" max="2437m">2</altitude>
				<altitude min="914m" max="1524m">3</altitude>
				<altitude min="*" max="914m">3</altitude>
			</paved>
		</airports>
		<ports-and-terminals>Bluefields, Corinto</ports-and-terminals>
	</transport>
	<military>
		<branches>National Army of Nicaragua (Ejercito Nacional de Nicaragua, ENN; includes Navy, Air Force) (2010)</branches>
		<manpower>
			<population-available>
				<male>1452</male>
				<female>1552</female>
			</population-available>
			<fit-for-service>
				<male>1227</male>
				<female>1335</female>
			</fit-for-service>
			<reaching-maturity>
				<male>69093</male>
				<female>67522</female>
			</reaching-maturity>
			<notes></notes>
		</manpower>
	</military>
	<issues>
		<disputes>memorials and countermemorials were filed by the parties in Nicaragua's 1999 and 2001 proceedings against Honduras and Colombia at the ICJ over the maritime boundary and territorial claims in the western Caribbean Sea, final public hearings are scheduled for 2007; the 1992 ICJ ruling for El Salvador and Honduras advised a tripartite resolution to establish a maritime boundary in the Gulf of Fonseca, which considers Honduran access to the Pacific; legal dispute over navigational rights of San Juan River on border with Costa Rica</disputes>
		<drugs>transshipment point for cocaine destined for the US and transshipment point for arms-for-drugs dealing</drugs>
	</issues>
</country>