<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<country>
	<code>ri</code>
	<name>Serbia</name>
	<region>Europe</region>
	<background>The Kingdom of Serbs, Croats, and Slovenes was formed in 1918; its name was changed to Yugoslavia in 1929. Various paramilitary bands resisted Nazi Germany's occupation and division of Yugoslavia from 1941 to 1945, but fought each other and ethnic opponents as much as the invaders. The military and political movement headed by Josip &quot;TITO&quot; Broz (Partisans) took full control of Yugoslavia when German and Croatian separatist forces were defeated in 1945. Although Communist, TITO's new government and his successors (he died in 1980) managed to steer their own path between the Warsaw Pact nations and the West for the next four and a half decades. In 1989, Slobodan MILOSEVIC became president of the Republic of Serbia and his ultranationalist calls for Serbian domination led to the violent breakup of Yugoslavia along ethnic lines. In 1991, Croatia, Slovenia, and Macedonia declared independence, followed by Bosnia in 1992. The remaining republics of Serbia and Montenegro declared a new Federal Republic of Yugoslavia (FRY) in April 1992 and under MILOSEVIC's leadership, Serbia led various military campaigns to unite ethnic Serbs in neighboring republics into a &quot;Greater Serbia.&quot; These actions were ultimately unsuccessful and led to the signing of the Dayton Peace Accords in 1995. MILOSEVIC retained control over Serbia and eventually became president of the FRY in 1997. In 1998, an ethnic Albanian insurgency in the formerly autonomous Serbian province of Kosovo provoked a Serbian counterinsurgency campaign that resulted in massacres and massive expulsions of ethnic Albanians living in Kosovo. The MILOSEVIC government's rejection of a proposed international settlement led to NATO's bombing of Serbia in the spring of 1999, to the withdrawal of Serbian military and police forces from Kosovo in June 1999, and to the stationing of a NATO-led force in Kosovo to provide a safe and secure environment for the region's ethnic communities. FRY elections in late 2000 led to the ouster of MILOSEVIC and the installation of democratic government. In 2003, the FRY became Serbia and Montenegro, a loose federation of the two republics. Widespread violence predominantly targeting ethnic Serbs in Kosovo in March 2004 caused the international community to open negotiations on the future status of Kosovo in January 2006. In June 2006, Montenegro seceded from the federation and declared itself an independent nation. Serbia subsequently gave notice that it was the successor state to the union of Serbia and Montenegro. In February 2008, after nearly two years of inconclusive negotiations, the UN-administered province of Kosovo declared itself independent of Serbia - an action Serbia refuses to recognize. At Serbia's request, the UN General Assembly (UNGA) in October 2008 sought an advisory opinion from the International Court of Justice (ICJ) on whether Kosovo's unilateral declaration of independence was in accordance with international law. In a ruling considered unfavorable to Serbia, the ICJ issued an advisory opinion in July 2010 stating that international law did not prohibit declarations of independence. In late 2010, Serbia agreed to an EU-drafted UNGA Resolution acknowledging the ICJ's decision and calling for a new round of talks between Serbia and Kosovo.</background>
	<geo>
		<note>controls one of the major land routes from Western Europe to Turkey and the Near East</note>
		<location>
			<desc>Southeastern Europe, between Macedonia and Hungary</desc>
			<coordinates>TO DO</coordinates>
		</location>
		<area>
			<total unit="sq km">77474</total>
			<land unit="sq km">77474</land>
			<water unit="sq km">0</water>
			<comparison>slightly smaller than South Carolina</comparison>
		</area>
		<boundaries>
			<borders unit=""></borders>
			<coastline unit="km">0</coastline>
		</boundaries>
		<maritime-claims>
			<territorial unit=""></territorial>
			<contiguous unit=""></contiguous>
			<economic unit=""></economic>
			<continental-shelf></continental-shelf>
		</maritime-claims>
		<climate>in the north, continental climate (cold winters and hot, humid summers with well distributed rainfall); in other parts, continental and Mediterranean climate (relatively cold winters with heavy snowfall and hot, dry summers and autumns)</climate>
		<terrain>extremely varied; to the north, rich fertile plains; to the east, limestone ranges and basins; to the southeast, ancient mountains and hills</terrain>
		<elevation>
			<high>Midzor 2,169 m</high>
			<low>Danube and Timok Rivers 35 m</low>
		</elevation>
		<resources>oil, gas, coal, iron ore, copper, zinc, antimony, chromite, gold, silver, magnesium, pyrite, limestone, marble, salt, arable land</resources>
		<land-use>
			<arable unit=""></arable>
			<crops unit=""></crops>
			<other unit=""></other>
		</land-use>
		<hazards>destructive earthquakes</hazards>
		<issues>air pollution around Belgrade and other industrial cities; water pollution from industrial wastes dumped into the Sava which flows into the Danube</issues>
		<water>
			<irrigated-land unit="sq km">890</irrigated-land>
			<renewable-water unit=""></renewable-water>
			<freshwater-withdrawal>
				<total unit=""></total>
				<per-capita unit=""></per-capita>
			</freshwater-withdrawal>
		</water>
		<!--
"geo": {

		"Natural hazards": "flooding is a threat in some areas of the country (e.g., parts of Jutland, along the southern coast of the island of Lolland) that are protected from the sea by a system of dikes",
		"Environment - current issues": "air pollution, principally from vehicle and power plant emissions; nitrogen and phosphorus pollution of the North Sea; drinking and surface water becoming polluted from animal wastes and pesticides",
		"Environment - international agreements": {
			"party to:": "Air Pollution, Air Pollution-Nitrogen Oxides, Air Pollution-Persistent Organic Pollutants, Air Pollution-Sulfur 85, Air Pollution-Sulfur 94, Air Pollution-Volatile Organic Compounds, Antarctic Treaty, Biodiversity, Climate Change, Climate Change-Kyoto Protocol, Desertification, Endangered Species, Environmental Modification, Hazardous Wastes, Law of the Sea, Marine Dumping, Marine Life Conservation, Ozone Layer Protection, Ship Pollution, Tropical Timber 83, Tropical Timber 94, Wetlands, Whaling",
			"signed, but not ratified:": "none of the selected agreements"
		},
		"Geography - note": "controls Danish Straits (Skagerrak and Kattegat) linking Baltic and North Seas; about one-quarter of the population lives in greater Copenhagen"

		-->
	</geo>
	<people>
		<population>
			<total>7310</total>
			<birth unit="births/1,000 population">9.19</birth>
			<death unit="deaths/1,000 population">13.85</birth>
			<migration unit="migrant(s)/1,000 population">0</migration>
			<growth unit=""></growth>
		</population>
		<age-distribution unit="percent">
			<group min="0" max="14">15.1</group>
			<group min="15" max="64">68.5</group>
			<group min="65"></group>
		</age-distribution>
		<median-age unit="years">
			<total>41.3</total>
			<male>39.6</male>
			<female>43.1</female>
		</median-age>
		<urbanization>
			<urban unit="% of total population">56</urban>
			<rate unit="% annual rate of change">0.6</urban>
			<cities>BELGRADE (capital) 1.115 million (2009)</cities>
		</urbanization>
		<sex unit="male(s)/female">
			<group name="at birth" max="0">1.065</group>
			<group name="0 to 14" min="0" max="14">1.07</group>
			<group name="15 to 64" min="15" max="64">1</group>
			<group name="65 and over" min="65" max="0"></group>
			<group name="total" min="0">0.95</group>
		</sex>
		<infant-mortality>
			<total unit="deaths/1,000 live births">6.52</total>
			<male unit="deaths/1,000 live births">7.53</male>
			<female unit="deaths/1,000 live births">5.45</female>
		</infant-mortality>
		<life-expectancy-at-birth>
			<total unit="years">74.32</total>
			<male unit="years">71.49</male>
			<female unit="years">77.34</female>
		</life-expectancy-at-birth>
		<fertility-rate unit="1.4">children born/woman</fertility-rate>
		<hiv>
			<prevalence>[object Object]</prevalence>
			<total>6400</total>
			<deaths>fewer than 100 (2009 est.)</deaths>
		</hiv>
		<infectious-disease risk="intermediate">
			<food-or-waterborne>bacterial diarrhea</food-or-waterborne>
			<vectorborne></vectorborne>
			<water-contact></water-contact>
		</infectious-disease>
		<drinking-water-source>[object Object]</drinking-water-source>
		<sanitation-access>[object Object]</sanitation-access>
		<nationality>
			<noun>Serb(s)</noun>
			<adjective>Serbian</adjective>
		</nationality>
		<ethnic-groups>Serb 82.9%, Hungarian 3.9%, Romany (Gypsy) 1.4%, Yugoslavs 1.1%, Bosniaks 1.8%, Montenegrin 0.9%, other 8% (2002 census)</ethnic-groups>
		<religions>Serbian Orthodox 85%, Catholic 5.5%, Protestant 1.1%, Muslim 3.2%, unspecified 2.6%, other, unknown, or atheist 2.6% (2002 census)</religions>
		<languages>[object Object]</languages>
		<literacy>
			<definition>age 15 and over can read and write</definition>
			<total unit="%">96.4</total>
			<male unit="%">98.9</male>
			<female unit="%">94.1</female>
		</literacy>
		<school-expectancy unit="years">14</school-expectancy>
		<education-expenditure unit="% of GDP">4.7</school-expectancy>
	</people>
	<government>
		<country-name>
			<long>Republic of Serbia</long>
			<short>Serbia</short>
		</country-name>
		<dependency></dependency>
		<government-type>republic</government-type>
		<capital>
			<name>Belgrade (Beograd)</name>
			<coordinates>44° 50' N, 20° 30' E</coordinates>
			<time-difference>UTC+1 (6 hours ahead of Washington, DC during Standard Time)</time-difference>
		</capital>
		<administrative-divisions>[object Object]</administrative-divisions>
		<independence>5 June 2006 (from Serbia and Montenegro)</independence>
		<national-holiday>National Day, 15 February</national-holiday>
		<legal-system>civil law system</legal-system>
		<suffrage>18 years of age; universal</suffrage>
		<executive>
			<head-of-state>President Boris TADIC (since 11 July 2004)</head-of-state>
			<head-of-government>Prime Minister Mirko CVETKOVIC (since 7 July 2008)</head-of-government>
			<cabinet>Republican Ministries act as cabinet</cabinet>
			<elections>president elected by direct vote for a five-year term (eligible for a second term); election last held on 3 February 2008 (next to be held in 2013); prime minister elected by the National Assembly</elections>
			<election-results>Boris TADIC elected president in the second round of voting; Boris TADIC received 51.2% of the vote and Tomislav NIKOLIC 48.8%</election-results>
		</executive>
		<legislative>
			<description>unicameral National Assembly (250 seats; deputies elected according to party lists to serve four-year terms)</description>
			<elections>last held on 11 May 2008 (next to be held in May 2012)</elections>
			<election-results>percent of vote by party - For a European Serbia coalition 38.4%, SRS 29.5%, DSS-NS 11.6%, SPS-led coalition 7.6%, LPD 5.2%, other 7.7%; seats by party - For a European Serbia coalition 102, SRS 57, DSS-NS 30, SNS 21, SPS-led coalition 20, LDP 13, other 7</election-results>
		</legislative>
		<judicial>courts of general jurisdiction (municipal courts, district courts, Appellate Courts, the Supreme Court of Cassation); courts of special jurisdiction (commercial courts, the High Commercial Court, the High Magistrates Court, the Administrative Court)</judicial>
		<parties>Coalition for Sandzak or KZS [Sulejman UGLJANIN]; Democratic Party or DS [Boris TADIC]; Democratic Party of Albanians or PDSh [Ragmi MUSTAFA]; Democratic Party of Serbia or DSS [Vojislav KOSTUNICA]; Democratic Union of the Valley or BDL [Skender DESTANI]; Force of Serbia Movement or PSS [Bogoljub KARIC]; G17 Plus [Mladjan DINKIC]; League of Social Democrats of Vojvodina or LSV [Nenad CANAK]; League of Vojvodina Hungarians or SVM [Istvan PASTOR]; Liberal Democratic Party or LDP [Cedomir JOVANOVIC]; Movement for Democratic Progress or LPD [Jonuz MUSLIU]; New Serbia or NS [Velimir ILIC]; Party of Democratic Action or PVD [Riza HALIMI]; Party of United Pensioners of Serbia or PUPS [Jovan KRKOBABIC]; People's Party or NS [Maja GOJKOVIC]; Roma Party or RP [Srdjan SAJN]; Sandzak Democratic Party or SDP [Resad HODZIC]; Serbian Progressive Party or SNS [Tomislav NIKOLIC]; Serbian Radical Party or SRS [Vojislav SESELJ (currently on trial at The Hague), with Dragan TODOROVIC as acting leader]; Serbian Renewal Movement or SPO [Vuk DRASKOVIC]; Social Democratic Party of Serbia or SDPS [Rasim LJAJIC]; Socialist Party of Serbia or SPS [Ivica DACIC]; Union of Roma of Serbia or URS [Rajko DJURIC]; United Serbia or JS [Dragan &quot;Palma&quot; MARKOVIC]</parties>
		<pressure-groups>TO DO</pressure-groups>
		<membership>BIS, BSEC, CE, CEI, EAPC, EBRD, FAO, G-9, IAEA, IBRD, ICAO, ICC, ICRM, IDA, IFC, IFRCS, IHO, ILO, IMF, IMO, IMSO, Interpol, IOC, IOM, IPU, ISO, ITSO, ITU, ITUC, MIGA, MONUSCO, NAM (observer), OAS (observer), OIF (observer), OPCW, OSCE, PCA, PFP, SECI, UN, UNCTAD, UNESCO, UNFICYP, UNHCR, UNIDO, UNMIL, UNOCI, UNWTO, UPU, WCO, WHO, WIPO, WMO, WTO (observer)</membership>
		<representation-in-usa>
			<chief>Ambassador Vladimir PETROVIC</chief>
			<chancery>2134 Kalorama Road NW, Washington, DC 20008</chancery>
			<telephone>[1] (202) 332-0333</telephone>
			<FAX>[1] (202) 332-3933</FAX>
			<consulates>Chicago, New York</consulates>
		</representation-in-usa>
		<representation-from-usa>
			<chief>Ambassador Mary WARLICK</chief>
			<embassy>Kneza Milosa 50, 11000 Belgrade</embassy>
			<mailing-address>5070 Belgrade Place, Washington, DC 20521-5070</mailing-address>
			<telephone>[381] (11) 361-9344</telephone>
			<FAX>[381] (11) 361-8230</FAX>
		</representation-from-usa>
		<flag>[object Object]</flag>
		<anthem>
			<name>&quot;Boze pravde&quot; (God of Justice)</name>
			<by>Jovan DORDEVIC/Davorin JENKO</by>
		</anthem>
	</government>
	<economy>
		<overview>MILOSEVIC-era mismanagement of the economy, an extended period of international economic sanctions, and the damage to Yugoslavia's infrastructure and industry during the NATO airstrikes in 1999 left the economy only half the size it was in 1990. After the ousting of former Federal Yugoslav President MILOSEVIC in September 2000, the Democratic Opposition of Serbia (DOS) coalition government implemented stabilization measures and embarked on a market reform program. After renewing its membership in the IMF in December 2000, Yugoslavia continued to reintegrate into the international community by rejoining the World Bank (IBRD) and the European Bank for Reconstruction and Development (EBRD). Belgrade has made progress in trade liberalization and enterprise restructuring and privatization, including telecommunications and small- and medium-size firms. It has made some progress towards EU membership, signing a Stabilization and Association Agreement with Brussels in May 2008, and with full implementation of the Interim Trade Agreement with the EU in February 2010. Serbia is also pursuing membership in the World Trade Organization. Structural economic reforms needed to ensure the country's long-term viability have largely stalled since the onset of the global financial crisis. Serbia, however, is slowly recovering from the crisis. Economic growth in 2010 was a modest 1.7%, following a 3.1% contraction in 2009, but exports rose by over 16% and manufacturing output increased 3.2%. High unemployment and stagnant household incomes are ongoing political and economic problems. Serbia signed an augmented $4 billion Stand By Arrangement with the IMF in May 2009 that expires in April 2011. IMF conditions on Serbia constrain the use of stimulus efforts to revive the economy, while Serbia's concerns about inflation and exchange rate stability preclude the use of expansionary monetary policy. Serbia adopted a new long-term economic growth plan in 2010 that calls for a quadrupling of exports over ten years and heavy investments in basic infrastructure. Serbia is still a transitional economy with unfinished privatization and incomplete structural reforms. Major challenges ahead include: high government expenditures for salaries, pensions and unemployment; a growing need for new government borrowing; rising public and private foreign debt; and stagnant levels of foreign direct investment. Privatization revenues have fallen precipitously in recent years, while a high percentage of economic activity remains in the hands of the state. Other serious challenges include an inefficient judicial system, high levels of corruption, and an aging population. Factors favorable to Serbia's economic growth include a strategic location, a relatively inexpensive and skilled labor force, and a generous package of incentives for foreign investments.</overview>
		<gdp>
			<purchasing-power-parity></purchasing-power-parity>
			<official-exchange-rate>38710000000</official-exchange-rate>
			<real-growth-rate unit="%">1.8</real-growth-rate>
			<per-capita></per-capita>
			<sector unit="%">
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
		</gdp>
		<labour>
			<force>2950000</force>
			<sector>
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
			<unemployment unit="%">19.2</unemployment>
		</labour>
		<poverty>[object Object]</poverty>
		<household-income>TO DO</household-income>
		<budget>
			<revenue unit="USD"></revenue>
			<expenditure unit="USD"></expenditure>
		</budget>
		<public-debt unit="% of GDP">41.5</public-debt>
		<consumer-inflation unit="%">10.3</consumer-inflation>
		<central-bank-discount-rate unit="%">12</central-bank-discount-rate>
		<commercial-prime-lending-rate unit="%">13.28</commercial-prime-lending-rate>
		<narrow-money-stock unit="USD">3060000000</narrow-money-stock>
		<broad-money-stock unit="USD">17680000000</broad-money-stock>
		<domestic-credit-stock unit="USD">20030000000</domestic-credit-stock>
		<agriculture-products>wheat, maize, sugar beets, sunflower, raspberries; beef, pork, milk</agriculture-products>
		<industries>base metals, furniture, food processing, machinery, chemicals, sugar, tires, clothes, pharmaceuticals</industries>
		<industrial-production-growth>[object Object]</industrial-production-growth>
		<electricity unit="kWh">
			<production>35900000000</production>
			<consumption>34100000000</consumption>
			<exports>1300000000</exports>
			<imports>770000000</imports>
		</electricity>
		<oil>
			<production unit="bbl/day">11400</production>
			<consumption unit="bbl/day">90000</consumption>
			<exports unit="bbl/day">5045</exports>
			<imports unit="bbl/day">78600</imports>
			<reserves unit="bbl">77500000</reserves>
		</oil>
		<natural-gas>
			<production unit="cu m">356000000</production>
			<consumption unit="cu m">2350000000</consumption>
			<exports unit="cu m">0</exports>
			<imports unit="cu m">2000000000</imports>
			<reserves unit="cu m">48140000000</reserves>
		</natural-gas>
		<exports>
			<total unit="USD"></total>
			<commodities>iron and steel, rubber, clothes, wheat, fruit and vegetables, nonferrous metals, electric appliances, metal products, weapons and ammunition</commodities>
			<partners>Italy 11.5%, Bosnia and Herzegovina 11.2%, Germany 10.5%, Montenegro 8.4%, Romania 6.3%, Russia 5.4%, Macedonia 4.9%, Slovenia 4.4% (2010 est.)</partners>
		</exports>
		<imports>
			<total unit="USD">15780000000</total>
			<commodities></commodities>
			<partners>Russia 12.8%, Germany 10.6%, Italy 8.5%, China 7.2%, Hungary 4.9% (2010 est.)</partners>
		</imports>
		<external-debt unit="USD">30900000000</external-debt>
		<exchange-rates>Serbian dinars (RSD) per US dollar -</exchange-rates>
	</economy>
	<communications>
		<telephones>
			<assessment>replacements of, and upgrades to, telecommunications equipment damaged during the 1999 war has resulted in a modern telecommunications system more than 95% digitalized in 2009</assessment>
			<domestic>wireless service, available through multiple providers with national coverage, is growing very rapidly; best telecommunications services are centered in urban centers; 3G mobile network launched in 2007</domestic>
			<international>country code - 381 (2009)</international>
			<land-lines>3106000</land-lines>
			<mobile>9912000</mobile>
		</telephones>
		<broadcast></broadcast>
		<internet>
			<tld>.rs</tld>
			<hosts>528253</hosts>
			<users>4107000</users>
		</internet>
	</communications>
	<transport>
		<airports>
			<total>29</total>
			<paved>
				<altitude min="*" max="*"></altitude>
				<altitude min="3047m" max="*">2</altitude>
				<altitude min="2438m" max="3047m">3</altitude>
				<altitude min="1524m" max="2437m">3</altitude>
				<altitude min="914m" max="1524m">3</altitude>
				<altitude min="*" max="914m"></altitude>
			</paved>
		</airports>
		<ports-and-terminals></ports-and-terminals>
	</transport>
	<military>
		<branches>Serbian Armed Forces (Vojska Srbije, VS): Land Forces Command (includes Riverine Component, consisting of a river flotilla on the Danube), Air and Air Defense Forces Command (2010)</branches>
		<manpower>
			<population-available>
				<male></male>
				<female></female>
			</population-available>
			<fit-for-service>
				<male>1395</male>
				<female>1356</female>
			</fit-for-service>
			<reaching-maturity>
				<male>43945</male>
				<female>41080</female>
			</reaching-maturity>
			<notes></notes>
		</manpower>
	</military>
	<issues>
		<disputes>Serbia with several other states protest the U.S. and other states' recognition of Kosovo's declaring itself as a sovereign and independent state in February 2008; ethnic Serbian municipalities along Kosovo's northern border challenge final status of Kosovo-Serbia boundary; several thousand NATO-led KFOR peacekeepers under UNMIK authority continue to keep the peace within Kosovo between the ethnic Albanian majority and the Serb minority in Kosovo; Serbia delimited about half of the boundary with Bosnia and Herzegovina, but sections along the Drina River remain in dispute</disputes>
		<drugs>transshipment point for Southwest Asian heroin moving to Western Europe on the Balkan route; economy vulnerable to money laundering</drugs>
	</issues>
</country>