<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<country>
	<code>so</code>
	<name>Somalia</name>
	<region>Africa</region>
	<background>Britain withdrew from British Somaliland in 1960 to allow its protectorate to join with Italian Somaliland and form the new nation of Somalia. In 1969, a coup headed by Mohamed SIAD Barre ushered in an authoritarian socialist rule characterized by the persecution, jailing and torture of political opponents and dissidents. After the regime's collapse early in 1991, Somalia descended into turmoil, factional fighting, and anarchy. In May 1991, northern clans declared an independent Republic of Somaliland that now includes the administrative regions of Awdal, Woqooyi Galbeed, Togdheer, Sanaag, and Sool. Although not recognized by any government, this entity has maintained a stable existence and continues efforts to establish a constitutional democracy, including holding municipal, parliamentary, and presidential elections. The regions of Bari, Nugaal, and northern Mudug comprise a neighboring semi-autonomous state of Puntland, which has been self-governing since 1998 but does not aim at independence; it has also made strides toward reconstructing a legitimate, representative government but has suffered some civil strife. Puntland disputes its border with Somaliland as it also claims portions of eastern Sool and Sanaag. Beginning in 1993, a two-year UN humanitarian effort (primarily in the south) was able to alleviate famine conditions, but when the UN withdrew in 1995, having suffered significant casualties, order still had not been restored. In 2000, the Somalia National Peace Conference (SNPC) held in Djibouti resulted in the formation of an interim government, known as the Transitional National Government (TNG). When the TNG failed to establish adequate security or governing institutions, the Government of Kenya, under the auspices of the Intergovernmental Authority on Development (IGAD), led a subsequent peace process that concluded in October 2004 with the election of Abdullahi YUSUF Ahmed as President of a second interim government, known as the Transitional Federal Government (TFG) of the Somali Republic. The TFG included a 275-member parliamentary body, known as the Transitional Federal Parliament (TFP). President YUSUF resigned late in 2008 while United Nations-sponsored talks between the TFG and the opposition Alliance for the Re-Liberation of Somalia (ARS) were underway in Djibouti. In January 2009, following the creation of a TFG-ARS unity government, Ethiopian military forces, which had entered Somalia in December 2006 to support the TFG in the face of advances by the opposition Islamic Courts Union (ICU), withdrew from the country. The TFP was increased to 550 seats with the addition of 200 ARS and 75 civil society members of parliament. The expanded parliament elected Sheikh SHARIF Sheikh Ahmed, the former CIC and ARS chairman as president on 31 January 2009, in Djibouti. Subsequently, President SHARIF appointed Omar Abdirashid ali SHARMARKE, son of a former president of Somalia, as prime minister on 13 February 2009. SHARMARKE resigned in September 2010 and was replaced by Mohamed Abdullahi MOHAMED, aka Farmajo, a dual US-Somali citizen who lived in the United States from 1985 until his return to Somalia in October 2010. The creation of the TFG was based on the Transitional Federal Charter (TFC), which outlines a five-year mandate leading to the establishment of a new Somali constitution and a transition to a representative government following national elections. However, in January 2009 the TFP amended the TFC to extend TFG's mandate until 2011.</background>
	<geo>
		<note>strategic location on Horn of Africa along southern approaches to Bab el Mandeb and route through Red Sea and Suez Canal</note>
		<location>
			<desc>Eastern Africa, bordering the Gulf of Aden and the Indian Ocean, east of Ethiopia</desc>
			<coordinates>TO DO</coordinates>
		</location>
		<area>
			<total unit="sq km">637657</total>
			<land unit="sq km">627337</land>
			<water unit="sq km">10320</water>
			<comparison>slightly smaller than Texas</comparison>
		</area>
		<boundaries>
			<borders unit=""></borders>
			<coastline unit="km">3025</coastline>
		</boundaries>
		<maritime-claims>
			<territorial unit="nm">200</territorial>
			<contiguous unit=""></contiguous>
			<economic unit=""></economic>
			<continental-shelf></continental-shelf>
		</maritime-claims>
		<climate>principally desert; northeast monsoon (December to February), moderate temperatures in north and hot in south; southwest monsoon (May to October), torrid in the north and hot in the south, irregular rainfall, hot and humid periods (tangambili) between monsoons</climate>
		<terrain>mostly flat to undulating plateau rising to hills in north</terrain>
		<elevation>
			<high>Shimbiris 2,416 m</high>
			<low>Indian Ocean 0 m</low>
		</elevation>
		<resources>uranium and largely unexploited reserves of iron ore, tin, gypsum, bauxite, copper, salt, natural gas, likely oil reserves</resources>
		<land-use>
			<arable unit="%">1.64</arable>
			<crops unit="%">0.04</crops>
			<other unit="%">98.32</other>
		</land-use>
		<hazards>recurring droughts; frequent dust storms over eastern plains in summer; floods during rainy season</hazards>
		<issues>famine; use of contaminated water contributes to human health problems; deforestation; overgrazing; soil erosion; desertification</issues>
		<water>
			<irrigated-land unit="sq km">2000</irrigated-land>
			<renewable-water unit="cu km">15.7</renewable-water>
			<freshwater-withdrawal>
				<total unit="cu km/yr">3.29</total>
				<per-capita unit="cu m/yr">400</per-capita>
			</freshwater-withdrawal>
		</water>
		<!--
"geo": {

		"Natural hazards": "flooding is a threat in some areas of the country (e.g., parts of Jutland, along the southern coast of the island of Lolland) that are protected from the sea by a system of dikes",
		"Environment - current issues": "air pollution, principally from vehicle and power plant emissions; nitrogen and phosphorus pollution of the North Sea; drinking and surface water becoming polluted from animal wastes and pesticides",
		"Environment - international agreements": {
			"party to:": "Air Pollution, Air Pollution-Nitrogen Oxides, Air Pollution-Persistent Organic Pollutants, Air Pollution-Sulfur 85, Air Pollution-Sulfur 94, Air Pollution-Volatile Organic Compounds, Antarctic Treaty, Biodiversity, Climate Change, Climate Change-Kyoto Protocol, Desertification, Endangered Species, Environmental Modification, Hazardous Wastes, Law of the Sea, Marine Dumping, Marine Life Conservation, Ozone Layer Protection, Ship Pollution, Tropical Timber 83, Tropical Timber 94, Wetlands, Whaling",
			"signed, but not ratified:": "none of the selected agreements"
		},
		"Geography - note": "controls Danish Straits (Skagerrak and Kattegat) linking Baltic and North Seas; about one-quarter of the population lives in greater Copenhagen"

		-->
	</geo>
	<people>
		<population>
			<total>9925</total>
			<birth unit="births/1,000 population">42.71</birth>
			<death unit="deaths/1,000 population">14.87</birth>
			<migration unit=""></migration>
			<growth unit="%">1.603</growth>
		</population>
		<age-distribution unit="percent">
			<group min="0" max="14">44.7</group>
			<group min="15" max="64">52.9</group>
			<group min="65"></group>
		</age-distribution>
		<median-age unit="years">
			<total>17.8</total>
			<male>17.8</male>
			<female>17.7</female>
		</median-age>
		<urbanization>
			<urban unit="% of total population">37</urban>
			<rate unit="% annual rate of change">4.1</urban>
			<cities>MOGADISHU (capital) 1.353 million (2009)</cities>
		</urbanization>
		<sex unit="male(s)/female">
			<group name="at birth" max="0">1.03</group>
			<group name="0 to 14" min="0" max="14">1</group>
			<group name="15 to 64" min="15" max="64">1</group>
			<group name="65 and over" min="65" max="0">0.7</group>
			<group name="total" min="0">1</group>
		</sex>
		<infant-mortality>
			<total unit="deaths/1,000 live births">105.56</total>
			<male unit="deaths/1,000 live births">114.53</male>
			<female unit="deaths/1,000 live births">96.31</female>
		</infant-mortality>
		<life-expectancy-at-birth>
			<total unit="years">50.4</total>
			<male unit="years">48.49</male>
			<female unit="years">52.37</female>
		</life-expectancy-at-birth>
		<fertility-rate unit="6.35">children born/woman</fertility-rate>
		<hiv>
			<prevalence>[object Object]</prevalence>
			<total>34000</total>
			<deaths>1600</deaths>
		</hiv>
		<infectious-disease risk="high">
			<food-or-waterborne>bacterial and protozoal diarrhea, hepatitis A and E, and typhoid fever</food-or-waterborne>
			<vectorborne>dengue fever, malaria, and Rift Valley fever</vectorborne>
			<water-contact></water-contact>
		</infectious-disease>
		<drinking-water-source>[object Object]</drinking-water-source>
		<sanitation-access>[object Object]</sanitation-access>
		<nationality>
			<noun>Somali(s)</noun>
			<adjective>Somali</adjective>
		</nationality>
		<ethnic-groups>Somali 85%, Bantu and other non-Somali 15% (including 30,000 Arabs)</ethnic-groups>
		<religions>Sunni Muslim</religions>
		<languages>Somali (official), Arabic, Italian, English</languages>
		<literacy>
			<definition>age 15 and over can read and write</definition>
			<total unit="%">37.8</total>
			<male unit="%">49.7</male>
			<female unit="%">25.8</female>
		</literacy>
		<school-expectancy unit="years">3</school-expectancy>
		<education-expenditure unit=""></school-expectancy>
	</people>
	<government>
		<country-name>
			<long>none</long>
			<short>Somalia</short>
		</country-name>
		<dependency></dependency>
		<government-type>no permanent national government; transitional, parliamentary federal government</government-type>
		<capital>
			<name>Mogadishu</name>
			<coordinates>2° 4' N, 45° 22' E</coordinates>
			<time-difference>UTC+3 (8 hours ahead of Washington, DC during Standard Time)</time-difference>
		</capital>
		<administrative-divisions>18 regions (plural - NA, singular - gobolka); Awdal, Bakool, Banaadir, Bari, Bay, Galguduud, Gedo, Hiiraan, Jubbada Dhexe (Middle Jubba), Jubbada Hoose (Lower Jubba), Mudug, Nugaal, Sanaag, Shabeellaha Dhexe (Middle Shabeelle), Shabeellaha Hoose (Lower Shabeelle), Sool, Togdheer, Woqooyi Galbeed</administrative-divisions>
		<independence>1 July 1960 (from a merger of British Somaliland that became independent from the UK on 26 June 1960 and Italian Somaliland that became independent from the Italian-administered UN trusteeship on 1 July 1960 to form the Somali Republic)</independence>
		<national-holiday>Foundation of the Somali Republic, 1 July (1960); note - 26 June (1960) in Somaliland</national-holiday>
		<legal-system>mixed legal system of civil law, Islamic law, and customary law (referred to as Xeer)</legal-system>
		<suffrage>18 years of age; universal</suffrage>
		<executive>
			<head-of-state>Transitional Federal President Sheikh SHARIF Sheikh Ahmed (since 31 January 2009); note - a transitional governing entity with a five-year mandate, known as the Transitional Federal Institutions (TFIs), was established in October 2004; the TFIs relocated to Somalia in June 2004; in 2009, the TFIs were given a two-year extension to October 2011</head-of-state>
			<head-of-government>Prime Minister Mohamed Abdullahi Mohamed FARMAJO (since 1 November 2010)</head-of-government>
			<cabinet>Cabinet appointed by the prime minister and approved by the Transitional Federal Assembly</cabinet>
			<elections></elections>
			<election-results>Sheikh SHARIF Sheikh Ahmed elected president by the expanded Transitional Federal Assembly in Djibouti</election-results>
		</executive>
		<legislative>
			<description>unicameral National Assembly</description>
			<elections></elections>
			<election-results></election-results>
		</legislative>
		<judicial>following the breakdown of the central government, most regions have reverted to local forms of conflict resolution, either secular, traditional Somali customary law, or sharia (Islamic) law with a provision for appeal of all sentences</judicial>
		<parties>none</parties>
		<pressure-groups>TO DO</pressure-groups>
		<membership>ACP, AfDB, AFESD, AMF, AU, CAEU, FAO, G-77, IBRD, ICAO, ICRM, IDA, IDB, IFAD, IFC, IFRCS, IGAD, ILO, IMF, IMO, Interpol, IOC, IOM, ITSO, ITU, LAS, NAM, OIC, UN, UNCTAD, UNESCO, UNHCR, UNIDO, UPU, WFTU, WHO, WIPO, WMO</membership>
		<representation-in-usa>
			<chief></chief>
			<chancery></chancery>
			<telephone></telephone>
			<FAX></FAX>
			<consulates></consulates>
		</representation-in-usa>
		<representation-from-usa>
			<chief></chief>
			<embassy></embassy>
			<mailing-address></mailing-address>
			<telephone></telephone>
			<FAX></FAX>
		</representation-from-usa>
		<flag>light blue with a large white five-pointed star in the center; the blue field was originally influenced by the flag of the UN, but today is said to denote the sky and the neighboring Indian Ocean; the five points of the star represent the five regions in the horn of Africa that are inhabited by Somali people: the former British Somaliland and Italian Somaliland (which together make up Somalia), Djibouti, Ogaden (Ethiopia), and the Northern Frontier District (Kenya)</flag>
		<anthem>
			<name>&quot;Soomaaliyeey toosoo&quot; (Somalia Wake Up)</name>
			<by>Ali Mire AWALE and Yuusuf Xaaji Aadan Cilmi QABILLE</by>
		</anthem>
	</government>
	<economy>
		<overview>Despite the lack of effective national governance, Somalia has maintained a healthy informal economy, largely based on livestock, remittance/money transfer companies, and telecommunications. Agriculture is the most important sector with livestock normally accounting for about 40% of GDP and more than 50% of export earnings. Nomads and semi-pastoralists, who are dependent upon livestock for their livelihood, make up a large portion of the population. Livestock, hides, fish, charcoal, and bananas are Somalia's principal exports, while sugar, sorghum, corn, qat, and machined goods are the principal imports. Somalia's small industrial sector, based on the processing of agricultural products, has largely been looted and the machinery sold as scrap metal. Somalia's service sector also has grown. Telecommunication firms provide wireless services in most major cities and offer the lowest international call rates on the continent. In the absence of a formal banking sector, money transfer/remittance services have sprouted throughout the country, handling up to $1.6 billion in remittances annually. Mogadishu's main market offers a variety of goods from food to the newest electronic gadgets. Hotels continue to operate and are supported with private-security militias. Due to armed attacks on and threats to humanitarian aid workers, the World Food Programme partially suspended its operations in southern Somalia in early January 2010 pending improvement in the security situation. Somalia's arrears to the IMF have continued to grow.</overview>
		<gdp>
			<purchasing-power-parity></purchasing-power-parity>
			<official-exchange-rate>2372000000</official-exchange-rate>
			<real-growth-rate unit="%">2.6</real-growth-rate>
			<per-capita></per-capita>
			<sector unit="%">
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
		</gdp>
		<labour>
			<force>3.447 million (few skilled laborers) (2007)</force>
			<sector>
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
			<unemployment unit=""></unemployment>
		</labour>
		<poverty>NA%</poverty>
		<household-income>TO DO</household-income>
		<budget>
			<revenue unit="USD"></revenue>
			<expenditure unit="USD"></expenditure>
		</budget>
		<public-debt unit=""></public-debt>
		<consumer-inflation unit="%"></consumer-inflation>
		<central-bank-discount-rate unit="%"></central-bank-discount-rate>
		<commercial-prime-lending-rate unit="%"></commercial-prime-lending-rate>
		<narrow-money-stock unit="USD"></narrow-money-stock>
		<broad-money-stock unit="USD"></broad-money-stock>
		<domestic-credit-stock unit="USD"></domestic-credit-stock>
		<agriculture-products>bananas, sorghum, corn, coconuts, rice, sugarcane, mangoes, sesame seeds, beans; cattle, sheep, goats; fish</agriculture-products>
		<industries>a few light industries, including sugar refining, textiles, wireless communication</industries>
		<industrial-production-growth>NA%</industrial-production-growth>
		<electricity unit="kWh">
			<production>280000000</production>
			<consumption>260399999.99999997</consumption>
			<exports>0</exports>
			<imports>0</imports>
		</electricity>
		<oil>
			<production unit="bbl/day">108.1</production>
			<consumption unit="bbl/day">5000</consumption>
			<exports unit="bbl/day">1475</exports>
			<imports unit="bbl/day">6387</imports>
			<reserves unit="bbl">0</reserves>
		</oil>
		<natural-gas>
			<production unit="cu m">0</production>
			<consumption unit="cu m">0</consumption>
			<exports unit="cu m">0</exports>
			<imports unit="cu m">0</imports>
			<reserves unit="cu m">5663000000</reserves>
		</natural-gas>
		<exports>
			<total unit="USD"></total>
			<commodities>livestock, bananas, hides, fish, charcoal, scrap metal</commodities>
			<partners>UAE 58.27%, Yemen 20.32%, Saudi Arabia 3.78% (2009)</partners>
		</exports>
		<imports>
			<total unit="USD">798000000</total>
			<commodities>manufactures, petroleum products, foodstuffs, construction materials, qat</commodities>
			<partners>Djibouti 30.84%, Kenya 8.06%, India 7.86%, China 6.97%, Brazil 6.59%, Yemen 4.97%, Oman 4.72%, UAE 4.6% (2009)</partners>
		</imports>
		<external-debt unit="USD">3000000000</external-debt>
		<exchange-rates>Somali shillings (SOS) per US dollar -</exchange-rates>
	</economy>
	<communications>
		<telephones>
			<assessment>the public telecommunications system was almost completely destroyed or dismantled during the civil war; private companies offer limited local fixed-line service and private wireless companies offer service in most major cities while charging the lowest international rates on the continent</assessment>
			<domestic>local cellular telephone systems have been established in Mogadishu and in several other population centers</domestic>
			<international>country code - 252; international connections are available from Mogadishu by satellite</international>
			<land-lines>100000</land-lines>
			<mobile>641000</mobile>
		</telephones>
		<broadcast>2 private TV stations rebroadcast Al-Jazeera and CNN; Somaliland has 1 government-operated TV station and Puntland has 1 private TV station; Radio Mogadishu operated by the transitional government; 1 SW and roughly 10 private FM radio stations broadcast in Mogadishu; several radio stations operate in central and southern regions; Somaliland has 1 government-operated radio station; Puntland has roughly a half dozen private radio stations; transmissions of at least 2 international broadcasters are available (2007)</broadcast>
		<internet>
			<tld>.so</tld>
			<hosts>3</hosts>
			<users>106000</users>
		</internet>
	</communications>
	<transport>
		<airports>
			<total>59</total>
			<paved>
				<altitude min="*" max="*"></altitude>
				<altitude min="3047m" max="*">4</altitude>
				<altitude min="2438m" max="3047m">2</altitude>
				<altitude min="1524m" max="2437m">1</altitude>
				<altitude min="914m" max="1524m"></altitude>
				<altitude min="*" max="914m"></altitude>
			</paved>
		</airports>
		<ports-and-terminals>Berbera, Kismaayo</ports-and-terminals>
	</transport>
	<military>
		<branches>National Security Force (NSF): Somali Army (2011)</branches>
		<manpower>
			<population-available>
				<male>2260</male>
				<female>2159</female>
			</population-available>
			<fit-for-service>
				<male>1331</male>
				<female>1357</female>
			</fit-for-service>
			<reaching-maturity>
				<male>101634</male>
				<female>101072</female>
			</reaching-maturity>
			<notes></notes>
		</manpower>
	</military>
	<issues>
		<disputes>Ethiopian forces invaded southern Somalia and routed Islamist Courts from Mogadishu in January 2007; &quot;Somaliland&quot; secessionists provide port facilities in Berbera to landlocked Ethiopia and have established commercial ties with other regional states; &quot;Puntland&quot; and &quot;Somaliland&quot; &quot;governments&quot; seek international support in their secessionist aspirations and overlapping border claims; the undemarcated former British administrative line has little meaning as a political separation to rival clans within Ethiopia's Ogaden and southern Somalia's Oromo region; Kenya works hard to prevent the clan and militia fighting in Somalia from spreading south across the border, which has long been open to nomadic pastoralists</disputes>
		<drugs></drugs>
	</issues>
</country>