<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<country>
	<code>sp</code>
	<name>Spain</name>
	<region>Europe</region>
	<background>Spain's powerful world empire of the 16th and 17th centuries ultimately yielded command of the seas to England. Subsequent failure to embrace the mercantile and industrial revolutions caused the country to fall behind Britain, France, and Germany in economic and political power. Spain remained neutral in World Wars I and II but suffered through a devastating civil war (1936-39). A peaceful transition to democracy following the death of dictator Francisco FRANCO in 1975, and rapid economic modernization (Spain joined the EU in 1986) gave Spain a dynamic and rapidly growing economy and made it a global champion of freedom and human rights. The government continues to battle the Basque Fatherland and Liberty (ETA) terrorist organization, but its major focus for the immediate future will be on measures to reverse the severe economic recession that started in mid-2008.</background>
	<geo>
		<note>strategic location along approaches to Strait of Gibraltar; Spain controls a number of territories in northern Morocco including the enclaves of Ceuta and Melilla, and the islands of Penon de Velez de la Gomera, Penon de Alhucemas, and Islas Chafarinas</note>
		<location>
			<desc>Southwestern Europe, bordering the Mediterranean Sea, North Atlantic Ocean, Bay of Biscay, and Pyrenees Mountains; southwest of France</desc>
			<coordinates>TO DO</coordinates>
		</location>
		<area>
			<total unit="sq km">505370</total>
			<land unit="sq km">498980</land>
			<water unit="sq km">6390</water>
			<comparison>slightly more than twice the size of Oregon</comparison>
		</area>
		<boundaries>
			<borders unit=""></borders>
			<coastline unit="km">4964</coastline>
		</boundaries>
		<maritime-claims>
			<territorial unit="nm">12</territorial>
			<contiguous unit="nm">24</contiguous>
			<economic unit="nm">200</economic>
			<continental-shelf></continental-shelf>
		</maritime-claims>
		<climate>temperate; clear, hot summers in interior, more moderate and cloudy along coast; cloudy, cold winters in interior, partly cloudy and cool along coast</climate>
		<terrain>large, flat to dissected plateau surrounded by rugged hills; Pyrenees Mountains in north</terrain>
		<elevation>
			<high>Pico de Teide (Tenerife) on Canary Islands 3,718 m</high>
			<low>Atlantic Ocean 0 m</low>
		</elevation>
		<resources>coal, lignite, iron ore, copper, lead, zinc, uranium, tungsten, mercury, pyrites, magnesite, fluorspar, gypsum, sepiolite, kaolin, potash, hydropower, arable land</resources>
		<land-use>
			<arable unit="%">27.18</arable>
			<crops unit="%">9.85</crops>
			<other unit="%">62.97</other>
		</land-use>
		<hazards>[object Object]</hazards>
		<issues>pollution of the Mediterranean Sea from raw sewage and effluents from the offshore production of oil and gas; water quality and quantity nationwide; air pollution; deforestation; desertification</issues>
		<water>
			<irrigated-land unit="sq km">38000</irrigated-land>
			<renewable-water unit="cu km">111.1</renewable-water>
			<freshwater-withdrawal>
				<total unit="cu km/yr">37.22</total>
				<per-capita unit="cu m/yr">864</per-capita>
			</freshwater-withdrawal>
		</water>
		<!--
"geo": {

		"Natural hazards": "flooding is a threat in some areas of the country (e.g., parts of Jutland, along the southern coast of the island of Lolland) that are protected from the sea by a system of dikes",
		"Environment - current issues": "air pollution, principally from vehicle and power plant emissions; nitrogen and phosphorus pollution of the North Sea; drinking and surface water becoming polluted from animal wastes and pesticides",
		"Environment - international agreements": {
			"party to:": "Air Pollution, Air Pollution-Nitrogen Oxides, Air Pollution-Persistent Organic Pollutants, Air Pollution-Sulfur 85, Air Pollution-Sulfur 94, Air Pollution-Volatile Organic Compounds, Antarctic Treaty, Biodiversity, Climate Change, Climate Change-Kyoto Protocol, Desertification, Endangered Species, Environmental Modification, Hazardous Wastes, Law of the Sea, Marine Dumping, Marine Life Conservation, Ozone Layer Protection, Ship Pollution, Tropical Timber 83, Tropical Timber 94, Wetlands, Whaling",
			"signed, but not ratified:": "none of the selected agreements"
		},
		"Geography - note": "controls Danish Straits (Skagerrak and Kattegat) linking Baltic and North Seas; about one-quarter of the population lives in greater Copenhagen"

		-->
	</geo>
	<people>
		<population>
			<total>46754</total>
			<birth unit="births/1,000 population">10.66</birth>
			<death unit="deaths/1,000 population">8.8</birth>
			<migration unit="migrant(s)/1,000 population">3.89</migration>
			<growth unit="%">0.574</growth>
		</population>
		<age-distribution unit="percent">
			<group min="0" max="14">15.1</group>
			<group min="15" max="64">67.7</group>
			<group min="65"></group>
		</age-distribution>
		<median-age unit="years">
			<total>40.5</total>
			<male>39.3</male>
			<female>41.9</female>
		</median-age>
		<urbanization>
			<urban unit="% of total population">77</urban>
			<rate unit="% annual rate of change">1</urban>
			<cities>MADRID (capital) 5.762 million; Barcelona 5.029 million; Valencia 812,000 (2009)</cities>
		</urbanization>
		<sex unit="male(s)/female">
			<group name="at birth" max="0">1.065</group>
			<group name="0 to 14" min="0" max="14">1.06</group>
			<group name="15 to 64" min="15" max="64">1.01</group>
			<group name="65 and over" min="65" max="0">0.72</group>
			<group name="total" min="0">0.96</group>
		</sex>
		<infant-mortality>
			<total unit="deaths/1,000 live births">3.39</total>
			<male unit="deaths/1,000 live births">3.74</male>
			<female unit="deaths/1,000 live births">3.03</female>
		</infant-mortality>
		<life-expectancy-at-birth>
			<total unit="years">81.17</total>
			<male unit="years">78.16</male>
			<female unit="years">84.37</female>
		</life-expectancy-at-birth>
		<fertility-rate unit="1.47">children born/woman</fertility-rate>
		<hiv>
			<prevalence>[object Object]</prevalence>
			<total>130000</total>
			<deaths>1600</deaths>
		</hiv>
		<infectious-disease risk="">
			<food-or-waterborne></food-or-waterborne>
			<vectorborne></vectorborne>
			<water-contact></water-contact>
		</infectious-disease>
		<drinking-water-source>[object Object]</drinking-water-source>
		<sanitation-access>[object Object]</sanitation-access>
		<nationality>
			<noun>Spaniard(s)</noun>
			<adjective>Spanish</adjective>
		</nationality>
		<ethnic-groups>composite of Mediterranean and Nordic types</ethnic-groups>
		<religions>Roman Catholic 94%, other 6%</religions>
		<languages>Castilian Spanish (official) 74%, Catalan 17%, Galician 7%, and Basque 2% (official regionally)</languages>
		<literacy>
			<definition>age 15 and over can read and write</definition>
			<total unit="%">97.9</total>
			<male unit="%">98.7</male>
			<female unit="%">97.2</female>
		</literacy>
		<school-expectancy unit="years">16</school-expectancy>
		<education-expenditure unit="% of GDP">4.3</school-expectancy>
	</people>
	<government>
		<country-name>
			<long>Kingdom of Spain</long>
			<short>Spain</short>
		</country-name>
		<dependency></dependency>
		<government-type>parliamentary monarchy</government-type>
		<capital>
			<name>Madrid</name>
			<coordinates>40° 24' N, 3° 41' W</coordinates>
			<time-difference>UTC+1 (6 hours ahead of Washington, DC during Standard Time)</time-difference>
		</capital>
		<administrative-divisions>[object Object]</administrative-divisions>
		<independence>1492; the Iberian peninsula was characterized by a variety of independent kingdoms prior to the Muslim occupation that began in the early 8th century A.D. and lasted nearly seven centuries; the small Christian redoubts of the north began the reconquest almost immediately, culminating in the seizure of Granada in 1492; this event completed the unification of several kingdoms and is traditionally considered the forging of present-day Spain</independence>
		<national-holiday>National Day, 12 October (1492); year when Columbus first set foot in the Americas</national-holiday>
		<legal-system>civil law system with regional variations</legal-system>
		<suffrage>18 years of age; universal</suffrage>
		<executive>
			<head-of-state>King JUAN CARLOS I (since 22 November 1975); Heir Apparent Prince FELIPE, son of the monarch, born 30 January 1968</head-of-state>
			<head-of-government>President of the Government (Prime Minister equivalent) Jose Luis Rodriguez ZAPATERO (since 17 April 2004); First Vice President (and Minister of the Interior) Alfredo Perez RUBALCABA (since 20 October 2010), Second Vice President (and Minister of Economy and Finance) Elena SALGADO Mendez (since 8 April 2009), and Third Vice President (and Minister of Regional Affairs) Manuel CHAVES Gonzalez (since 8 April 2009)</head-of-government>
			<cabinet>Council of Ministers designated by the president</cabinet>
			<elections>the monarchy is hereditary; following legislative elections, the leader of the majority party or the leader of the majority coalition usually proposed president by the monarch and elected by the National Assembly; election last held on 9 and 11 April 2008 (next to be held in March 2012); vice presidents appointed by the monarch on the proposal of the president</elections>
			<election-results></election-results>
		</executive>
		<legislative>
			<description>bicameral; General Courts or Las Cortes Generales (National Assembly) consists of the Senate or Senado (264 seats as of 2008; 208 members directly elected by popular vote and the other 56 - as of 2008 - appointed by the regional legislatures; members to serve four-year terms) and the Congress of Deputies or Congreso de los Diputados (350 seats; each of the 50 electoral provinces fills a minimum of two seats and the North African enclaves of Ceuta and Melilla fill one seat each with members serving a four-year term; the other 248 members are determined by proportional representation based on popular vote on block lists who serve four-year terms)</description>
			<elections>Senate - last held on 9 March 2008 (next to be held by March 2012); Congress of Deputies - last held on 9 March 2008 (next to be held by March 2012)</elections>
			<election-results>Senate - percent of vote by party - NA; seats by party - PP 101, PSOE 88, Entesa Catalona de Progress 12, CiU 4, PNV 2, CC 1, members appointed by regional legislatures 56; Congress of Deputies - percent of vote by party - PSOE 43.6%, PP 40.1%, CiU 3.1%, PNV 1.2%, ERC 1.2%, other 10.8%; seats by party - PSOE 169, PP 154, CiU 10, PNV 6, ERC 3, other 8; note - seats by party in the Congress of Deputies as of 15 December 2009 - PSOE 169, PP 153, CiU 10, PNV 6, ERC 3, other 9</election-results>
		</legislative>
		<judicial>Supreme Court or Tribunal Supremo</judicial>
		<parties>Basque Nationalist Party or PNV or EAJ [Inigo URKULLU Renteria]; Canarian Coalition or CC [Claudina MORALES Rodriquez] (a coalition of five parties); Convergence and Union or CiU [Artur MAS i Gavarro] (a coalition of the Democratic Convergence of Catalonia or CDC [Artur MAS i Gavarro] and the Democratic Union of Catalonia or UDC [Josep Antoni DURAN i LLEIDA]); Entesa Catalonia de Progress (a Senate coalition grouping four Catalan parties - PSC, ERC, ICV, EUA); Galician Nationalist Bloc or BNG [Guillerme VAZQUEZ Vazquez]; Initiative for Catalonia Greens or ICV [Joan SAURA i Laporta]; Navarra Yes or NaBai [collective leadership] (a coalition of four Navarran parties); Popular Party or PP [Mariano RAJOY Brey]; Republican Left of Catalonia or ERC [Joan PUIGCERCOS i Boixassa]; Spanish Socialist Workers Party or PSOE [Jose Luis Rodriguez ZAPATERO]; Union of People of Navarra or UPN [Yolanda BARCINA Angulo]; Union, Progress and Democracy or UPyD [Rosa DIEZ Gonzalez]; United Left or IU [Cayo LARA Moya] (a coalition of parties including the Communist Party of Spain or PCE and other small parties)</parties>
		<pressure-groups>TO DO</pressure-groups>
		<membership>ADB (nonregional member), AfDB (nonregional member), Arctic Council (observer), Australia Group, BCIE, BIS, CBSS (observer), CE, CERN, EAPC, EBRD, EIB, EMU, ESA, EU, FAO, FATF, IADB, IAEA, IBRD, ICAO, ICC, ICRM, IDA, IEA, IFAD, IFC, IFRCS, IHO, ILO, IMF, IMO, IMSO, Interpol, IOC, IOM, IPU, ISO, ITSO, ITU, ITUC, LAIA (observer), MIGA, MONUSCO, NATO, NEA, NSG, OAS (observer), OECD, OPCW, OSCE, Paris Club, PCA, Schengen Convention, SECI (observer), SICA (observer), UN, UNCTAD, UNESCO, UNHCR, UNIDO, UNIFIL, Union Latina, UNMIS, UNRWA, UNWTO, UPU, WCO, WHO, WIPO, WMO, WTO, ZC</membership>
		<representation-in-usa>
			<chief>Ambassador Jorge DEZCALLAR de Mazarredo</chief>
			<chancery>2375 Pennsylvania Avenue NW, Washington, DC 20037</chancery>
			<telephone>[1] (202) 452-0100, 728-2340</telephone>
			<FAX>[1] (202) 833-5670</FAX>
			<consulates>Boston, Chicago, Houston, Los Angeles, Miami, New Orleans, New York, San Francisco, San Juan (Puerto Rico)</consulates>
		</representation-in-usa>
		<representation-from-usa>
			<chief>Ambassador Alan D. SOLOMONT</chief>
			<embassy>Serrano 75, 28006 Madrid</embassy>
			<mailing-address>PSC 61, APO AE 09642</mailing-address>
			<telephone>[34] (91) 587-2200</telephone>
			<FAX>[34] (91) 587-2303</FAX>
		</representation-from-usa>
		<flag>[object Object]</flag>
		<anthem>
			<name>&quot;Himno Nacional Espanol&quot; (National Anthem of Spain)</name>
			<by>none/unknown</by>
		</anthem>
	</government>
	<economy>
		<overview>Spain's mixed capitalist economy is the 12th largest in the world, and its per capita income roughly matches that of Germany and France. However, after almost 15 years of above average GDP growth, the Spanish economy began to slow in late 2007 and entered into a recession in the second quarter of 2008. GDP contracted by 3.7% in 2009, ending a 16-year growth trend, and by another 0.2% in 2010, making Spain the last major economy to emerge from the global recession. The reversal in Spain's economic growth reflected a significant decline in construction amid an oversupply of housing and falling consumer spending, while exports actually have begun to grow. Government efforts to boost the economy through stimulus spending, extended unemployment benefits, and loan guarantees did not prevent a sharp rise in the unemployment rate, which rose from a low of about 8% in 2007 to 20% in 2010. The government budget deficit worsened from 3.8% of GDP in 2008 to about 9.7% of GDP in 2010, more than three times the euro-zone limit. Spain's large budget deficit and poor economic growth prospects have made it vulnerable to financial contagion from other highly-indebted euro zone members despite the government's efforts to cut spending, privatize industries, and boost competitiveness through labor market reforms. Spanish banks' high exposure to the collapsed domestic construction and real estate market also poses a continued risk for the sector. The government oversaw a restructuring of the savings bank sector in 2010, and provided some $15 billion in capital to various institutions. Investors remain concerned that Madrid may need to bail out more troubled banks. The Bank of Spain, however, is seeking to boost confidence in the financial sector by pressuring banks to come clean about their losses and consolidate into stronger groups.</overview>
		<gdp>
			<purchasing-power-parity></purchasing-power-parity>
			<official-exchange-rate>1410000000000</official-exchange-rate>
			<real-growth-rate unit=""></real-growth-rate>
			<per-capita></per-capita>
			<sector unit="%">
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
		</gdp>
		<labour>
			<force>22960000</force>
			<sector>
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
			<unemployment unit="%">20</unemployment>
		</labour>
		<poverty>[object Object]</poverty>
		<household-income>TO DO</household-income>
		<budget>
			<revenue unit="USD"></revenue>
			<expenditure unit="USD"></expenditure>
		</budget>
		<public-debt unit="% of GDP">63.4</public-debt>
		<consumer-inflation unit="%">1.3</consumer-inflation>
		<central-bank-discount-rate unit="%"></central-bank-discount-rate>
		<commercial-prime-lending-rate unit="%">10.72</commercial-prime-lending-rate>
		<narrow-money-stock unit="USD"></narrow-money-stock>
		<broad-money-stock unit="USD">2264000000000</broad-money-stock>
		<domestic-credit-stock unit="USD">3683000000000</domestic-credit-stock>
		<agriculture-products>grain, vegetables, olives, wine grapes, sugar beets, citrus; beef, pork, poultry, dairy products; fish</agriculture-products>
		<industries>textiles and apparel (including footwear), food and beverages, metals and metal manufactures, chemicals, shipbuilding, automobiles, machine tools, tourism, clay and refractory products, footwear, pharmaceuticals, medical equipment</industries>
		<industrial-production-growth>-2% (2010 est.)</industrial-production-growth>
		<electricity unit="kWh">
			<production>300500000000</production>
			<consumption>276100000000</consumption>
			<exports>16920000000.000002</exports>
			<imports>5880000000</imports>
		</electricity>
		<oil>
			<production unit="bbl/day">27230</production>
			<consumption unit="bbl/day">1482000</consumption>
			<exports unit="bbl/day">218600</exports>
			<imports unit="bbl/day">1716000</imports>
			<reserves unit="bbl">150000000</reserves>
		</oil>
		<natural-gas>
			<production unit="cu m">13000000</production>
			<consumption unit="cu m">33880000000.000004</consumption>
			<exports unit="cu m">975000000</exports>
			<imports unit="cu m">34670000000</imports>
			<reserves unit="cu m">2548000000</reserves>
		</natural-gas>
		<exports>
			<total unit="USD"></total>
			<commodities>machinery, motor vehicles; foodstuffs, pharmaceuticals, medicines, other consumer goods</commodities>
			<partners>France 19.27%, Germany 11.11%, Portugal 9.21%, Italy 8.24%, UK 6.18% (2009)</partners>
		</exports>
		<imports>
			<total unit="USD">324600000000</total>
			<commodities>machinery and equipment, fuels, chemicals, semifinished goods, foodstuffs, consumer goods, measuring and medical control instruments</commodities>
			<partners>Germany 15.02%, France 12.82%, Italy 7.17%, China 5.8%, Netherlands 5.22%, UK 4.7% (2009)</partners>
		</imports>
		<external-debt unit="USD">2166000000000</external-debt>
		<exchange-rates>euros (EUR) per US dollar -</exchange-rates>
	</economy>
	<communications>
		<telephones>
			<assessment>well developed, modern facilities; fixed-line teledensity is roughly 50 per 100 persons</assessment>
			<domestic>combined fixed-line and mobile-cellular teledensity is nearly 175 telephones per 100 persons</domestic>
			<international>country code - 34; submarine cables provide connectivity to Europe, Middle East, Asia, and US; satellite earth stations - 2 Intelsat (1 Atlantic Ocean and 1 Indian Ocean), NA Eutelsat; tropospheric scatter to adjacent countries</international>
			<land-lines>20057000</land-lines>
			<mobile>50991000</mobile>
		</telephones>
		<broadcast>a mixture of both publicly-operated and privately-owned TV and radio stations broadcasting; overall, hundreds of TV channels are available including national, regional, local, public, and international channels; satellite and cable TV systems are accessible; multiple national radio networks, a large number of regional radio networks, and a larger number of local radio stations broadcasting; overall, hundreds of radio stations operating (2008)</broadcast>
		<internet>
			<tld>.es</tld>
			<hosts>3822000</hosts>
			<users>28119000</users>
		</internet>
	</communications>
	<transport>
		<airports>
			<total>154</total>
			<paved>
				<altitude min="*" max="*"></altitude>
				<altitude min="3047m" max="*">18</altitude>
				<altitude min="2438m" max="3047m">13</altitude>
				<altitude min="1524m" max="2437m">18</altitude>
				<altitude min="914m" max="1524m">24</altitude>
				<altitude min="*" max="914m"></altitude>
			</paved>
		</airports>
		<ports-and-terminals>Algeciras, Barcelona, Bilbao, Cartagena, Huelva, Tarragona, Valencia (Spain); Las Palmas, Santa Cruz de Tenerife (Canary Islands)</ports-and-terminals>
	</transport>
	<military>
		<branches>Spanish Armed Forces: Army (Ejercito de Tierra), Spanish Navy (Armada Espanola, AE; includes Marine Corps), Spanish Air Force (Ejercito del Aire Espanola, EdA) (2010)</branches>
		<manpower>
			<population-available>
				<male>11759</male>
				<female>11204</female>
			</population-available>
			<fit-for-service>
				<male>9603</male>
				<female>9116</female>
			</fit-for-service>
			<reaching-maturity>
				<male>217244</male>
				<female>205278</female>
			</reaching-maturity>
			<notes></notes>
		</manpower>
	</military>
	<issues>
		<disputes>in 2002, Gibraltar residents voted overwhelmingly by referendum to reject any &quot;shared sovereignty&quot; arrangement; the government of Gibraltar insists on equal participation in talks between the UK and Spain; Spain disapproves of UK plans to grant Gibraltar greater autonomy; Morocco protests Spain's control over the coastal enclaves of Ceuta, Melilla, and the islands of Penon de Velez de la Gomera, Penon de Alhucemas, and Islas Chafarinas, and surrounding waters; both countries claim Isla Perejil (Leila Island); Morocco serves as the primary launching site of illegal migration into Spain from North Africa; Portugal does not recognize Spanish sovereignty over the territory of Olivenza based on a difference of interpretation of the 1815 Congress of Vienna and the 1801 Treaty of Badajoz</disputes>
		<drugs>despite rigorous law enforcement efforts, North African, Latin American, Galician, and other European traffickers take advantage of Spain's long coastline to land large shipments of cocaine and hashish for distribution to the European market; consumer for Latin American cocaine and North African hashish; destination and minor transshipment point for Southwest Asian heroin; money-laundering site for Colombian narcotics trafficking organizations and organized crime</drugs>
	</issues>
</country>