<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<country>
	<code>uz</code>
	<name>Uzbekistan</name>
	<region>Central Asia</region>
	<background>Russia conquered the territory of present-day Uzbekistan in the late 19th century. Stiff resistance to the Red Army after the Bolshevik Revolution was eventually suppressed and a socialist republic established in 1924. During the Soviet era, intensive production of &quot;white gold&quot; (cotton) and grain led to overuse of agrochemicals and the depletion of water supplies, which have left the land poisoned and the Aral Sea and certain rivers half dry. Independent since 1991, the country seeks to gradually lessen its dependence on agriculture while developing its mineral and petroleum reserves. Current concerns include terrorism by Islamic militants, economic stagnation, and the curtailment of human rights and democratization.</background>
	<geo>
		<note>along with Liechtenstein, one of the only two doubly landlocked countries in the world</note>
		<location>
			<desc>Central Asia, north of Turkmenistan, south of Kazakhstan</desc>
			<coordinates>TO DO</coordinates>
		</location>
		<area>
			<total unit="sq km">447400</total>
			<land unit="sq km">425400</land>
			<water unit="sq km">22000</water>
			<comparison>slightly larger than California</comparison>
		</area>
		<boundaries>
			<borders unit=""></borders>
			<coastline unit=""></coastline>
		</boundaries>
		<maritime-claims>
			<territorial unit=""></territorial>
			<contiguous unit=""></contiguous>
			<economic unit=""></economic>
			<continental-shelf></continental-shelf>
		</maritime-claims>
		<climate>mostly midlatitude desert, long, hot summers, mild winters; semiarid grassland in east</climate>
		<terrain>mostly flat-to-rolling sandy desert with dunes; broad, flat intensely irrigated river valleys along course of Amu Darya, Syr Darya (Sirdaryo), and Zarafshon; Fergana Valley in east surrounded by mountainous Tajikistan and Kyrgyzstan; shrinking Aral Sea in west</terrain>
		<elevation>
			<high>Adelunga Toghi 4,301 m</high>
			<low>Sariqamish Kuli -12 m</low>
		</elevation>
		<resources>natural gas, petroleum, coal, gold, uranium, silver, copper, lead and zinc, tungsten, molybdenum</resources>
		<land-use>
			<arable unit="%">10.51</arable>
			<crops unit="%">0.76</crops>
			<other unit="%">88.73</other>
		</land-use>
		<hazards>NA</hazards>
		<issues>shrinkage of the Aral Sea is resulting in growing concentrations of chemical pesticides and natural salts; these substances are then blown from the increasingly exposed lake bed and contribute to desertification; water pollution from industrial wastes and the heavy use of fertilizers and pesticides is the cause of many human health disorders; increasing soil salination; soil contamination from buried nuclear processing and agricultural chemicals, including DDT</issues>
		<water>
			<irrigated-land unit="sq km">42230</irrigated-land>
			<renewable-water unit="cu km">72.2</renewable-water>
			<freshwater-withdrawal>
				<total unit="cu km/yr">58.34</total>
				<per-capita unit="cu m/yr">2194</per-capita>
			</freshwater-withdrawal>
		</water>
		<!--
"geo": {

		"Natural hazards": "flooding is a threat in some areas of the country (e.g., parts of Jutland, along the southern coast of the island of Lolland) that are protected from the sea by a system of dikes",
		"Environment - current issues": "air pollution, principally from vehicle and power plant emissions; nitrogen and phosphorus pollution of the North Sea; drinking and surface water becoming polluted from animal wastes and pesticides",
		"Environment - international agreements": {
			"party to:": "Air Pollution, Air Pollution-Nitrogen Oxides, Air Pollution-Persistent Organic Pollutants, Air Pollution-Sulfur 85, Air Pollution-Sulfur 94, Air Pollution-Volatile Organic Compounds, Antarctic Treaty, Biodiversity, Climate Change, Climate Change-Kyoto Protocol, Desertification, Endangered Species, Environmental Modification, Hazardous Wastes, Law of the Sea, Marine Dumping, Marine Life Conservation, Ozone Layer Protection, Ship Pollution, Tropical Timber 83, Tropical Timber 94, Wetlands, Whaling",
			"signed, but not ratified:": "none of the selected agreements"
		},
		"Geography - note": "controls Danish Straits (Skagerrak and Kattegat) linking Baltic and North Seas; about one-quarter of the population lives in greater Copenhagen"

		-->
	</geo>
	<people>
		<population>
			<total>28128</total>
			<birth unit="births/1,000 population">17.43</birth>
			<death unit="deaths/1,000 population">5.29</birth>
			<migration unit=""></migration>
			<growth unit="%">0.94</growth>
		</population>
		<age-distribution unit="percent">
			<group min="0" max="14">26.5</group>
			<group min="15" max="64">68.8</group>
			<group min="65"></group>
		</age-distribution>
		<median-age unit="years">
			<total>25.7</total>
			<male>25.2</male>
			<female>26.3</female>
		</median-age>
		<urbanization>
			<urban unit="% of total population">36</urban>
			<rate unit="% annual rate of change">1.4</urban>
			<cities>TASHKENT (capital) 2.201 million (2009)</cities>
		</urbanization>
		<sex unit="male(s)/female">
			<group name="at birth" max="0">1.06</group>
			<group name="0 to 14" min="0" max="14">1.05</group>
			<group name="15 to 64" min="15" max="64">0.99</group>
			<group name="65 and over" min="65" max="0">0.75</group>
			<group name="total" min="0">0.99</group>
		</sex>
		<infant-mortality>
			<total unit="deaths/1,000 live births">21.92</total>
			<male unit="deaths/1,000 live births">25.95</male>
			<female unit="deaths/1,000 live births">17.64</female>
		</infant-mortality>
		<life-expectancy-at-birth>
			<total unit="years">72.51</total>
			<male unit="years">69.48</male>
			<female unit="years">75.71</female>
		</life-expectancy-at-birth>
		<fertility-rate unit="1.89">children born/woman</fertility-rate>
		<hiv>
			<prevalence>[object Object]</prevalence>
			<total>28000</total>
			<deaths>fewer than 500 (2009 est.)</deaths>
		</hiv>
		<infectious-disease risk="">
			<food-or-waterborne></food-or-waterborne>
			<vectorborne></vectorborne>
			<water-contact></water-contact>
		</infectious-disease>
		<drinking-water-source>[object Object]</drinking-water-source>
		<sanitation-access>[object Object]</sanitation-access>
		<nationality>
			<noun>Uzbekistani</noun>
			<adjective>Uzbekistani</adjective>
		</nationality>
		<ethnic-groups>Uzbek 80%, Russian 5.5%, Tajik 5%, Kazakh 3%, Karakalpak 2.5%, Tatar 1.5%, other 2.5% (1996 est.)</ethnic-groups>
		<religions>Muslim 88% (mostly Sunni), Eastern Orthodox 9%, other 3%</religions>
		<languages>Uzbek (official) 74.3%, Russian 14.2%, Tajik 4.4%, other 7.1%</languages>
		<literacy>
			<definition>age 15 and over can read and write</definition>
			<total unit="%">99.3</total>
			<male unit="%">99.6</male>
			<female unit="%">99</female>
		</literacy>
		<school-expectancy unit="years">11</school-expectancy>
		<education-expenditure unit=""></school-expectancy>
	</people>
	<government>
		<country-name>
			<long>Republic of Uzbekistan</long>
			<short>Uzbekistan</short>
		</country-name>
		<dependency></dependency>
		<government-type>republic; authoritarian presidential rule, with little power outside the executive branch</government-type>
		<capital>
			<name>Tashkent (Toshkent)</name>
			<coordinates>41° 20' N, 69° 18' E</coordinates>
			<time-difference>UTC+5 (10 hours ahead of Washington, DC during Standard Time)</time-difference>
		</capital>
		<administrative-divisions>[object Object]</administrative-divisions>
		<independence>1 September 1991 (from the Soviet Union)</independence>
		<national-holiday>Independence Day, 1 September (1991)</national-holiday>
		<legal-system>civil law system</legal-system>
		<suffrage>18 years of age; universal</suffrage>
		<executive>
			<head-of-state>President Islom KARIMOV (since 24 March 1990, when he was elected president by the then Supreme Soviet; elected president of independent Uzbekistan in 1991)</head-of-state>
			<head-of-government>Prime Minister Shavkat MIRZIYOYEV (since 11 December 2003); First Deputy Prime Minister Rustam AZIMOV (since 2 January 2008)</head-of-government>
			<cabinet>Cabinet of Ministers appointed by the president with approval of the Supreme Assembly</cabinet>
			<elections>president elected by popular vote for a seven-year term (eligible for a second term; previously was a five-year term, extended by constitutional amendment in 2002); election last held on 23 December 2007 (next to be held in 2014); prime minister, ministers, and deputy ministers appointed by the president</elections>
			<election-results>Islom KARIMOV reelected president; percent of vote - Islom KARIMOV 88.1%, Asliddin RUSTAMOV 3.2%, Dilorom T0SHMUHAMEDOVA 2.9%, Akmal SAIDOV 2.6%, other 3.2%</election-results>
		</executive>
		<legislative>
			<description>bicameral Supreme Assembly or Oliy Majlis consists of an upper house or Senate (100 seats; 84 members elected by regional governing councils and 16 appointed by the president; members to serve five-year terms) and a lower house or Legislative Chamber (150 seats; 135 members elected by popular vote to serve five-year terms, while 15 spots reserved for the new Ecological Movement of Uzbekistan)</description>
			<elections>last held on 27 December 2009 and 10 January 2010 (next to be held in December 2014)</elections>
			<election-results>Senate - percent of vote by party - NA; seats by party - NA; Legislative Chamber - percent of vote by party - NA; seats by party - LDPU 53, NDP 32, National Rebirth Party 31, Adolat 19</election-results>
		</legislative>
		<judicial>Supreme Court (judges are nominated by the president and confirmed by the Supreme Assembly)</judicial>
		<parties>Adolat (Justice) Social Democratic Party [Ismoil SAIFNAZAROV]; Ecological Movement of Uzbekistan [Boriy ALIXONOV, chairman]; Liberal Democratic Party of Uzbekistan or LDPU [Muhammadjon AHMADJONOV]; National Rebirth Party (Milliy Tiklanish) [Ahtam TURSUNOV]; People's Democratic Party or NDP (formerly Communist Party) [Latif GULOMOV]</parties>
		<pressure-groups>TO DO</pressure-groups>
		<membership>ADB, CICA, CIS, EAPC, EBRD, ECO, FAO, IAEA, IBRD, ICAO, ICRM, IDA, IDB, IFC, IFRCS, ILO, IMF, Interpol, IOC, ISO, ITSO, ITU, MIGA, NAM, OIC, OPCW, OSCE, PFP, SCO, UN, UNCTAD, UNESCO, UNIDO, UNWTO, UPU, WCO, WFTU, WHO, WIPO, WMO, WTO (observer)</membership>
		<representation-in-usa>
			<chief>Ambassador Ilxamdjan NEMATOV</chief>
			<chancery>1746 Massachusetts Avenue NW, Washington, DC 20036</chancery>
			<telephone>[1] (202) 887-5300</telephone>
			<FAX>[1] (202) 293-6804</FAX>
			<consulates>New York</consulates>
		</representation-in-usa>
		<representation-from-usa>
			<chief>Ambassador Richard B. NORLAND</chief>
			<embassy>3 Moyqo'rq'on, 5th Block, Yunusobod District, Tashkent 100093</embassy>
			<mailing-address>use embassy street address</mailing-address>
			<telephone>[998] (71) 120-5450</telephone>
			<FAX>[998] (71) 120-6335</FAX>
		</representation-from-usa>
		<flag>three equal horizontal bands of blue (top), white, and green separated by red fimbriations with a white crescent moon (closed side to the hoist) and 12 white stars shifted to the hoist on the top band; blue is the color of the Turkic peoples and of the sky, white signifies peace and the striving for purity in thoughts and deeds, while green represents nature and is the color of Islam; the red stripes are the vital force of all living organisms that links good and pure ideas with the eternal sky and with deeds on earth; the crescent represents Islam and the 12 stars the months and constellations of the Uzbek calendar</flag>
		<anthem>
			<name>&quot;O'zbekiston Respublikasining Davlat Madhiyasi&quot; (National Anthem of the Republic of Uzbekistan)</name>
			<by>Abdulla ARIPOV/Mutal BURHANOV</by>
		</anthem>
	</government>
	<economy>
		<overview>Uzbekistan is a dry, landlocked country; 11% of the land is intensely cultivated, in irrigated river valleys. More than 60% of the population lives in densely populated rural communities. Export of hydrocarbons, including natural gas and petroleum, provided about 40% of foreign exchange earnings in 2009. Other major export earners include gold and cotton. Uzbekistan is now the world's second-largest cotton exporter and fifth largest producer; it has come under increasing international criticism for the use of child labor in its annual cotton harvest. Nevertheless, Uzbekistan enjoyed a bumper cotton crop in 2010 amidst record high prices. Following independence in September 1991, the government sought to prop up its Soviet-style command economy with subsidies and tight controls on production and prices. While aware of the need to improve the investment climate, the government still sponsors measures that often increase, not decrease, its control over business decisions. A sharp increase in the inequality of income distribution has hurt the lower ranks of society since independence. In 2003, the government accepted Article VIII obligations under the IMF, providing for full currency convertibility. However, strict currency controls and tightening of borders have lessened the effects of convertibility and have also led to some shortages that have further stifled economic activity. The Central Bank often delays or restricts convertibility, especially for consumer goods. Potential investment by Russia and China in Uzbekistan's gas and oil industry, as well as increased cooperation with South Korea in the realm of civil aviation, may boost growth prospects. However, decreased demand for natural gas in Europe and Russia in the wake of the global financial crisis could reduce energy-related revenues in the near term. In November 2005, Russian President Vladimir PUTIN and Uzbekistan President KARIMOV signed an &quot;alliance,&quot; which included provisions for economic and business cooperation. Russian businesses have shown increased interest in Uzbekistan, especially in mining, telecom, and oil and gas. In 2006, Uzbekistan took steps to rejoin the Collective Security Treaty Organization (CSTO) and the Eurasian Economic Community (EurASEC), which it subsequently left in 2008, both organizations dominated by Russia. In the past Uzbek authorities had accused US and other foreign companies operating in Uzbekistan of violating Uzbek tax laws and have frozen their assets, but no new expropriations occurred in 2008-09. Instead, the Uzbek Government has actively courted several major U.S. and international corporations, offering attractive financing and tax advantages, and has landed a significant US investment in the automotive industry. Although growth slowed in 2009-10, Uzbekistan has seen few other effects from the global economic downturn, primarily due to its relative isolation from the global financial markets.</overview>
		<gdp>
			<purchasing-power-parity></purchasing-power-parity>
			<official-exchange-rate>38990000000</official-exchange-rate>
			<real-growth-rate unit="%">8.5</real-growth-rate>
			<per-capita></per-capita>
			<sector unit="%">
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
		</gdp>
		<labour>
			<force>16000000</force>
			<sector>
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
			<unemployment unit=""></unemployment>
		</labour>
		<poverty>[object Object]</poverty>
		<household-income>TO DO</household-income>
		<budget>
			<revenue unit="USD"></revenue>
			<expenditure unit="USD"></expenditure>
		</budget>
		<public-debt unit="% of GDP">9</public-debt>
		<consumer-inflation unit="%"></consumer-inflation>
		<central-bank-discount-rate unit="%"></central-bank-discount-rate>
		<commercial-prime-lending-rate unit="%"></commercial-prime-lending-rate>
		<narrow-money-stock unit="USD">4895000000</narrow-money-stock>
		<broad-money-stock unit="USD">7197000000</broad-money-stock>
		<domestic-credit-stock unit="USD">6482000000</domestic-credit-stock>
		<agriculture-products>cotton, vegetables, fruits, grain; livestock</agriculture-products>
		<industries>textiles, food processing, machine building, metallurgy, gold, petroleum, natural gas, chemicals</industries>
		<industrial-production-growth>[object Object]</industrial-production-growth>
		<electricity unit="kWh">
			<production>44800000000</production>
			<consumption>40100000000</consumption>
			<exports>11520000000</exports>
			<imports>11440000000</imports>
		</electricity>
		<oil>
			<production unit="bbl/day">70910</production>
			<consumption unit="bbl/day">145000</consumption>
			<exports unit="bbl/day">6104</exports>
			<imports unit="bbl/day">35810</imports>
			<reserves unit="bbl">594000000</reserves>
		</oil>
		<natural-gas>
			<production unit="cu m">67599999999.99999</production>
			<consumption unit="cu m">52600000000</consumption>
			<exports unit="cu m">15000000000</exports>
			<imports unit="cu m">0</imports>
			<reserves unit="cu m">1841000000000</reserves>
		</natural-gas>
		<exports>
			<total unit="USD"></total>
			<commodities>energy products, cotton, gold, mineral fertilizers, ferrous and nonferrous metals, textiles, food products, machinery, automobiles</commodities>
			<partners>Ukraine 29.91%, Russia 13.94%, Turkey 7.53%, Kazakhstan 7.26%, Bangladesh 6.83%, China 5.69%, South Korea 4.19% (2009)</partners>
		</exports>
		<imports>
			<total unit="USD">9440000000</total>
			<commodities>machinery and equipment, foodstuffs, chemicals, ferrous and nonferrous metals</commodities>
			<partners>Russia 23.72%, China 20.36%, South Korea 13.03%, Germany 6.09%, Ukraine 5.39%, Kazakhstan 4.68% (2009)</partners>
		</imports>
		<external-debt unit="USD">4236000000</external-debt>
		<exchange-rates>Uzbekistani soum (UZS) per US dollar -</exchange-rates>
	</economy>
	<communications>
		<telephones>
			<assessment>digital exchanges in large cities but still antiquated and inadequate in rural areas</assessment>
			<domestic>the state-owned telecommunications company, Uzbektelecom, owner of the fixed line telecommunications system, has used loans from the Japanese government and the China Development Bank to upgrade fixed-line services including conversion to digital exchanges; mobile-cellular services are growing rapidly, with the subscriber base exceeding 16 million in 2009</domestic>
			<international>country code - 998; linked by fiber-optic cable or microwave radio relay with CIS member states and to other countries by leased connection via the Moscow international gateway switch; after the completion of the Uzbek link to the Trans-Asia-Europe (TAE) fiber-optic cable, Uzbekistan plans to establish a fiber-optic connection to Afghanistan (2009)</international>
			<land-lines>1857000</land-lines>
			<mobile>16418000</mobile>
		</telephones>
		<broadcast>government controls media; 8 state-owned broadcasters - 4 TV and 4 radio - provide service to virtually the entire country; about 20 privately-owned TV stations, overseen by local officials, broadcast to local markets; privately-owned TV stations are required to lease transmitters from the government-owned Republic TV and Radio Industry Corporation and are prohibited from broadcasting live; about 15 privately-owned radio broadcasters; programming content includes news updates, music, call-in talk shows, and other entertainment in a half-Russian, half-Uzbek format mandated for private radio (2007)</broadcast>
		<internet>
			<tld>.uz</tld>
			<hosts>47718</hosts>
			<users>4689000</users>
		</internet>
	</communications>
	<transport>
		<airports>
			<total>54</total>
			<paved>
				<altitude min="*" max="*"></altitude>
				<altitude min="3047m" max="*">6</altitude>
				<altitude min="2438m" max="3047m">13</altitude>
				<altitude min="1524m" max="2437m">6</altitude>
				<altitude min="914m" max="1524m">4</altitude>
				<altitude min="*" max="914m"></altitude>
			</paved>
		</airports>
		<ports-and-terminals>Termiz (Amu Darya)</ports-and-terminals>
	</transport>
	<military>
		<branches>Army, Air and Air Defense Forces, National Guard</branches>
		<manpower>
			<population-available>
				<male>7887</male>
				<female>7886</female>
			</population-available>
			<fit-for-service>
				<male>6566</male>
				<female>6745</female>
			</fit-for-service>
			<reaching-maturity>
				<male>306404</male>
				<female>295456</female>
			</reaching-maturity>
			<notes></notes>
		</manpower>
	</military>
	<issues>
		<disputes>prolonged drought and cotton monoculture in Uzbekistan and Turkmenistan creates water-sharing difficulties for Amu Darya river states; field demarcation of the boundaries with Kazakhstan commenced in 2004; border delimitation of 130 km of border with Kyrgyzstan is hampered by serious disputes around enclaves and other areas</disputes>
		<drugs>transit country for Afghan narcotics bound for Russian and, to a lesser extent, Western European markets; limited illicit cultivation of cannabis and small amounts of opium poppy for domestic consumption; poppy cultivation almost wiped out by government crop eradication program; transit point for heroin precursor chemicals bound for Afghanistan</drugs>
	</issues>
</country>