<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<country>
	<code>ym</code>
	<name>Yemen</name>
	<region>Middle East</region>
	<background>North Yemen became independent of the Ottoman Empire in 1918. The British, who had set up a protectorate area around the southern port of Aden in the 19th century, withdrew in 1967 from what became South Yemen. Three years later, the southern government adopted a Marxist orientation. The massive exodus of hundreds of thousands of Yemenis from the south to the north contributed to two decades of hostility between the states. The two countries were formally unified as the Republic of Yemen in 1990. A southern secessionist movement in 1994 was quickly subdued. In 2000, Saudi Arabia and Yemen agreed to a delimitation of their border. Fighting in the northwest between the government and Huthi rebels, a group seeking a return to traditional Zaydi Islam, began in 2004 and has since resulted in seven rounds of fighting - the last ended in early 2010 with a tentative ceasefire. The southern secessionist movement was revitalized in 2008 when a popular socioeconomic protest movement initiated the prior year took on political goals including secession. Public rallies in Sana'a against President SALIH - inspired by similar demonstrations in Tunisia and Egypt - slowly built momentum starting in late January 2011 fueled by complaints over high unemployment, poor economic conditions, and corruption. By the following month, some protests had resulted in violence, and the demonstrations had spread to other major cities. By March the opposition had hardened its demands and was unifying behind calls for SALIH's immediate ouster. Media reports indicated that as many as 100 protesters had been killed and many more injured amid the protests. Domestic and international efforts to mediate a resolution to the political crisis had not yielded a deal as of mid April.</background>
	<geo>
		<note>strategic location on Bab el Mandeb, the strait linking the Red Sea and the Gulf of Aden, one of world's most active shipping lanes</note>
		<location>
			<desc>Middle East, bordering the Arabian Sea, Gulf of Aden, and Red Sea, between Oman and Saudi Arabia</desc>
			<coordinates>TO DO</coordinates>
		</location>
		<area>
			<total unit="sq km">527968</total>
			<land unit="sq km">527968</land>
			<water unit="sq km">0</water>
			<comparison>slightly larger than twice the size of Wyoming</comparison>
		</area>
		<boundaries>
			<borders unit=""></borders>
			<coastline unit="km">1906</coastline>
		</boundaries>
		<maritime-claims>
			<territorial unit="nm">12</territorial>
			<contiguous unit="nm">24</contiguous>
			<economic unit="nm">200</economic>
			<continental-shelf>200 nm or to the edge of the continental margin</continental-shelf>
		</maritime-claims>
		<climate>mostly desert; hot and humid along west coast; temperate in western mountains affected by seasonal monsoon; extraordinarily hot, dry, harsh desert in east</climate>
		<terrain>narrow coastal plain backed by flat-topped hills and rugged mountains; dissected upland desert plains in center slope into the desert interior of the Arabian Peninsula</terrain>
		<elevation>
			<high>Jabal an Nabi Shu'ayb 3,760 m</high>
			<low>Arabian Sea 0 m</low>
		</elevation>
		<resources>petroleum, fish, rock salt, marble; small deposits of coal, gold, lead, nickel, and copper; fertile soil in west</resources>
		<land-use>
			<arable unit="%">2.91</arable>
			<crops unit="%">0.25</crops>
			<other unit="%">96.84</other>
		</land-use>
		<hazards>[object Object]</hazards>
		<issues>limited natural freshwater resources; inadequate supplies of potable water; overgrazing; soil erosion; desertification</issues>
		<water>
			<irrigated-land unit="sq km">6800</irrigated-land>
			<renewable-water unit="cu km">4.1</renewable-water>
			<freshwater-withdrawal>
				<total unit="cu km/yr">6.63</total>
				<per-capita unit="cu m/yr">316</per-capita>
			</freshwater-withdrawal>
		</water>
		<!--
"geo": {

		"Natural hazards": "flooding is a threat in some areas of the country (e.g., parts of Jutland, along the southern coast of the island of Lolland) that are protected from the sea by a system of dikes",
		"Environment - current issues": "air pollution, principally from vehicle and power plant emissions; nitrogen and phosphorus pollution of the North Sea; drinking and surface water becoming polluted from animal wastes and pesticides",
		"Environment - international agreements": {
			"party to:": "Air Pollution, Air Pollution-Nitrogen Oxides, Air Pollution-Persistent Organic Pollutants, Air Pollution-Sulfur 85, Air Pollution-Sulfur 94, Air Pollution-Volatile Organic Compounds, Antarctic Treaty, Biodiversity, Climate Change, Climate Change-Kyoto Protocol, Desertification, Endangered Species, Environmental Modification, Hazardous Wastes, Law of the Sea, Marine Dumping, Marine Life Conservation, Ozone Layer Protection, Ship Pollution, Tropical Timber 83, Tropical Timber 94, Wetlands, Whaling",
			"signed, but not ratified:": "none of the selected agreements"
		},
		"Geography - note": "controls Danish Straits (Skagerrak and Kattegat) linking Baltic and North Seas; about one-quarter of the population lives in greater Copenhagen"

		-->
	</geo>
	<people>
		<population>
			<total>24133</total>
			<birth unit="births/1,000 population">33.49</birth>
			<death unit="deaths/1,000 population">7.02</birth>
			<migration unit="migrant(s)/1,000 population">0</migration>
			<growth unit="%">2.647</growth>
		</population>
		<age-distribution unit="percent">
			<group min="0" max="14">43</group>
			<group min="15" max="64">54.4</group>
			<group min="65"></group>
		</age-distribution>
		<median-age unit="years">
			<total>18.1</total>
			<male>18</male>
			<female>18.2</female>
		</median-age>
		<urbanization>
			<urban unit="% of total population">32</urban>
			<rate unit="% annual rate of change">4.6</urban>
			<cities>SANAA (capital) 2.229 million (2009)</cities>
		</urbanization>
		<sex unit="male(s)/female">
			<group name="at birth" max="0">1.05</group>
			<group name="0 to 14" min="0" max="14">1.04</group>
			<group name="15 to 64" min="15" max="64">1.03</group>
			<group name="65 and over" min="65" max="0">0.91</group>
			<group name="total" min="0">1.03</group>
		</sex>
		<infant-mortality>
			<total unit="deaths/1,000 live births">55.11</total>
			<male unit="deaths/1,000 live births">59.7</male>
			<female unit="deaths/1,000 live births">50.29</female>
		</infant-mortality>
		<life-expectancy-at-birth>
			<total unit="years">63.74</total>
			<male unit="years">61.7</male>
			<female unit="years">65.87</female>
		</life-expectancy-at-birth>
		<fertility-rate unit="4.63">children born/woman</fertility-rate>
		<hiv>
			<prevalence>[object Object]</prevalence>
			<total>12000</total>
			<deaths>NA</deaths>
		</hiv>
		<infectious-disease risk="high">
			<food-or-waterborne>bacterial diarrhea, hepatitis A, and typhoid fever</food-or-waterborne>
			<vectorborne>dengue fever and malaria</vectorborne>
			<water-contact></water-contact>
		</infectious-disease>
		<drinking-water-source>[object Object]</drinking-water-source>
		<sanitation-access>[object Object]</sanitation-access>
		<nationality>
			<noun>Yemeni(s)</noun>
			<adjective>Yemeni</adjective>
		</nationality>
		<ethnic-groups>predominantly Arab; but also Afro-Arab, South Asians, Europeans</ethnic-groups>
		<religions>Muslim including Shaf'i (Sunni) and Zaydi (Shia), small numbers of Jewish, Christian, and Hindu</religions>
		<languages>Arabic (official)</languages>
		<literacy>
			<definition>age 15 and over can read and write</definition>
			<total unit="%">50.2</total>
			<male unit="%">70.5</male>
			<female unit="%">30</female>
		</literacy>
		<school-expectancy unit="years">9</school-expectancy>
		<education-expenditure unit="% of GDP">5.2</school-expectancy>
	</people>
	<government>
		<country-name>
			<long>Republic of Yemen</long>
			<short>Yemen</short>
		</country-name>
		<dependency></dependency>
		<government-type>republic</government-type>
		<capital>
			<name>Sanaa</name>
			<coordinates>15° 21' N, 44° 12' E</coordinates>
			<time-difference>UTC+3 (8 hours ahead of Washington, DC during Standard Time)</time-difference>
		</capital>
		<administrative-divisions>21 governorates (muhafazat, singular - muhafazah); Abyan, 'Adan (Aden), Ad Dali', Al Bayda', Al Hudaydah, Al Jawf, Al Mahrah, Al Mahwit, Amanat al 'Asimah, 'Amran, Dhamar, Hadramawt, Hajjah, Ibb, Lahij, Ma'rib, Raymah, Sa'dah, San'a' (Sanaa), Shabwah, Ta'izz</administrative-divisions>
		<independence>22 May 1990 (Republic of Yemen was established with the merger of the Yemen Arab Republic [Yemen (Sanaa) or North Yemen] and the Marxist-dominated People's Democratic Republic of Yemen [Yemen (Aden) or South Yemen]); note - previously North Yemen became independent in November 1918 (from the Ottoman Empire) and became a republic with the overthrow of the theocratic Imamate in 1962; South Yemen became independent on 30 November 1967 (from the UK)</independence>
		<national-holiday>Unification Day, 22 May (1990)</national-holiday>
		<legal-system>mixed legal system of Islamic law, English common law, and customary law</legal-system>
		<suffrage>18 years of age; universal</suffrage>
		<executive>
			<head-of-state>President Ali Abdallah SALIH (since 22 May 1990, the former president of North Yemen, assumed office upon the merger of North and South Yemen); Vice President Maj. Gen. Abd al-Rab Mansur HADI (since 3 October 1994)</head-of-state>
			<head-of-government>Prime Minister Ali Muhammad MUJAWWAR (since 31 March 2007)</head-of-government>
			<cabinet>Council of Ministers appointed by the president on the advice of the prime minister; note - President Ali Abdallah SALIH dimissed the Council of Ministers on 20 March 2011</cabinet>
			<elections>president elected by popular vote for a seven-year term; election last held on 20 September 2006 (next to be held in September 2013); vice president appointed by the president; prime minister and deputy prime ministers appointed by the president</elections>
			<election-results>Ali Abdallah SALIH elected president; percent of vote - Ali Abdallah SALIH 77.2%, Faysal BIN SHAMLAN 21.8%, other 1%</election-results>
		</executive>
		<legislative>
			<description>bicameral legislature consisting of a Shura Council (111 seats; members appointed by the president) and House of Representatives (301 seats; members elected by popular vote to serve eight-year terms)</description>
			<elections>last held on 27 April 2003 (scheduled April 2009 election postponed for two years)</elections>
			<election-results>percent of vote by party - NA; seats by party - GPC 238, Islah 47, YSP 6, Nasserite Unionist Party 3, National Arab Socialist Ba'th Party 2, independents 5</election-results>
		</legislative>
		<judicial>Supreme Court</judicial>
		<parties>General People's Congress or GPC [Abdul-Kader BAJAMMAL]; Islamic Reform Grouping or Islah [Muhammed Abdallah AL-YADUMI]; Nasserite Unionist Party [Abd al-Malik al-MAKHLAFI]; National Arab Socialist Ba'th Party [Dr. Qasim SALAM]; Yemeni Socialist Party or YSP [Yasin Said NU'MAN]; note - there are at least seven more active political parties</parties>
		<pressure-groups>TO DO</pressure-groups>
		<membership>AFESD, AMF, CAEU, FAO, G-77, IAEA, IBRD, ICAO, ICRM, IDA, IDB, IFAD, IFC, IFRCS, ILO, IMF, IMO, Interpol, IOC, IOM, IPU, ISO, ITSO, ITU, ITUC, LAS, MIGA, MINURSO, MONUSCO, NAM, OAS (observer), OIC, OPCW, UN, UNAMID, UNCTAD, UNESCO, UNHCR, UNIDO, UNMIL, UNMIS, UNOCI, UNWTO, UPU, WCO, WFTU, WHO, WIPO, WMO, WTO (observer)</membership>
		<representation-in-usa>
			<chief>Ambassador Abd al-Wahab Abdallah al-HAJRI</chief>
			<chancery>2319 Wyoming Avenue NW, Washington, DC 20008</chancery>
			<telephone>[1] (202) 965-4760</telephone>
			<FAX>[1] (202) 337-2017</FAX>
			<consulates></consulates>
		</representation-in-usa>
		<representation-from-usa>
			<chief>Ambassador Gerald M. FEIERSTEIN</chief>
			<embassy>Sa'awan Street, Sanaa</embassy>
			<mailing-address>P. O. Box 22347, Sanaa</mailing-address>
			<telephone>[967] (1) 755-2000 ext. 2153 or 2266</telephone>
			<FAX>[967] (1) 303-182</FAX>
		</representation-from-usa>
		<flag>[object Object]</flag>
		<anthem>
			<name>&quot;al-qumhuriyatu l-muttahida&quot; (United Republic)</name>
			<by>Abdullah Abdulwahab NOA'MAN/Ayyoab Tarish ABSI</by>
		</anthem>
	</government>
	<economy>
		<overview>Yemen is a low income country that is highly dependent on declining oil resources for revenue. Petroleum accounts for roughly 25% of GDP and 70% of government revenue. Yemen has tried to counter the effects of its declining oil resources by diversifying its economy through an economic reform program initiated in 2006 that is designed to bolster non-oil sectors of the economy and foreign investment. In October 2009, Yemen exported its first liquefied natural gas as part of this diversification effort. In January 2010, the international community established the Friends of Yemen group that aims to support Yemen's efforts towards economic and political reform, and in August 2010 the IMF approved a three-year $370 million program to further this effort. Despite these ambitious endeavors, Yemen continues to face difficult long term challenges, including declining water resources and a high population growth rate.</overview>
		<gdp>
			<purchasing-power-parity></purchasing-power-parity>
			<official-exchange-rate>31270000000</official-exchange-rate>
			<real-growth-rate unit="%">8</real-growth-rate>
			<per-capita></per-capita>
			<sector unit="%">
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
		</gdp>
		<labour>
			<force>6832000</force>
			<sector>
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
			<unemployment unit="%">35</unemployment>
		</labour>
		<poverty>[object Object]</poverty>
		<household-income>TO DO</household-income>
		<budget>
			<revenue unit="USD"></revenue>
			<expenditure unit="USD"></expenditure>
		</budget>
		<public-debt unit="% of GDP">39.1</public-debt>
		<consumer-inflation unit="%">12.2</consumer-inflation>
		<central-bank-discount-rate unit="%"></central-bank-discount-rate>
		<commercial-prime-lending-rate unit="%">18</commercial-prime-lending-rate>
		<narrow-money-stock unit="USD">3551000000</narrow-money-stock>
		<broad-money-stock unit="USD">9739000000</broad-money-stock>
		<domestic-credit-stock unit="USD">5297000000</domestic-credit-stock>
		<agriculture-products>grain, fruits, vegetables, pulses, qat, coffee, cotton; dairy products, livestock (sheep, goats, cattle, camels), poultry; fish</agriculture-products>
		<industries>crude oil production and petroleum refining; small-scale production of cotton textiles and leather goods; food processing; handicrafts; small aluminum products factory; cement; commercial ship repair; natural gas production</industries>
		<industrial-production-growth>[object Object]</industrial-production-growth>
		<electricity unit="kWh">
			<production>5665000000</production>
			<consumption>4133000000</consumption>
			<exports>0</exports>
			<imports>0</imports>
		</electricity>
		<oil>
			<production unit="bbl/day">288400</production>
			<consumption unit="bbl/day">155000</consumption>
			<exports unit="bbl/day">274400</exports>
			<imports unit="bbl/day">65860</imports>
			<reserves unit="bbl">3160000000</reserves>
		</oil>
		<natural-gas>
			<production unit="cu m">454700</production>
			<consumption unit="cu m">0</consumption>
			<exports unit="cu m">454700</exports>
			<imports unit="cu m">0</imports>
			<reserves unit="cu m">478500000000</reserves>
		</natural-gas>
		<exports>
			<total unit="USD"></total>
			<commodities>crude oil, coffee, dried and salted fish, liquefied natural gas</commodities>
			<partners>China 36%, Thailand 17.63%, India 13.54%, South Africa 6.16%, Japan 5.49%, UAE 4.99% (2009)</partners>
		</exports>
		<imports>
			<total unit="USD">8350000000</total>
			<commodities>food and live animals, machinery and equipment, chemicals</commodities>
			<partners>China 13.98%, UAE 12.3%, India 8.63%, Saudi Arabia 5.8%, US 4.52%, Brazil 4.51%, Turkey 4.51%, Kuwait 4.33%, France 4.24% (2009)</partners>
		</imports>
		<external-debt unit="USD">7147000000</external-debt>
		<exchange-rates>Yemeni rials (YER) per US dollar -</exchange-rates>
	</economy>
	<communications>
		<telephones>
			<assessment>since unification in 1990, efforts have been made to create a national telecommunications network</assessment>
			<domestic>the national network consists of microwave radio relay, cable, tropospheric scatter, GSM and CDMA mobile-cellular telephone systems; fixed-line and mobile-cellular teledensity remains low by regional standards</domestic>
			<international>country code - 967; landing point for the international submarine cable Fiber-Optic Link Around the Globe (FLAG); satellite earth stations - 3 Intelsat (2 Indian Ocean and 1 Atlantic Ocean), 1 Intersputnik (Atlantic Ocean region), and 2 Arabsat; microwave radio relay to Saudi Arabia and Djibouti</international>
			<land-lines>997000</land-lines>
			<mobile>8313000.000000001</mobile>
		</telephones>
		<broadcast>state-run TV with 2 stations; state-run radio with 2 national radio stations and 5 local stations; stations from Oman and Saudi Arabia can be accessed (2007)</broadcast>
		<internet>
			<tld>.ye</tld>
			<hosts>255</hosts>
			<users>2349000</users>
		</internet>
	</communications>
	<transport>
		<airports>
			<total>55</total>
			<paved>
				<altitude min="*" max="*"></altitude>
				<altitude min="3047m" max="*">4</altitude>
				<altitude min="2438m" max="3047m">9</altitude>
				<altitude min="1524m" max="2437m">3</altitude>
				<altitude min="914m" max="1524m">1</altitude>
				<altitude min="*" max="914m"></altitude>
			</paved>
		</airports>
		<ports-and-terminals>Aden, Al Hudaydah, Al Mukalla</ports-and-terminals>
	</transport>
	<military>
		<branches>Army, Navy (includes Marines), Yemen Air Force (Al Quwwat al Jawwiya al Jamahiriya al Yemeniya; includes Air Defense Force), Republican Guard (2010)</branches>
		<manpower>
			<population-available>
				<male>5652</male>
				<female>5387</female>
			</population-available>
			<fit-for-service>
				<male>4056</male>
				<female>4116</female>
			</fit-for-service>
			<reaching-maturity>
				<male>287141</male>
				<female>277612</female>
			</reaching-maturity>
			<notes>a Coast Guard was established in 2002</notes>
		</manpower>
	</military>
	<issues>
		<disputes>Saudi Arabia has reinforced its concrete-filled security barrier along sections of the fully demarcated border with Yemen to stem illegal cross-border activities</disputes>
		<drugs></drugs>
	</issues>
</country>